<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Productivity &#8211; teamfocus | project team management | web-based task management</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/productivity/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Workflows for teams</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 May 2017 14:01:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	
	<item>
		<title>24 Project Management Recruiters to Help You Hire in Australia</title>
		<link>/project-management-recruiters/</link>
					<comments>/project-management-recruiters/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 20:00:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Australia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5284</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you’re looking to change jobs or find an employee in Australia, here are 24 project management recruiters who can make your search easier.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Even if you have the best processes and smoothest workflows, your company will struggle if you hire someone who is a bad fit. This can frustrate your current employees and slow down project performance as a whole. </p>
<p>Getting the fit right is the real value that recruiters deliver. </p>
<p>The best recruiters are able to evaluate a company’s culture — and even a particular department’s culture — to suggest candidates who would perform well in that environment. When done well, both company and new employee will enjoy several years working together.</p>
<p>Here in Australia, we’re fortunate to have talented people and the top recruiters to find them. If you’re looking to change jobs or find an employee to fill a project management role, here are 24 recruiters who can make your search easier. </p>
<h2>Matthew Bown</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/matthew-bown-63a88413/">Matthew Bown</a> is an executive recruiter at Ethos BeathChapman in Sydney, where he’s worked for the past 10 years. Bown specializes in business transformation and change management, specifically within the banking and financial services industries. Ethos BeathChapman is known for executive recruitment, making it an ideal company to work with for finding high-level placements.</p>
<h2>Ken Boots</h2>
<p>With more than 10 years in the recruitment industry, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/talentsourcer/">Ken Boots</a> has an impressive track record. He boasts a 94 percent success rate with recruits with 85 percent retained after three years. He specializes in federal and state government positions, executive sales recruitment, and hard-to-fill technical roles.</p>
<h2>Terry Lawson</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/telawson/">Terry Lawson</a> is a senior IT recruiter for both contract and permanent positions. He specializes in software and infrastructure staff, including infrastructure managers, IT project teams and business analysts. His deep knowledge of IT processes helps him find and vet top candidates.</p>
<h2>Rochelle Taylor</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rochelle-taylor-535a713/">Rochelle Taylor</a> is a senior IT recruiter based in Sydney. She has more than 19 years of experience and works to fill junior and senior positions within IT departments. She works to keep an eye on the overall technology market in Australia, not just her clients, so she can anticipate changes and future trends. </p>
<h2>Jane Pingo</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/janepingo/">Jane Pingo</a>, based in Melbourne, has more than 25 years of experience recruiting for top companies in the area. Her specialties include change management, leadership development and succession planning. Pingo is an associate member of the Career Development Association of Australia (CDAA), which works to help people make informed career decisions. </p>
<h2>Kristy Coulter</h2>
<p>As a senior recruiter for Hudson Global Resources since 2004, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kristycoulter1/">Kristy Coulter</a> works closely to fill vacancies in the ICT industry. She mostly works with business analysts, project managers and organizational change managers. He network stretches across Brisbane, the Sunshine Coast and the Gold Coast.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/melbourne.jpg" alt="melbourne" width="798" height="531" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5290" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/melbourne.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/05/melbourne-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/05/melbourne-768x511.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/05/melbourne-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>Kathy Santamaria</h2>
<p>While <a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kathy-santamaria-439680117/">Kathy Santamaria</a> has three years of technical recruitment experience, she has also worked as a project manager and is familiar with the demands of the field. She primarily works to fill positions for IT administrators and software engineers. She’s based in Sydney.</p>
<h2>Grant Lynn</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/grantlynn/">Grant Lynn</a> has more than 10 years of experience in the Sydney IT industry and currently works with Thornhill Recruitment. Thornhill specializes in recruitment for project management, business analysis, support and development positions. He works to fill both contract and permanent positions.</p>
<h2>Sumeet Kaur</h2>
<p>Also based in Sydney, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/recruitersumeetsydney/">Sumeet Kaur</a> is a recruitment specialist in project management and business analysis. She is a candidate manager for Greythorn Australia, a firm that has specialized in IT placement and recruiting for the past 30 years.</p>
<h2>John Watt</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/johnwattsydney/">John Watt</a> has worked at About Recruitment for almost 11 years and specifically works with IT and management recruitment. He and his colleagues work with the finance, engineering, legal and insurance industries to fill technical positions. Previously, he worked as a marketing manager at Microsoft and as a business development manager at Exact Software.  </p>
<h2>Michelle Cheong</h2>
<p>Living in Brisbane, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/michellecheongrecruit/">Michelle Cheong</a> has been working to showcase and improve her recruitment skills since 2012. She currently works at Humanised Group (formally known as Just People) to pair business developers, account managers and partner managers with employers. She is also involved in the local WiT (Women in Technology) chapter. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/brisbane.jpg" alt="brisbane" width="798" height="531" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5287" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/brisbane.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/05/brisbane-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/05/brisbane-768x511.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/05/brisbane-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>Jareth Oades-Gularte</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jarethoadesgularte/">Jareth Oades-Gularte</a>, who also works at the Humanised Group in Brisbane, has worked in recruiting since 2010. He has since grown his experience and now scouts the top five percent of talent in the area to fill top technology positions. One of his goals to grow professionally in 2017 includes working with help desk managers and systems/DevOps engineers to increase their networking opportunities.  </p>
<h2>Chris Garibaldi</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/chrisgaribaldi/">Chris Garibaldi</a> is the director of GRIT Talent Consulting in Brisbane, a technology recruitment boutique that boasts personal communication and service. While he is new to GRIT, Garibaldi has several years of recruiting experience and has built a large network across southeast Queensland.</p>
<h2>Michael Cant </h2>
<p>As a recruiter and director at Binary People, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/michaelcant/">Michael Cant</a> works closely with the Brisbane tech sector. He’s passionate about the startup revolution hitting Australia and loves working with companies to find the right fit to continue growing or sustaining their business within the community. </p>
<h2>Raphaël Laffitte</h2>
<p>Located in Sydney, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/raphaellaffitte/">Raphaël Laffitte</a> is a technical recruiter at Just Digital People who recently moved to the area from Paris. His recruitment specialty is software engineering along with DevOps, deployment leads and architecture professionals. He works closely with the digital industry to find the right fit for his clients.</p>
<h2>Joel Stein</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joelstein/">Joel Stein</a> is the team manager and principal recruiter at Precision Sourcing in Sydney. He and his group specialize in finding candidates to fill business intelligence, digital and project management roles. He considers himself a specialist in the analytics market in Australia and can comfortably fill technical and complex positions.</p>
<h2>Max Kelly</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/max-kelly-specialist-risk-compliance-recruiter-b0433571/">Max Kelly</a> is an audit, risk and compliance recruiter at T+O+M Executive in Sydney. T+O+M works closely to fill project and change management roles, accounting positions, and strategy roles. Kelly has worked there for four years and has nine years of professional experience in total. </p>
<h2>Garry Wylie</h2>
<p>For the past six years, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/garry-wylie-a784a421/">Garry Wylie</a> has worked at Wise Recruitment in Sydney, even though he has worked with clients and companies on a national level. He identifies the best people for highly technical roles and moves quickly to bring them in for interviews. The goal is to reduce the time companies have in an empty position so they can increase their productivity.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/candidates.jpg" alt="candidates" width="798" height="531" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5288" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/candidates.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/05/candidates-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/05/candidates-768x511.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/05/candidates-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>Jim Cooper</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jimcoopersedgman/">Jim Cooper</a> has worked with KBR, Inc. for a little more than a year, but he has several years of experience as a consultant, business development manager and recruiter. KBR, Inc. works to fill employees in engineering and project staff with an emphasis on technology, engineering and government services. </p>
<h2>Sarah Goldberg</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sarah-goldberg-a2a70026/">Sarah Goldberg</a> is an executive director and senior IT recruiter at Allegro Recruitment Consulting in Melbourne. She has worked with the company for more than 10 years to fill infrastructure and application roles including project management, team leaderships and network integration. Allegro is an international recruiting company with offices in the US, UK, Europe and Asia. </p>
<h2>Scott Harrison</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/scottharrison25/">Scott Harrison</a> has multiple years of experience in the global recruiting market. He has also worked as a business development manager with multiple software companies to find people to lead design and development projects. This gives him a tech speciality with business acumen. He works at Firebrand Talent and lives in Melbourne.  </p>
<h2>Rob Staples</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rob-staples-3468b613/">Rob Staples</a> is a senior account manager at First Advantage, and also has experience as a recruitment consultant for business transformation and change management at Ethos BeathChapman. He has a decade of experience in the recruiting field and has a passion for working closely with businesses to understand their goals and needs.</p>
<h2>Carrie Fitzpatrick</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/carriefitzpatrick/">Carrie Fitzpatrick</a> also works at Ethos BeathChapman to find project managers, technical architect, and systems analysts. She lives in Sydney and has worked with the company for eight years. She specializes in interim management and executive contracting for companies that need temporary replacements.</p>
<h2>Luda Collins</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/luda-collins-sobutska-989b504a/">Luda Collins</a> is originally from Ukraine and has lived in Sydney for a little more than two years. She has more than six years of recruiting experience and has a passion for the tech sector. She loves working with smart people to find a role they’re passionate about so they’re excited to go to work every day. </p>
<p><small><em>images by: ©stockbroker/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a target="_blank" href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/tpsdave-12019/"><em>tpsdave</em></a><em>, </em><a target="_blank" href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/davodlbnn-3459603/"><em>davodlbnn</em></a><em>, ©pressmaster/123RF Stock Photo</em></small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/project-management-recruiters/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Distributed Down Under: 13 Australian Companies That Get Remote Teamwork</title>
		<link>/australian-companies/</link>
					<comments>/australian-companies/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 13:00:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5279</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you are struggling to understand how to manage a remote team, look to these 13 Australian companies for examples of best practices.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most companies in Australia struggle to integrate their <a href="https://www.teamfocus.me/hire-remote-employees/" >remote employees</a> into company operations and workflows.</p>
<p>It’s not that they fail to grasp the benefits of telecommuting, nor are they stuck in the mindset that employee productivity is measured by time spent in the office.</p>
<p>According to the team at <a href="http://www.launchgroup.com.au/2016/03/02/australian-management-not-equipped-to-deal-with-remote-workers/" >Launch Group</a>, the sticking point most companies have is actually understanding how to manage their remote team members. Less than half of Australian businesses offer senior management any special training in supervising distributed teams, Launch Group says, citing research from Regus. </p>
<p>Still, several companies in Australia have solved this onboarding problem — and some are growing rapidly thanks to their distributed teams.</p>
<p>The 13 companies below are ahead of the curve. If your company is struggling to understand how to manage a remote team, look to them for examples of best practices.</p>
<p></p>
<h2>X-Team</h2>
<p><a href="https://x-team.com/" >X-Team</a> brings together ad hoc teams of full-time developers for any clients who need to have software built. By being totally distributed, the company has the flexibility to scale its dev teams up or down to whatever the client’s needs are.</p>
<p>CEO Ryan Chartrand frequently writes on the X-Team blog about the challenges of leading such a company. One tip, he says, is to break the ice among team members by having each person host a Q&amp;A chat on Slack. </p>
<p>“For example, we do AMAs in our #travel channel whenever someone gets back from a nomading trip to another country,” he writes. “&#8230; It allows people an opportunity to learn something new from someone with hands-on experience and/or a ton of passion around the topic.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>Red Guava</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.redguava.com.au/" >Red Guava</a> is the company that built Cliniko, a healthcare practice management system that clinics and hospitals in 55 different countries are currently using.</p>
<p>The company’s apparent secret to success is pretty straightforward, too: Focus on people. Not in a sterile, “people-centric outlook” kind of way, but in a way that demonstrates real compassion. </p>
<p>For example, one of Cliniko’s killer features is its support community, which includes an active forum plus responsive phone and email communication. And internally, the company extends that same kind of compassion to its team: Standard terms of employment include full-time pay for a 30-hour workweek.</p>
<p></p>
<h2>Envato</h2>
<p><a href="https://envato.com/" >Envato</a> is one of Australia’s great success stories. Millions of people tap this marketplace for creative work — website building, software development, graphic design, etc. — every year.</p>
<p>As with Red Guava above, Envato’s growth is built on a pretty simple premise: “We believe good ideas deserve a chance to grow. We believe people deserve to earn a living doing what they love. We believe in making it easy to get things done.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>WP Curve</h2>
<p><a href="https://wpcurve.com/" >WP Curve</a>, which announced it was joining GoDaddy at the end of 2016, has been one of the Internet’s go-to providers for WordPress help for a few years. Note that WordPress powers about a quarter of all websites, which is why WP Curve’s team is handling more than 4,000 jobs per month.</p>
<p>And like X-Team, WP Curve has employees all over the map. That flexibility allows the company to offer 24-7 support to WordPress users, no matter the time zone.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/workspace-1024x682.jpg" alt="workspace" width="1024" height="682" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5282" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/workspace-1024x682.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/workspace-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/workspace-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/workspace-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/workspace.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>SuiteBox</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.suitebox.com/" >SuiteBox</a>’s entire offering is built on remote workflows. The company has patented a handful of tools and processes so that its clients can conclude deals remotely. This includes group video conferencing, document collaboration and even legal digital signatures.</p>
<p>Banks, financial firms and insurance companies especially have adopted SuiteBox because no longer having to meet clients on site lets them scale their operations exponentially. </p>
<p></p>
<h2>Campaign Monitor</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.campaignmonitor.com/" >Campaign Monitor</a> is actually better-known for being one of Australia’s best places to work. The email marketing provider — which turned heads a few years ago by closing a quarter-billion-dollar funding round — does leave room for remote roles among its team members, though.</p>
<p>The perks there are nice, too: Remote employees receive an additional allowance, a brand new Macbook Air, and ample flex and holiday time so they can find the work/life balance that best suits them.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most important lesson we can learn from Campaign Monitor’s success is the importance of values. These lay the foundation for company culture, which like everything else has to be strong enough to scale rapidly at a tech company, <a href="https://www.virgin.com/entrepreneur/difference-between-culture-and-values" >CEO Alex Bard</a> says. </p>
<p>Having that kind of values focus changes the discussion. It’s no longer about where an employee is located — the office or elsewhere — but whether you have in place “the framework on which to base key decisions like hiring talent into new offices.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>Appen</h2>
<p><a href="http://appen.com/" >Appen</a> is one of the veterans on this list. Founded in Sydney in 1996, Appen was building out linguistic technologies long before <a href="http://a16z.com/2016/08/20/why-software-is-eating-the-world/" >software began to eat the world</a>. In those 21 years, Appen has navigated a company merger and a name change, and it has partnered with some of the biggest names in technology.</p>
<p>For example, in 2010 after the Haitian earthquake Appen worked with Microsoft to build machine translation tools so disaster relief teams could understand Haitian Creole.</p>
<p></p>
<h2>Canva</h2>
<p><a href="https://about.canva.com/" >Canva</a> is among the best-known and fastest-growing startups in Australia. As at Campaign Monitor, Canva’s executive team understood that a tech startup needs to be flexible with its employees to scale at the speed it’s built for. That’s why employees are given the option to work from home as much as they need to.</p>
<p>“We know people work best when they’re happy and challenged to keep getting even better at what they do,” the company says. “So at Canva, we look after our team.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>INCSUB</h2>
<p><a href="https://incsub.com/" >INCSUB</a>, short for “Incorporated Subversion,” builds some of the most-used blogging tools for WordPress users. The company’s headquarters are in Melbourne, but its team is located all over the world. In fact, the company says just about every time zone in the world is represented on its team.</p>
<p>This policy, the company says, means it can recruit the best and brightest from anywhere. The company also puts a special emphasis on diversity because providing equal opportunity employment to all applicants makes the company better.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/remote-employee-1024x660.jpg" alt="working online from home" width="1024" height="660" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5280" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/remote-employee-1024x660.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/remote-employee-300x193.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/remote-employee-768x495.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/remote-employee-600x387.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/remote-employee.jpg 1706w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Quiip</h2>
<p><a href="http://quiip.com.au/" >Quiip</a> provides online community management for companies around the world, who hire Quiip to moderate forums, update social feeds and respond to blog comments, among other things.</p>
<p>This means there is a 24-7 demand for what Quiip’s team does.</p>
<p>To meet that demand, the company has a policy of what it calls radical flexibility: “The notion of the 40 (or 60) hour week is a legacy of the long-gone days of industry and we can do better. Why not create jobs that are 10/20/30 hours a week. Not job-share, not part-time, just simply a role in itself that suits the employee.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>CloudPeeps</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.cloudpeeps.com/" >CloudPeeps</a> — which makes the list by having an Australian founder, though the company is based in San Francisco — is a marketplace for freelancers and service providers. These professionals are vetted and then connected with clients for specific projects.</p>
<p>Founder and CEO Kate Kendall was herself a freelancer before she launched the company in 2015. Kendall spoke with <a href="https://remote.co/company/cloudpeeps/" >Remote.co</a> at the time to discuss the challenges of building relationships on a distributed team:</p>
<p>“We place a strong emphasis on transparency, authenticity and being direct. We do monthly one-on-one feedback sessions, which we call ‘pair calls,’ where we run through challenges, positive feedback and constructive areas to improve. These are non-hierarchical where openness and honesty is encouraged. It doesn’t matter if you’re the CEO or the newest member of the team — we share how you can improve coming from a kind place.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>Fifty Acres</h2>
<p><a href="http://fiftyacres.com.au/" >Fifty Acres</a> is the first virtual communications and government agency in Australia. The agency’s principal, Jo Scard, says she baked remote work flexibility into the foundation of her company because the rigidity of a 9-to-5 schedule excluded so many working mothers.</p>
<p>“We don’t need an office,” Scard tells <a href="https://www.myob.com/au/blog/remote-working-made-these-3-companies-successful/" >Nina Sochon</a> (a New Zealand-based consultant who has built a career by teaching company leaders how to help their remote teams thrive — the very weak spot SMEs identified in the Regus research). </p>
<p>“&#8230; As a result we can avoid passing on office costs to our clients, which has helped to keep our charges down.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>Jobvibe</h2>
<p><a href="http://jobvibe.me/" >Jobvibe</a> is another Australian company that builds remote working into the core of its offering. </p>
<p>Jobvibe’s software lets teams share feedback in real time so that companies can establish a culture of transparency and trust, even if team members don’t share an office or time zone.</p>
<p>While the company’s headquarters are in Sydney, it relies on a network of contractors around the world build out and scale up the business. The secret to making that structure work? Trust.</p>
<p>“Everyone is treated as an adult, so we work from home from time to time, and we don&#8217;t care so much about when you start or finish,” the company says. “It&#8217;s about getting the job done.”</p>
<p>
<em><small>images by: ©verbaska/123RF Stock Photo, <a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/TheDigitalWay-3008341/" >TheDigitalWay</a>, <a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/350543-350543/" >350543</a></small></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/australian-companies/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>5 Types of Meetings (And How to Make Your Employees Love Them)</title>
		<link>/types-of-meetings/</link>
					<comments>/types-of-meetings/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 11:06:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5270</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[These are the 5 types of meetings you frequently encounter in the workplace, and how an effective leader can get the most out of them.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most organizations have a love-hate relationships with meetings. Some companies ban meetings at certain times or days, while others feel like more meetings will solve all of their problems. </p>
<p>However, the meeting length and frequency isn’t nearly as important as the meeting content.</p>
<p>To make your meetings more productive — and to improve the happiness of employees who sit through them — we’ve created a guide to the five types of meetings you encounter in the workspace, and how you can make the most of them.</p>
<h2>1. Status Updates and Check-Ins</h2>
<p>Every company has these meetings on a regular basis, from daily scrums to end-of-week reviews. While they’re often appreciated by employees, they can get out of hand.</p>
<p>“The stand-up became enormously popular as a core practice of software teams using an agile development methodology,” <a target="_blank" href="http://blog.lucidmeetings.com/blog/4-ways-status-meetings-remote-team-that-work">Elise Keith</a> writes at Lucid Meetings. “Since then, it’s gained many names (daily Scrum, daily meeting) and spread to other departments, who liked the fast, energetic pace.” </p>
<p>Update meetings should last no more than 15-minutes for daily scrum reviews, and no more than an hour for weekly or monthly check-ins. Anything longer, and you’ve lost your audience.</p>
<p>“Since the time is short, the team members should know exactly what they would speak at the meeting,” <a target="_blank" href="http://www.scrum-institute.org/blog/10-Tips-To-Get-The-Best-Out-Of-Your-Daily-Scrum-Meetings">Nirav Patel</a> writes at The Scrum Institute. “Their speech should be strictly limited to what they did the day before, what they plan to do today and what are the difficulties they are facing in meeting their goals. </p>
<p>“For this, the scrum leader should make it clear to the team members what he expects to hear from them at the meeting. Anything off the topic should be immediately interrupted.” </p>
<p>Furthermore, not all problems need to be solved in one specific meeting. Place items that require more time or discussion in the “parking lot,” and address them at a later time or during a one-on-one with those involved. </p>
<p>“The purpose of [these] meetings is to provide information,” <a target="_blank" href="https://www.hrbartender.com/2015/training/the-only-3-reasons-to-hold-a-business-meeting/">Sharlyn Lauby</a> writes as HR Bartender. “The reason they’re so dreaded is because, when there’s nothing to convey, the meeting still happens.” </p>
<p>Almost all employees have languished through a pointless meeting with no updates, praying it ends early. Conversely, other teams have scheduled meetings, but continue to cancel them every week to the point where they’re completely forgotten. The key to these update meetings is to make sure actual news is shared, or they should be held less often.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/startup.jpg" alt="startup" width="798" height="531" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5275" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/startup.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/startup-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/startup-768x511.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/startup-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>2. Decision-Making Meetings</h2>
<p>Decision meetings tend to be the most heated within the company. Representatives from multiple departments want to make sure they’re heard and the company moves in the best interest of their team. </p>
<p>“For continuity, it’s helpful to tie all discussions back to your broader strategic goals,” <a target="_blank" href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/272078">David Chait</a> writes at Entrepreneur. “There are many ways to do this, but a dead simple one is to simply start your regular team meetings by posting or quickly running through those goals.”</p>
<p>This ensures that all decisions made by the assembled team will be in the best interest of the company, even if certain members are inconvenienced. </p>
<p>After the goals, the moderator should explain the process for finding a solution. By explaining this before the debate begins, employees can understand how everyone came to a solution at the end. </p>
<p>“Some decisions may call for unanimous agreement, while others may best be done as a decision by the owner,” <a target="_blank" href="http://www.quickanddirtytips.com/productivity/meetings/how-to-run-a-decision-making-meeting?page=1">Stever Robbins</a> writes at Quick and Dirty Tips. “When people agree on process first, then even if that process chooses an option some people don&#8217;t like, they&#8217;ll usually agree to abide by the decision.” If people are unaware that the manager can override them at anytime, they could feel suppressed when the meeting comes to an abrupt end. </p>
<p>By explaining the process and goals, the team moderator is able to reduce friction when people disagree on certain decisions. </p>
<p>“One of the most important aspects of decision meetings is to create unity around the decision that is created,” writes the team at <a target="_blank" href="http://meetingsift.com/decision-making-meetings/">Meeting Sift</a>. “When each participant feels their opinion has been fully considered as part of the decision making process they are more likely to feel ownership of the decision, even in cases when it is not the outcome they hoped for.”</p>
<p>By following these rules, and making sure every employee is listened to and treated with respect, managers can ensure decision-making meetings stay professional and productive. </p>
<h2>3. Creative Planning and Brainstorming Sessions</h2>
<p>On the opposite end of the decision spectrum is the creative brainstorming sessions, which tend to go long because employees are distracted and having fun.</p>
<p>“Meetings want to suck,” <a target="_blank" href="https://heleo.com/jake-knapp-brainstorming-hurting-meetings-success/5789/">Jake Knapp</a> writes at Heleo. “Two of their favorite suckiness tactics are group brainstorming and group negotiation. Give them half a chance, and they’ll waste your time, sap your energy, and leave you with poor ideas and a watered-down decision. But meetings don’t have to be that way.”</p>
<p>Despite their power to hijack an afternoon, many amazing concepts and solutions come from these meetings. </p>
<p>“The ability to contribute to a shared vision is the magic behind those 2 a.m. breakthroughs that are part of every startup story,” Veer Gidwaney of <a target="_blank" href="http://www.inc.com/veer-gidwaney/how-to-hold-a-weekly-team-meeting-without-wasting-people-s-time.html">Maxwell Health</a> writes at Inc. “The human collective is much more creative than one person working alone, because employees&#8217; individual experiences bump up against one another, forming new associations and revealing intriguing possibilities.”</p>
<p>By adding structure to your meeting, whether you’re brainstorming a client solution or planning a fundraiser, you should be able to stay on task and leave with actionable ideas. </p>
<p>“A lot of creatives are quick on their feet and love to spitball ideas,” <a target="_blank" href="http://www.unseminary.com/9-elements-of-effective-creative-brainstorm-meetings/">Rich Birch</a> writes at Unseminary. “But not every creative person is wired this way. Not everyone develops their best ideas in the midst of a brainstorming meeting. Some people thrive with time and thought. Communicate the scope of the discussion beforehand to aid folks who like to mull over ideas.”</p>
<p>This also allows your team to conduct research beforehand about the topic, so they’re better informed when coming up with ideas. </p>
<p>“It&#8217;s [the] moderator&#8217;s duty to note down all the ideas on a whiteboard or anything else as per the convenience and discuss them with the participants,” Bhupendra Sharma writes at <a target="_blank" href="https://yourstory.com/2016/09/successful-brainstorming-session/">YourStory</a>. “For this, a brainstorming session can be divided into two or more sub-sessions. While the first half can be dedicated to the idea-sharing activity, the other half can be devoted to discussing the pros and cons of those ideas.”</p>
<p>Not only does this limit segues that take the discussion off track, but it also lets teams return to past ideas and use them at a different time without needing to call a fresh meeting. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/laptop.jpg" alt="laptop" width="798" height="531" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5274" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/laptop.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/laptop-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/laptop-768x511.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/laptop-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>4. Collaborative and Planning Meetings</h2>
<p>Collaborative meetings are becoming more popular as a way to kick off a project and make sure it has the appropriate follow-through. </p>
<p>“39% of employees surveyed in a recent study felt that people within their organizations did not collaborate enough, while 86% of executives and employees cite lack of collaboration or ineffective communication for workplace failures,” <a target="_blank" href="http://www.wespire.com/8-steps-to-improve-workplace-collaboration/">Elliot Gordon</a> writes at WeSpire. </p>
<p>“The core benefit of collaboration is the ability to share knowledge and expertise quickly and easily, and this sharing leads to better products and innovations, which in turn drives better profitability, employee engagement, and employee satisfaction.”</p>
<p>These meetings often work to map out a strategy, decide on certain elements, and assign tasks to complete afterward. The challenge of these meetings is that they can be dense and overwhelming to attendees who struggle to keep up. </p>
<p>“Social scientists are discovering evidence that the human brain is wired to pay attention and absorb information for 10 to 18 minutes before it begins to tune out,” Ade at the <a target="_blank" href="https://jell.com/blog/productive-meetings-science/">Jell</a> blog writes. “The more information an audience is asked to consume, the more intense the mental load becomes. Eventually this ‘cognitive backlog’ becomes so heavy that listeners drop it all and fail to remember anything at all.” </p>
<p>Consider that next time you try to map out an entire project in one sitting. Before your attendees arrive at the meeting, send out an agenda of what will be covered and when. This way, your team comes prepared and knows what to expect. </p>
<p>“Looking at your agenda will give you a rough idea of how much time you can afford to devote to each item, because time is an important element of team meetings,” <a target="_blank" href="http://recruitloop.com/blog/5-steps-to-running-an-effective-team-meeting/">Paul Slezak</a> writes at RecruitLoop. “They should start on time and only go for the allotted time. If some items on the agenda require more time than is available, they should be moved to the next meeting or, if urgent, a separate meeting should be held with those immediately involved.” </p>
<p>In some cases, the actual task assigned at the completion of the agenda item might be for two or three people to meet individually to come up with a plan or make a decision. </p>
<p>“In general, meetings and obligations tend to fill the space you give them,” <a target="_blank" href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/281131">Cameron Herold</a> writes at Entrepreneur. “Estimate how long you think a meeting or task will take, then cut it in half. By limiting time, you increase your productivity, maximize efficiency and create a more highly profitable system of time management.”</p>
<p>If you schedule an hour-long meeting with only 30-minutes of content to cover, then your meeting will still last an hour. Try to limit the time to what is absolutely necessary, so your team can focus on doing instead of just planning. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/training.jpg" alt="training" width="798" height="531" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5276" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/training.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/training-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/training-768x511.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/training-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>5. Training and Professional Improvement Hours</h2>
<p>The last type of meeting doesn’t directly impact the sales and revenue of a company, but it can improve the company in the long run. These sessions typically involve one or two presenters working with a handful of employees. While these meetings aren’t stressful, they can get boring if the subject isn’t relevant. </p>
<p>“Let employees choose training topics,” <a target="_blank" href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/larry-alton/stop-neglecting-employee-_b_8954736.html">Larry Alton</a> writes at the Huffington Post. “Nobody knows your employees better than themselves. Using our IT example, an employee struggling with a particular security solution has incentive to take a class on this topic because they know that it’s an opportunity to get better at their job and continue advancement.” </p>
<p>This also ensures the training will be relevant and fresh, and training meetings won’t go unattended after the first few sessions.</p>
<p>“Employees who don’t love learning can make your training sessions a nightmare,” <a target="_blank" href="https://smallbiztrends.com/2015/06/small-business-training-new-employees.html">Drew Hendricks</a> writes at SmallBizTrends. “If you want successful trainings, begin by encouraging self-motivation and a love of learning.” </p>
<p>These benefits will extend beyond training meetings. Self-motivated employees can work by themselves and will research new ideas and possibilities before they come to you with a problem. This takes the burden off of you as a manager to constantly put out their fires. </p>
<p>“Employee training shouldn’t just be based on acquiring specific knowledge for a position,” <a target="_blank" href="http://www.polleverywhere.com/blog/train-to-retain-7-tips-for-better-employee-training/">Heather Huhman</a> writes at Poll Everywhere. “Focus training efforts on building an understanding the company mission, organizational culture, values, and goals. Through this specific training, employees will garner a greater understanding, interest, and respect for company culture, allowing them to better utilize it on a day-to-day basis.” </p>
<p>This gives them a sense of purpose by showing them where the company is going (and how they can help achieve it) while instilling a sense of importance and value in their work — which turns into loyalty. </p>
<p>With this information, you can ensure that your employees approach every meeting confident that they will accomplish their goals without leaving drained, ignored, or bored. You’re proving that their time is valuable, and that you value what they do throughout the day. Soon your whole office — not just your meetings — will be buzzing with efficiency. </p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
<em>©goodluz/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a target="_blank" href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/StartupStockPhotos-690514/"><em>StartupStockPhotos</em></a><em>, </em><a target="_blank" href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/jamesoladujoye-3409212/"><em>jamesoladujoye</em></a><em>, ©rawpixel/123RF Stock Photo</em><br />
</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/types-of-meetings/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Executive Pitch: How to Make Management Love Your Idea</title>
		<link>/executive-pitch/</link>
					<comments>/executive-pitch/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 06:00:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Entrepreneurship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marketing]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5261</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here’s how you can make a successful executive pitch to upper management and get them to say yes to and get behind your ideas.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The key to growth is change and the introduction of new ideas. </p>
<p>From a department perspective, your team needs to grow if you’re going to hit your goals for the year and keep the company moving. </p>
<p>From a professional perspective, you need to grow within the company by leading new ideas and projects. </p>
<p>All of this growth can easily be stopped by one group of people: management. Executives and managers hold the keys to unlocking new ideas through additional budget and resources. In order to get those resources, you need to get their buy-in. </p>
<p>Here’s how you can successfully pitch upper management and get them to say yes to your ideas, projects and changes so you can continue to grow the company while improving yourself professionally. </p>
<h2>Understand Where Management is Coming From</h2>
<p>In the same way that sales teams research prospective clients before making a call, you need to understand where management is coming from in order to successfully tailor your pitch. </p>
<p>“It is an executive’s duty to define and defend a strategic agenda — a small set of initiatives that will keep the organization competitive and relevant,” <a href="http://fortune.com/2015/10/04/pitching-an-idea-to-your-boss/" target="_blank">Liz Wiseman</a>, author of Rookie Smarts, writes at Forbes. “So if you want support for a new idea, instead of trying to add your stuff onto the the agenda of an executive, show how your ideas will further their already-set agenda. In other words, to get buy in, you have to make the tie-in.”</p>
<p>Listen to town hall meetings and take note of what needs to be improved this quarter, or what your management team keeps talking about. Using these buzzwords in your presentation turns your idea from additional work that adds to their burden to a solution to help them achieve company goals more efficiently. </p>
<p>“Presenting to a C-suite executive or senior manager, especially when you’re entry-level or somewhere in the middle, requires a different set of skills compared to run-of-the-mill speaking presentations,” <a href="https://www.themuse.com/advice/how-to-successfully-present-to-a-higherup-at-work-without-freaking-out" target="_blank">Jo Miller</a> writes at The Muse. “Because the roles of these high-level staff are quite different than the mid-level managers you may be used to working with, their objectives, communication styles, and decision-making methods are going to be distinct as well.”</p>
<p>Take note of how they voice their concerns and how they listen to others. This will allow you to mimic how they want to be addressed so you can use verbiage that makes sense to them. </p>
<p>Remember, while you’re up against people who hear ideas throughout the day, their job isn’t to say no. It’s to decide how to achieve their goals in the best way possible. </p>
<p>“By their nature, CEOs are typically entrepreneurs with an appetite for disrupting the current state of a given industry,” <a href="http://www.chiefmarketer.com/selling-an-idea-to-the-c-suite-a-cmos-guide/" target="_blank">Ben Plomion</a> writes at Chief Marketer. “This enthusiasm for the novel and new is tempered by the CEO’s interest in marketing ideas that align with their specific vision of the company. &#8230; Pro tip: You’ll know you’ve succeeded when a CEO claims your idea as their own, without attribution or irony.”</p>
<h2>Beta Test Your Idea Before Making the Pitch</h2>
<p>A few days before you make your pitch, start training to go into battle. Grab a few co-workers and run through the process with them. You might even want to talk with middle managers and people in other departments to get their perspectives. </p>
<p>“You’re likely surrounded by a great resource to prepare for an interrogation of your idea,” <a href="http://www.makeuseof.com/tag/5-tips-help-make-perfect-pitch-boss-team/" target="_blank">Brad Jones</a> writes at MakeUseOf. “If you’re pitching at work, who better to call upon for insight than your co-workers? They have the experience to clue you into any failings of your pitch, thus tapping that knowledge is in your best interests.”</p>
<p>Make sure your peers aren’t holding back. After all, these are all questions you’re going to face in front of the C-suite, so you can use the practice fielding them in front of well-meaning co-workers.</p>
<p>“Embrace the naysayers,” <a href="http://www.inc.com/daily-muse/how-to-convince-your-company-to-change.html" target="_blank">Amanda Berlin</a> writes at Inc. “If your idea isn’t an immediate winner among your colleagues, don’t just write them off as dream-stompers who fear change. Listen to their perspectives, and use their objections to strengthen your idea. Their reservations may point to holes in your plan.” </p>
<p>The more they’re able to tear apart your plan, the more you’re able to tweak it until you create something that will work. Eventually, you will have an answer (and solution) for almost anything. </p>
<p>Furthermore, even if your CEO accepts the idea, you might want to invite opponents of your idea to your meeting, if only to show that you’ve thought of everything.  </p>
<p>“Your pitch to them needs to reflect their own nature, level of risk aversion, and their trust in you based on past relationships,” Kairos CEO <a href="https://www.kairos.com/blog/142-how-to-sell-innovation-within-your-organization" target="_blank">Brian Brackeen</a> explains. “Make certain that you have invited every relevant stakeholder to your presentation. This includes anybody who you know will clearly argue against your innovation. If they make a drama, it is more likely to get your idea noticed, and you hopefully will be able to provide counter-arguments to their attacks.”</p>
<p>Another benefit of bringing in these parties is that your CEO can give the final word and prevent future pushback. If he or she is on board, then co-workers who are against the plan aren’t easily able to go against it.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/collaborate-1024x683.jpg" alt="collaborate" width="1024" height="683" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5265" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/collaborate-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/02/collaborate-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/02/collaborate-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/02/collaborate-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/02/collaborate.jpg 1680w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Assemble a Team to Help Your Cause</h2>
<p>Along with the executive suite and your detractors, who else should be in your pitch meeting? Before you enter the room, you should have a crack team of supporters willing to add their pull and contribute to the project’s execution. </p>
<p>“If your idea is interesting and possibly beneficial, it shouldn’t be hard to get a co-worker or two to also want to try the new thing,” <a href="http://scottberkun.com/2014/how-to-convince-your-boss-to-try-new-things/" target="_blank">Scott Berkun</a> writes. “Provided the boss respects their opinion, their interest in participating helps support your arguments. In some cases it might even be better if someone other than you makes the pitch.”</p>
<p>In fact, if you’re new to the company, or pitching an idea that requires the participation of other departments or levels, you should consider inviting a more senior member of the team to collaborate with you. They have more pull and might be received better. </p>
<p>“C-Suites always check out your reputation,” <a href="http://micheleandco.com/blog/getting-yes-pitching-ideas-c-suite/" target="_blank">Michele Wierzgac</a> writes. “If you have a reputation for being a rebel, your ideas may never be heard or implemented. If your ideas are always being rejected, you may want to examine your reputation. If you have said or done something that has damaged your reputation within the organization, you may want to consider moving on and starting over.”</p>
<p>Remember, you’re not just getting buy-in from your CEO, but also your co-workers in other departments. If you can make them excited to get involved in the projects (instead of just approving of it), then you increase your odds of approval. </p>
<p>“We may get compliance but we won’t get the kind of buy-in that motivates others to deeply support our ideas,” <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/work-in-progress/2015/03/16/how-to-get-real-buy-in-for-your-idea/#34bfdb51694b" target="_blank">Kristi Hedges</a> writes at Forbes. “Real buy-in involves at least some element of co-creation. It invites discussion, debate, and allows everyone to feel even more vested in the outcome.”</p>
<p>However your pitch is received, take time at the end to solicit feedback. This proves that the project is a team effort and will only succeed with the whole team’s input. </p>
<p>“One of the best strategies you can use when you walk into the lion’s den and have this honest conversation with your stakeholder is to ask for advice and feedback,” <a href="http://www.esi-intl.co.uk/blogs/pmoperspectives/index.php/how-to-win-people-over-and-gain-buy-in-from-senior-stakeholders/" target="_blank">Susanne Madsen</a> writes at the PM Perspectives Blog. “This is a very disarming move, which instantly builds trust and opens up the relationship because you show that you care and that you are humble enough to ask for their opinion.”</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/meeting-1024x678.jpg" alt="meeting" width="1024" height="678" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5266" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/meeting-1024x678.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/02/meeting-300x199.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/02/meeting-768x508.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/02/meeting-600x397.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/02/meeting.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Mitigate the Risk and Cost to the Company</h2>
<p>One universal tactic for getting your management team to say yes is by lowering the potential risk to the organization. Remember, “risk” applies to lost time, money, resources, and reputation, so even a relatively affordable venture could be viewed as risky if it takes up significant chunks of employee hours. </p>
<p>“The whole time you’re talking, they’re adding up the risks of your proposal on one side of the scale and weighing them against potential rewards on the other side,” John Reed writes at <a href="http://pitchmaps.com/how-to-pitch-senior-executives/" target="_blank">PitchMaps</a>, where he’s shared a 10-point checklist for pitching to senior executives. “You have to prove one thing: that the cost of doing nothing is greater than the cost of implementing your recommendation.”</p>
<p>To mitigate risk, suggest a pilot program on a smaller scale to determine preliminary results and benefits.</p>
<p>“Ideas that can be tried on a small scale are often more likely to be adopted,” <a href="http://blog.marketresearch.com/how-to-sell-your-idea-to-senior-management" target="_blank">Sarah Schmidt</a> writes at MarketResearch.com. “If your idea requires a huge upfront investment and significant effort and coordination among different teams, people may be less open to the risks involved. &#8230; Find ways to experiment with your idea on a smaller scale before committing to wholesale changes.” </p>
<p>Then, if the program is accepted, you will be able to execute it on a large scale with ideas for improvement and better planning. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/women-1024x682.jpg" alt="women" width="1024" height="682" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5267" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/women-1024x682.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/02/women-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/02/women-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/02/women-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/02/women.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Flesh Out As Many Details as Possible</h2>
<p>While co-worker buy-in is a big part of pitching ideas, you also need to prove that you know your stuff. Don’t waste your CEO’s time with a half-baked idea that lacks detail, evidence and goals. </p>
<p>“You must have a clear and detailed understanding on the project and its sequential stages in order to be able to communicate what each of the affected business areas needs to support the project,” writes the team at <a href="https://www.pm-partners.com.au/insights/6-steps-to-gaining-approval-for-a-project/" target="_blank">PM-Partners Group</a>. “Each of the areas will need to know the cost and time impacts on each of them during the commissioning, implementation and ongoing support of the new initiative.”</p>
<p>In all likelihood, your idea will affect other departments and increase their workloads. By understanding the scope and your needs from them, you can phrase this ask in an informed manner. </p>
<p>“The first thing you will want to assure your boss of is that it won’t distract from all of the work already on your plate,” (or on the plates of others) <a href="https://www.themuse.com/advice/how-to-pitch-a-new-idea-to-your-boss" target="_blank">Sara McCord</a> writes at The Muse. “Phrasing this actually takes a more delicate balance than you may imagine. Seem too busy, and your boss may suggest you hold off on a new initiative, but make it seem like you have all the time in the world, and your supervisor may wonder what’s taken you so long to suggest additional tasks.”</p>
<p>Again, this is where listening comes in. What is your C-suite concerned with when starting a new project. Is it incremental revenue? Is it exposure? One of the easiest ways to win them over is with hard facts.  </p>
<p>“Illustrating benefits is similar to making it relevant, but clearly show how this change or idea will positively impact the organization,” <a href="http://annuitas.com/blog/2016/09/06/3-ways-gain-executive-buy/" target="_blank">Erika Goldwater</a> writes at Annuitas. “Speak the language of your boss; use numbers, statistics, revenues or savings percentage to help quantify the value of the proposed change.”</p>
<p>Finally, end your pitch with a timeline and implementation plan (with your pilot program and eventual goals). Create a specific ask regarding the budget and resources so your CEO isn’t just agreeing to an abstract concept that’s forgotten. </p>
<p>“Contrary to popular belief, ideas in and of themselves are not particularly valuable,” <a href="https://www.pursuant.com/blog/how-to-get-leadership-buy-in-for-your-innovative-ideas/" target="_blank">Trent Ricker</a> writes at Pursuant. “Thousands of great ideas are born every day but very few ever come to life. Why? Implementation, that’s the hard part. It’s what separates an idea from an innovation.”</p>
<p>Your management team is surrounded by people trying to push their ideas and agendas all day. By making a prepared and informed case, you’re setting yourself up to successfully stand out and receive one of the few instances of “yes.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
<a href="https://unsplash.com/@evanrclark" target="_blank"><em>Evan Clark</em></a><em>, </em><a href="https://unsplash.com/@alexisrbrown" target="_blank"><em>Alexis Brown</em></a><em>, </em><a href="http://unsplash/" target="_blank"><em>unsplash</em></a><em>, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/StartupStockPhotos-690514/" target="_blank"><em>StartupStockPhotos</em></a><br />
</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/executive-pitch/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pizza, Praise, Ping Pong Tables: How to Motivate Your Company to Do Great Work</title>
		<link>/motivate-your-company/</link>
					<comments>/motivate-your-company/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2017 15:21:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Career Planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Entrepreneurship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5233</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To motivate your company, you have to understand what causes employees to disengage in the first place. Here’s how you can create a culture they respond to.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Motivation is the lifeblood of your organization. Without it, your employees will stop after they complete the bare minimum of what is expected of them, and your turnover rate will continue to grow. </p>
<p>In order to motivate your team, you have to understand what causes them to lose their drive and disengage in the first place. Here’s what makes your team tick, and how you can create an environment they respond to. </p>
<h2>Culture Motivates Employees, and Employees Motivate Culture</h2>
<p>Culture is often treated with a top-down approach. The founders and powers-that-be decide what cultural values the company should embody, and then decree that all others in the organization should follow their guidelines. </p>
<p>However, defining what you want your culture to be doesn’t necessarily mean that’s what your culture is. </p>
<p>“Everyone talks about company culture, but most have it backwards,” writes <a href="http://fortune.com/2016/08/26/this-is-how-you-motivate-employees/" target="_blank">Steve Tobak</a>, author of Real Leaders Don’t Follow. “Culture isn’t something you set out to create, but something you don’t know you’ve created until after the fact. Culture is a way to document that unique combination of factors that somehow came together and, against all odds, actually achieved what the company set out to do.”</p>
<p>One of the easiest ways to demotivate employees is to develop a “do what I say, not what I do” approach to culture — which puts the onus on management to be thoughtful about both what they say and what they do. </p>
<p>“Nothing speaks more loudly about the culture of an organization than the leader’s behavior, which influences employee action and has the potential to drive their results,” <a href="http://www.yourthoughtpartner.com/blog/bid/59619/leaders-follow-these-6-steps-to-build-trust-with-employees-improve-how-you-re-perceived" target="_blank">David Grossman</a> writes. “If you say teamwork is important, reinforce the point by collaborating across teams and functions. Give credit when people do great work and you’ll set the stage for an appreciative culture.”</p>
<p>Every company has a culture guided by principles, but it’s the actions of employees and managers that determine whether those principles become toxic. </p>
<h2>A Pat on the Back Goes a Long Way</h2>
<p>So, what should be included in your company culture? Start by creating an environment of recognition to make your employees feel valued. </p>
<p>“It’s easy to underestimate the power of a pat on the back, especially with top performers who are intrinsically motivated,” <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/critical-ways-managers-motivate-demotivate-employees-bradberry" target="_blank">Dr. Travis Bradberry</a> writes at LinkedIn. “Everyone likes kudos, none more so than those who work hard and give their all. Rewarding individual accomplishments shows that you’re paying attention. Managers need to communicate with their people to find out what makes them feel good and then to reward them for a job well done.”</p>
<p>Even <a href="https://www.teamfocus.me/remote-employees/">self-motivated remote employees</a> need a pat of the back on occasion, and a few kind words can motivate employees better than other physical incentives.  </p>
<p>In one study, employees were offered multiple incentives: a cash bonus, free pizza, or a compliment from the boss. While pizza certainly performed well, the biggest motivator was getting a pat on the back.</p>
<p>“I never encourage flattery — or praise that you don&#8217;t really mean,” <a href="http://www.inc.com/justin-bariso/study-says-pizza-works-better-than-cash-to-motivate-employees-but-one-thing-work.html" target="_blank">Justin Bariso</a> writes at Inc. “But everyone deserves praise for something; as a leader, it&#8217;s your job to figure out what. To look for the good, to see the potential, and to bring out the best in them. Your employees will value that a heckuva lot more than pizza.”</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Employee-1024x683.jpg" alt="employee" width="1024" height="683" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5236" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Employee-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Employee-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Employee-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Employee-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Employee.jpg 1677w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Encourage Employees to Work for a Higher Cause</h2>
<p>Of course, you don’t have to choose between pizza and kind words to motivate employees. You simply have to create a sense of purpose and big picture for them to work toward. </p>
<p>“No matter what your organization does — whether it’s offering a service or building products — it is important that your culture be infused with meaning,” <a href="https://hbr.org/2016/01/to-motivate-employees-do-3-things-well" target="_blank">Emma Seppälä, Ph.D.</a> writes at the Harvard Business Review. “Studies show that people who have a sense of purpose are more focused, creative, and resilient, so leaders should make a point of reminding employees how their work is improving people’s lives.”  </p>
<p>What does this mean for companies that aren’t nonprofits or don’t create products that save the world? Your “higher purpose” can come in many different forms: </p>
<h3>What Causes Does Your Company Support?</h3>
<p>If your company isn’t actually saving the whales or curing cancer, how is it helping those who do? </p>
<p>Do you have a nonprofit client that helps rescue dogs? Does your team participate in a local charity run each year? That matters to your employees, especially the younger ones.</p>
<p>“When millennials are considering applying for a job, their top priority is what the company actually sells, produces, or distributes,” <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/causeintegration/2015/05/05/new-report-on-millennials-shows-link-between-engagement-and-cause-work/#c0c39442341e" target="_blank">Ryan Scott</a>, CEO of Causecast, writes at Forbes. “But beyond compensation and benefits, what matters most to them is the company’s work culture, involvement with causes, office environment, and attention to diversity and HR standards.”</p>
<p>It’s possible to create a culture of purpose through corporate initiatives, even if it’s simply collecting cans for the food bank. </p>
<h3>What Are Your Company’s Goals and Plans for Growth?</h3>
<p>Another way to motivate your employees through a cause is to get them on board with the company’s plans in the next few months and years. </p>
<p>“According to one survey, only 40% of the workforce knew about their company’s goals, strategies and tactics,” <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/ashleystahl/2015/12/04/five-secrets-to-motivate-and-retain-employees/#4c9daf515e4e" target="_blank">Ashley Stahl</a> writes at Forbes. “Bringing your team into the fold and exposing them to the bigger picture of what you are trying to accomplish — and WHY you’re trying to accomplish it — is the most powerful way to motivate them.” </p>
<p>No one wants to feel like they’re a cog and aren’t high enough on the ladder to ask questions. Further, creating a culture of openness will enable employees to trust you if you do need them to do something without explanation. </p>
<h3>Why Should Your Employees Take Pride in Their Environment?</h3>
<p>Are there cupcakes in the breakroom to celebrate employee birthdays? Do you have a question wall to get to know your team on a personal level?</p>
<p>“Create an attractive workplace that gives employees a sense of pride,” <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/252548" target="_blank">Jane Wesman</a> writes at Entrepreneur. “I’ve found that painting office walls bright colors, instead of boring gray or beige, increases energy levels. Buying attractive furniture, whether it’s from IKEA or a top designer, gives employees a sense of pride. They tend to keep their workspaces neater and thus find it easier to be productive.”</p>
<p>Small steps to improve the environment can set the standards for how employees treat their office spaces — and their jobs. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/space-1024x685.jpg" alt="space" width="1024" height="685" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5238" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/space-1024x685.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/space-300x201.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/space-768x514.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/space-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/space.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Prove That You’re Invested In Your Team</h2>
<p>To some, the idea of sprucing up an office area might seem superficial, especially when managers are trying to boost employee morale and motivation. However, there’s a deeper purpose to these minor adjustments. </p>
<p>And there’s a classic study from the early 20th Century that demonstrates why. </p>
<p>That study broke employees into two groups: A control group, and a group whose environment began to change (think improved lighting or a more comfortable office layout). Those incremental changes translated into sustained productivity.</p>
<p>“Every case found that the level of productivity increased whenever there was a change in the work conditions,” <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/283324" target="_blank">Pratik Dholakiya</a> writes. “The increased productivity remained elevated even when the conditions returned back to normal. The researchers eventually deduced that the increase in productivity was not attributable to the changes in the physical conditions, but to the fact that attention was being paid to them, and employees felt that someone was genuinely concerned about their working conditions.”</p>
<p>Replacing a tattered and broken chair proves that you’re watching for your employees and care about their comfort. Similarly, investing in them professionally proves that you care about their future careers — especially within the company. </p>
<p>“If you expect your employees to stay at your company for the long haul, you need to have plans in place for their growth and advancement,” Formstack CEO <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/273944" target="_blank">Chris Byers</a> writes. “Very few people will be content to stay in the exact same position for years on end. You want to hold on to employees who are interested in contributing to the forward movement of your company.”</p>
<p>From the management’s perspective, this means treating your employees like individuals and finding ways that grow based on their skills. </p>
<p>“I’d recommend conducting a skills assessment before deciding on what training you’re going to organise for each employee,” <a href="https://social.hays.com/2016/04/26/5-things-that-motivate-your-employees-more-than-money/" target="_blank">Marc Burrage</a> at Hays Recruiting Experts writes. </p>
<p>“The employee will better appreciate, and be more motivated by, a sensible and well-considered plan of training for them. You need not worry if your business/department has no budget for learning and development — many don’t — there should be plenty of free and relevant networking events and conferences your employees can attend; you just need to look around.”</p>
<h2>Understand the Meaning and Value of Trust</h2>
<p>Often, employee motivation comes from within, especially when they’re placed in an environment with high levels of trust from all parties. </p>
<p>“Companies deemed by employees to have both strong character and inspired trust performed almost four times better than those that had other positive cultural attributes, such as collaboration and celebrating others,” <a href="http://fortune.com/2016/04/27/why-trust-motivates-employees-more-than-pay/" target="_blank">Jennifer Reingold</a> writes at Fortune. “What’s more, ‘high trust’ organizations were 11 times as likely to be called more innovative than their competitors.”</p>
<p>When managers trust their employees to make wise decisions, employees <a href="https://www.teamfocus.me/embracing-failure/">feel better about taking risks</a>, which can have bigger payoffs in the long run.  </p>
<p>“Most people think distrust is the opposite of trust, but it’s not — the opposite of trust is control,” <a href="https://leadingwithtrust.com/2016/05/08/developing-motivated-and-engaged-employees-begins-with-trust/" target="_blank">Randy Conley</a> writes at the Leading With Trust Blog. “Leaders who compulsively try to maintain control erode their team members’ sense of autonomy [and] squash their sense of motivation. It’s human nature to desire independence and to feel in control of our lives. That desire doesn’t stop at the office door.”</p>
<p>If everything they do is going to be questions and criticized, why should your employees try to grow and improve the company? </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/trust-1024x634.jpg" alt="trust" width="1024" height="634" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5239" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/trust-1024x634.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/trust-300x186.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/trust-768x475.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/trust-600x371.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/trust.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Work-Life Balance Contributes to the Culture of Trust</h2>
<p>A high level of trust also contributes to a company’s work-life culture. When employees aren’t insecure about their performance, they’re able to make decisions that benefit their health and their motivation to perform their best. </p>
<p>“When employees feel a greater sense of control and ownership over their own lives, they tend to have better relationships with management and are able to leave work issues at work and home issues at home,” the team at <a href="https://pingboard.com/work-life-balance/" target="_blank">Pingboard</a> writes. </p>
<p>“Balanced employees tend to feel more motivated and less stressed out at work, which thereby increases company productivity and reduces the number of conflicts among co-workers and management.”</p>
<p>Frankly, sometimes employees just need to get out of the office for a while. </p>
<p>“The normal work environment has limitations, even if micromanagement is eliminated,” Soma co-founder <a href="http://fortune.com/2016/03/16/motivate-your-employees/" target="_blank">Mike Del Ponte</a> writes. “Anytime an employee needs to check out and recalibrate, they’re free to work from home or their favorite coffee shop. Giving autonomy to employees not only produces higher productivity, it also reminds everyone that they are their own bosses and we trust their judgment to decide what will make them work most efficiently.”</p>
<p>The work-life balance is often viewed as a company perk, but it’s actually part of the culture. When managers trust their employees to get their work done in a timely manner, employees treat themselves better and are healthier for it. </p>
<p>“Keeping a reasonable balance will mean employees are less susceptible to burning out at work — the feeling of being overwhelmed and unable to meet constant demands of a workplace,” <a href="http://theundercoverrecruiter.com/ways-motivate-employees/" target="_blank">Ruby Lowe</a> writes for The Undercover Recruiter. “Keeping a healthy work-life balance has even been proven to improve your health and wellbeing. Taking time out for yourself can limit health problems and let you lead a more productive lifestyle in general.”</p>
<p>Employee motivation doesn’t come in the form of free food, unlimited vacation days, and high pay. It comes from your company’s culture of trust, growth, and transparency. These are items that can’t be added to a benefits package, and need to be constantly developed within your organization to encourage employees to stay. </p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
<em>©pressmaster/123RF Stock Photo, ©racorn/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/ChristianHoppe-377053/" target="_blank"><em>ChristianHoppe</em></a><em>, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/jdpereiro-2378671/" target="_blank"><em>jdpereiro</em></a><br />
</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/motivate-your-company/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Find and Hire the Right Remote Employees for Your Team</title>
		<link>/hire-remote-employees/</link>
					<comments>/hire-remote-employees/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 01:50:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Career Planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5223</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It’s possible to find remote employees who will stick with your company and get results. Here’s how to find and hire those people.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hiring and onboarding new employees can be a frustrating and time-consuming process, particularly when you are hiring remote employees who need to adapt to your style and expectations quickly.</p>
<p>While flexible startups can complete the hiring process (from job posting to first day) in about one month, managers often have to set aside large chunks of their schedule during the first few weeks for training and transitioning.</p>
<p>All of this effort goes to waste if your prospect quits within a few months, or you have to let them go due to poor work. </p>
<p>However, it&#8217;s possible to vet your remote employees to find people who will stick with your company and provide your desired results. You just need to hone in your process and know what to look for. </p>
<p>Here&#8217;s how the pros hire remotely, and how you can learn to do the same. </p>
<h3>A Test Project is Worth a Thousand Interviews</h3>
<p>More companies than ever are asking candidates to &#8220;put their money where their mouth is&#8221; by assigning test projects to vet the top performers. </p>
<p>&#8220;The [problem] with hiring based on a resume is that it might just show you that the candidate is really good at writing resumes, but not necessary good at their job,&#8221; the team at <a href="https://blog.timedoctor.com/2016/09/15/mistakes-when-hiring-remote-workers" target="_blank">Time Doctor</a> writes. &#8220;Develop a test which exactly matches the type of work they will be doing in their job. For example, I recently hired a marketing team member. To find the best possible candidate I could, I created a task which was exactly what I wanted them to do for the job which I was hiring.&#8221;</p>
<p>For a copy editor, this might be a literal test where they&#8217;re asked to fix grammar errors and format an article to match a client&#8217;s tone. For developers, this could entail building a landing page with certain characteristics. </p>
<p>&#8220;When hiring remote employees, candidate interviews mostly happen via a phone interview or a video interview,&#8221; Heba Asaad writes at <a href="https://www.deltek.com/en/learn/blogs/talent-management/2016/09/remote-employees-and-a-successful-hiring-process" target="_blank">Deltek</a>. &#8220;However, many hiring processes should be further refined by asking the remote candidate to do a trial test project or task to test how well they follow instructions, ask questions, and perform in a remote environment.&#8221;</p>
<p>This is important: The test is supposed to do more than test their skills. It&#8217;s also supposed to provide a window into their work processes and what you can expect when collaborating with them. </p>
<p>When administering the test, make sure you pay your candidates for their work. You could lose top talent if you assign a five-hour project without compensating them for their time.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Video-Call-1024x691.jpg" alt="video call conference chatting communication concept" width="1024" height="691" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5228" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Video-Call-1024x691.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Video-Call-300x202.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Video-Call-768x518.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Video-Call-600x405.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Video-Call.jpg 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h3>Ask the Right Questions in the Interviews</h3>
<p>Your interview process should certainly cover the hard skills needed for the job, but that&#8217;s mainly what the test section is for. The bulk of interview time should be spent asking questions that give employees opportunities to share their qualities to become a good remote employee. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you don&#8217;t know what you&#8217;re looking for (i.e. can you tell if a coder&#8217;s PHP is up to snuff?) then you may not be asking the right questions,&#8221; <a href="http://blog.hubstaff.com/recruit-top-virtual-employees/" target="_blank">Dave Nevogt</a>, co-founder of Hubstaff.com, says. &#8220;Spend some time assessing how you can qualify candidates in a field you don&#8217;t fully understand, and if you hit too many roadblocks think about contracting a specialized recruiter to vet them for you to start.&#8221;</p>
<p>In the meantime, here are three questions to add to your initial interviews: </p>
<h3>What Time of Day You Plan to Complete the Work?</h3>
<p>&#8220;While not all remote employees will need to clock in and out as specific times, it is important to understand the timeframe in which the candidate intends to perform their assignments,&#8221; the team at <a href="http://www.advancestaffingsolutions.com/2016/08/05/hiring-remote-employees-dont-forget-ask-5-questions/" target="_blank">Advance Staffing Solutions</a> explains. </p>
<p>&#8220;This allows you to evaluate their availability, ensuring it includes times when they need to be available for contact. Additionally, it provides insights into other obligations they may also need to meet that could cause conflict.&#8221;</p>
<p>Many remote teams try to find a &#8220;universal hour&#8221; when team members are awake and working so they can have meetings. This also helps you determine whether their schedule would match that timeframe. </p>
<h3>How Do You React When Faced With Unexpected Crises?</h3>
<p>&#8220;As a remote worker, it&#8217;s easy to run into a problem and feel like you have to solve it on your own,&#8221; <a href="https://skillcrush.com/2015/03/17/remote-job-interview-questions/" target="_blank">Randle Browning</a> writes at SkillCrush. &#8220;Because you&#8217;re not sitting in the same office as your team, you can get off schedule or overwhelmed without anyone else noticing</p>
<p>&#8220;&#8230; Your future employer is hoping to see your strategies for proactively preventing this situation by letting your co-workers and even your boss know when you need help so that you don&#8217;t put yourself or your team at risk.&#8221;</p>
<p>Some employees prefer employees to solve problems on their own, while others want to communicate and collaborate even when the plan is failing. Try to gauge their threshold for reaching out to ask for help. </p>
<h3>What is Your Process for Approaching a New Project?</h3>
<p>&#8220;Your hiring documents will give a taste of what you bring to the team, but storytelling will be crucial throughout the verbal interview process to reassure the hiring manager that you can work remotely,&#8221; <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/kaviguppta/2016/05/30/how-to-master-your-remote-work-job-interview/#296381f378fe" target="_blank">Kavi Guppta</a> writes at Forbes. </p>
<p>&#8220;This is your opportunity to discuss concrete examples of how autonomous and organized you can be. Don&#8217;t just talk about your ability to produce great work; be explicit about the production process you encountered or were responsible for designing.&#8221;</p>
<p>Furthermore, some employees prefer to take a big-picture approach to work, while others only want the first few steps to focus on to avoid getting overwhelmed. Understanding their work process will help the employee-manager relationship right off the bat. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/time-1024x703.jpg" alt="time" width="1024" height="703" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5227" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/time-1024x703.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/12/time-300x206.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/12/time-768x527.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/12/time-600x412.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/12/time.jpg 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h3>Look for Soft Skills That Remote Employees Need to Thrive</h3>
<p>In many cases, vetting candidates based on hard skills is the easy part. Deciding whether they can do this job is a yes-or-no answer.</p>
<p>&#8220;When [managers] decide to hire remotely after giving up locally, [they] suddenly have thousands of options,&#8221; <a href="http://x-team.com/2015/03/mistakes-remote-developers/" target="_blank">Ryan Chartrand</a>, CEO of X-Team, writes. &#8220;This is why you need to be able to express your value, your superpower, your primary expertise within 15 seconds to anyone who stumbles upon your profiles. If Drupal is where you will bring the most value, make it clear. If JavaScript is where you&#8217;ll be a ninja on my team, make it clear.&#8221;</p>
<p>However, deciding whether they&#8217;re right for the job is more complex. In-house as well as remote managers are starting to realize <a href="https://www.salesforceiq.com/blog/4-skills-employers-look-for-in-the-modern-salesperson" target="_blank">the importance of soft skills</a> in their hires. For remote employees, these soft skills can dictate employee morale, product quality and manager satisfaction. </p>
<h3>Communication</h3>
<p>&#8220;Unless you continually monitor your employees with cameras and network tracking software, you&#8217;re still extending a high level of trust, regardless of their location,&#8221; writes <a href="http://blog.rayalleninc.com/look-for-strong-communicators-when-hiring-remote-employees/" target="_blank">Todd Ringleman</a>, co-founder of Ray Allen Inc. &#8220;One key skill to keep in mind is communication. It seems obvious, but communication really is a group of skills that range from writing simple emails to representation of the company culture. There are nuances to be understood by both sides.&#8221;</p>
<p>How your employees communicate with each other and in the chats — from sharing weekend stories or offering criticism — can have just as much of an effect on your company as a poorly constructed sales pitch email.</p>
<h3>Time Management </h3>
<p>&#8220;The flexibility that working from home allows can be a blessing and a curse,&#8221; Kate Van Bremen, Ph.D., writes at <a href="http://www.selectinternational.com/blog/hiring-remote-employees-can-be-scary-focus-on-these-four-things" target="_blank">Select International</a>. &#8220;In order for remote employees to be successful, they need to have strong time management skills. They&#8217;ll need to be able to estimate the amount of time and other resources necessary to complete their work and plan and execute accordingly.&#8221;</p>
<p>How can employers test this? Include it in the test project. Have an idea of how long the project should take and ask the candidates about their time use when they submit it for completion.<br />
 </p>
<h3>Self-Direction</h3>
<p>&#8220;A candidate with a high level of skill but a low level of self-direction might be fine if he&#8217;s in the cubicle down the hall, working closely with other team members to keep him on track,&#8221; <a href="https://www.themuse.com/advice/3-mistakes-not-to-make-when-hiring-remote-employees" target="_blank">Josh Tolan</a>, CEO at Spark Hire, says. &#8220;But if this candidate is located across the country instead of across the office floor, your all-star hire might quickly turn into a dud.&#8221;</p>
<p>In fact, self-direction is hands-down one of the most important traits that managers need to identify during this process. We will talk about it more in the next section. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/write-1024x605.jpg" alt="write" width="1024" height="605" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5229" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/write-1024x605.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/12/write-300x177.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/12/write-768x454.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/12/write-600x354.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/12/write.jpg 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h3>Self-Motivation Can Compensate for Previous Remote Work</h3>
<p>One of the best indicators of a successful remote employee is previous remote experience. However, this doesn&#8217;t mean self-motivated individuals working remotely for the first time should be ignored. </p>
<p>&#8220;Ideal employees should be able to take on a job or task and figure out a solution without having to be harassed by the manager throughout the entire day,&#8221; the team at <a href="https://www.qualitylogoproducts.com/blog/4-employee-personality-traits-hiring-managers/" target="_blank">Quality Logo Products</a> writes. &#8220;This takes a ‘get it done&#8217; type of personality in which they are not afraid to help out with things without being asked or constantly nagged. Bosses want to be confident that things are getting done when they turn their back on employees.&#8221;</p>
<p>Not all employees are going to come out and call themselves self-motivated, but you can ask them about it and look for clues in their resume or other documents. </p>
<p>&#8220;When you are perusing LinkedIn profiles or online resumes, you can usually find self-motivated prospects by looking for the right keywords and phrases,&#8221; <a href="https://www.eremedia.com/ere/hire-self-motivated-people-the-single-smartest-thing-a-hiring-manager-can-do/" target="_blank">Dr. John Sullivan</a> says, writing for ERE. &#8220;You should begin the process by looking at the resumes and profiles of your own self-motivated employees to see which key indicators they have.&#8221;</p>
<p>If you are giving an employee their first remote experience, make sure you set checks to make sure they&#8217;re adapting to the new environment well. Remote work can derail even the best workers. </p>
<p>&#8220;Employees don&#8217;t always know what to expect when working from home,&#8221; the team at <a href="http://www.arsbackgrounds.com/5-abilities-to-look-for-in-your-remote-employee-candidates" target="_blank">ARS Backgrounds</a> writes. &#8220;For some, it becomes more than they bargained for — the isolation, a humming refrigerator beckoning them to have a snack, an inability to be self-directed, or pure dislike for remote work environments. Working from home or other remote locations simply doesn&#8217;t work out for everyone.&#8221;</p>
<h3>Evaluate Their Interest in Your Company and the Position</h3>
<p>Most employers focus on what the employees can do for them, and barely touch on what the company can do for the employee. However, failing to consider what your candidates think of the position can mean rehiring in a few months when they find something better. </p>
<p>&#8220;Any recruiter worth their salt knows that it&#8217;s important to hire not just any ol&#8217; employee, but one who knows about the company, believes in its mission, and wants to make a positive contribution to the organization,&#8221; <a href="https://www.recruiter.com/i/5-traits-to-look-for-when-hiring-remote-workers/" target="_blank">Brie Reynolds</a> writes for Recruiter.com. </p>
<p>&#8220;If a prospective employee seems ho-hum about the possibility of working with your company, chances are they won&#8217;t bring much enthusiasm or excitement to the job — which could lead to poor productivity and/or missed deadlines.&#8221;</p>
<p>Also, managers need to understand why remote employees choose this path and tailor their pitch toward the fulfilling aspects of the job. </p>
<p>&#8220;It&#8217;s not about the perks, the office Ping-Pong table, or the stock options,&#8221; <a href="https://www.helpscout.net/blog/hiring-top-talent/" target="_blank">Nick Francis</a>, co-founder of Help Scout, writes. &#8220;These people are most fulfilled when they feel empowered to do their best work. The best remote people have a particular passion for their craft, and one of the biggest reasons they love to work remotely is so they can focus on the work itself.&#8221;</p>
<p>To gauge their interest, ask why they chose your company and position to apply to, and then dig deeper into understanding their future goals. If you know where they want to go career-wise, you can decide if your company has the tools to make it happen. </p>
<p>&#8220;In traditional hiring, you&#8217;ll be focusing on qualification,&#8221; <a href="https://www.jorgedelgado.co/justtalking/tips-hiring-remote-employees/" target="_blank">Jorge Delgado</a> writes. &#8220;While this is still important, keeping remote workers delivering at a level that justifies their salary means they need to be well-motivated by their work as well. For example, picking people who are excited about your specific product or mission is a great way to ensure that you will actually have a remote employee that puts in the hours when they need to.&#8221; </p>
<p>This is easier for some companies than others, so you may have to compensate in other ways (through schedule flexibility or project opportunities) if you struggle to retain interested candidates. </p>
<p>The best employees can turn sour a few months after hiring, whether they&#8217;re not cut out work remotely or aren&#8217;t motivated by your mission. However, these steps cut down the personality factors that could lead to lower retention rates. </p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Image by:</em><br />
<em>©stockbroker/123RF Stock Photo, ©rawpixel/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/StartupStockPhotos-690514/" target="_blank"><em>StartupStockPhotos</em></a><em>, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/27707-27707/" target="_blank"><em>27707</em></a><br />
</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/hire-remote-employees/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>5 Types of Problematic Remote Employees [infographic]</title>
		<link>/problematic-remote-employees/</link>
					<comments>/problematic-remote-employees/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 15:56:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5200</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Problematic remote employees can be a challenge. But by knowing your team better, you can understand behavior and create policies that work for everyone.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Recent studies by <a href="http://globalworkplaceanalytics.com/resources/costs-benefits" target="_blank">Global Workplace Analytics</a> have found that 37% of employees would take a pay cut of 10% if they could work from home. Many employees crave the freedom, flexibility, and convenience of remote work. </p>
<p>But that doesn&#8217;t necessarily mean they&#8217;re cut out for the job. In some cases, distractions pop up that cut into employee productivity. In others, insecurities lead to overwork and job frustration. </p>
<p>Managers often struggle to identify why their employees are having problems. In a traditional office, they could walk over and talk to that employee, or they would be able to identify the problem just from observation. </p>
<p>This is harder for remote workers, who might be in different time zones and rely primarily on digital communication. To make it easier for them to understand what is happening, we created the infographic below: </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/TE126-IG.jpg" alt="te126-ig" width="800" height="5626" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5201" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/TE126-IG.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/TE126-IG-768x5401.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/TE126-IG-600x4220.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /> </p>
<h4>Embed this infographic on your site:</h4>
<p><textarea cols="60" rows="6">&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.teamfocus.me/5-types-problematic-remote-employees&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/TE126-IG.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;5 Types of Problematic Remote Employees&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.teamfocus.me/5-types-problematic-remote-employees&quot;&gt;5 Types of Problematic Remote Employees – www.teamfocus.me&lt;/a&gt;</textarea></p>
<p>Not all employees are a good fit for remote work setups. Some — especially those who don&#8217;t have previous telecommuting experience — get easily distracted by their surroundings. They think they&#8217;re multi-tasking by running a load of laundry during the day or clearing the dishwasher during a conference call, but they&#8217;re really just tuned out. </p>
<p>At best, this person is distracted. At worst, they&#8217;re a liability when they miss deadlines and show up unprepared. </p>
<p>Of course, not all hard-to-reach employees are distracted. Some remote workers enjoy working from home to reduce distractions found in the workplace. According to <a href="https://www.surepayroll.com/resources/blog/productivity-prohibitors-how-to-stop-them-in-their-tracks" target="_blank">Surepayroll</a>, 61 percent of employees said loud colleagues were the biggest distraction in the office, and 86 percent said they hit maximum productivity when working alone. It&#8217;s entirely possible that this employee has signed out of chat boxes and closed their emails as a way to eliminate distractions completely. </p>
<p>This silence is what frustrates some managers. They want to know that their remote teams are working hard and able to meet their deadlines, which they can&#8217;t do if their employees are unreachable. </p>
<p>This actually creates a double-edged sword: Checking in distracts employees, but managers need to contact them for regular updates and confirmation. </p>
<p>These are just two types of employees whom managers have to deal with when leading remote teams. In every case, though, by knowing your remote employees&#8217; personalities, you can better understand their behavior and create policies that will keep them focused, on-task and accountable.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/problematic-remote-employees/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Form Strong Relationships with Your Remote Employees (And Why You Should)</title>
		<link>/remote-employees/</link>
					<comments>/remote-employees/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 14:56:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Entrepreneurship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet Tools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5189</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Even when your remote employees are on the other side of the world, you need to be able to form close working relationships with them. Here’s how.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s easy to get caught up in the manic pace of the startup world. </p>
<p>Managers can get so focused on hitting deadlines in order to keep the company alive that they forget to step back and connect with the people working with them. But even when your team is on the other side of the world — and it&#8217;s hard to high-five your computer or tablet — you should still be able to have personal as well as professional relationships with them. </p>
<p>Here is how to get to know those employees better. </p>
<h2>The Benefits of Forming Relationships with Remote Employees</h2>
<p>You might not see the value of setting aside personal time if your employees already work well together. This is because remote employees tend to be self-motivated and notorious for their independence. However, that doesn&#8217;t mean they don&#8217;t want to form a personal bond with you.</p>
<p>&#8220;More than half of people who leave their jobs do so because of their relationship with their boss,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/249903" target="_blank">Dr. Travis Bradberry</a>, president of TalentSmart. &#8220;Bosses who fail to really care will always have high turnover rates. It&#8217;s impossible to work for someone eight-plus hours a day when they aren&#8217;t personally involved and don&#8217;t care about anything other than your production yield.&#8221;</p>
<p>Furthermore, building emotional connections can move your team off their islands and increase collaboration. If all of the pieces are good on their own, they might be amazing when you put them together. </p>
<p>&#8220;If all individual members of your team are productive, does that mean the team itself is as productive as can be?&#8221; asks <a href="https://www.teamgantt.com/blog/how-retreats-can-lead-to-breakthroughs-in-team-productivity/" target="_blank">Tim Macchi at Teamgantt</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;While it certainly won&#8217;t hurt things, unless they all work in a literal vacuum and don&#8217;t need anything from anyone ever, then personal productivity does not directly translate to team productivity. [Communication] is a major aspect involved with making sure your team is operating like a well-oiled machine.&#8221;</p>
<p>With personal bonds, employees can get questions answered faster and won&#8217;t rely on you — the CEO or manager — to solve all of their problems.</p>
<p>&#8220;Being able to form emotional ties among remote team members also is critical to establishing trust,&#8221; says author <a href="http://www.quickbase.com/blog/how-to-improve-remote-team-collaboration" target="_blank">Anita Bruzzese, writing for QuickBase&#8217;s The Fast Track</a> blog. &#8220;Beginning or ending meetings with some informal conversation or offering ‘small gives&#8217; such as interesting links to videos or articles can also help members form closer personal bonds.&#8221;</p>
<p>This article will start with these &#8220;small gives&#8221; and easy steps you can take for personal engagement, then work up to more complex team-building opportunities. </p>
<h2>Make Small Changes to Build Bonds in Your Company</h2>
<p>The first step toward improving internal relationships within your team is to analyze how your company works and make small changes toward growth. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you&#8217;re the sort of manager who only deals with her inbox once a day, you may be unwittingly alienating virtual teammates in a different time zone,&#8221; says former <a href="http://www.inc.com/ilan-mochari/bridging-social-distance-remote-teams.html" target="_blank">Inc. senior writer Ilan Mochari</a>. &#8220;The habit that makes your day more efficient could make an employee across the sea feel as if she always has to wait 24 hours for answers.&#8221;</p>
<p>In the name of long-term employee retention, you may have to open new communication channels or change your behavior to become more available. This also includes increasing transparency. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you&#8217;re a founder, owner, or team-lead, you should hold an ‘Ask Me Anything&#8217; session and be as transparent and honest with your team as possible,&#8221; explains <a href="https://pspdfkit.com/blog/2016/the-importance-of-retreats-for-a-remote-company/" target="_blank">Jonathan Rhyne at PSPDFKit</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;The more open and transparent you are with your team, the more likely they are to follow you into battle and buy into the company. No one wants to work somewhere when they don&#8217;t know the person behind the curtain nor his/her thought process into decisions.&#8221;</p>
<p>Again, this doesn&#8217;t have to be a major production. You can either create an anonymous Google Form or a specific folder for &#8220;Ask Me&#8221; questions. </p>
<p>&#8220;Employees must feel safe when they take the initiative to try something new, whether or not the idea works,&#8221; writes <a href="http://www.inc.com/peter-economy/7-proven-ways-to-genuinely-connect-with-your-employees.html" target="_blank">Peter Economy, The Leadership Guy, at Inc.</a> &#8220;It&#8217;s your job to provide your people with a safe haven to bring forward their ideas, and to tell the truth — no matter how hard it may be for you to hear.&#8221;</p>
<p>Even if these steps seems trivial, they can boost morale and reduce overall turnover rate. </p>
<p>&#8220;Most employees at large organizations feel little or no loyalty to their current employer,&#8221; explains <a href="http://www.raptmedia.com/blog/report-us-employees-detached-disengaged" target="_blank">Jennifer Bergen, director of content marketing at Rapt Media</a>. &#8220;One in three employees feel like their employers don&#8217;t care about them, and a staggering 69 percent are open to other opportunities or already seeking their next job.&#8221;</p>
<h2>Set Up Icebreakers Before Conference Calls</h2>
<p>While digital communication has certainly made it easier to chat online, many companies still rely on conference calls to check in. This is a great opportunity for icebreaker questions to help people get to know each other. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you&#8217;re hosting a meeting, keep it quick,&#8221; says collaboration specialist <a href="http://www.polleverywhere.com/blog/virtual-icebreakers-for-remote-teams/" target="_blank">Lisette Sutherland, writing for Poll Everywhere</a>. &#8220;You are meeting because there are things that need to be discussed as a team. These icebreaker questions should not get in the way of what needs to get done.&#8221; </p>
<p>The same statement can be made about planning personal social hours and company retreats. You don&#8217;t want the fun committee to co-opt the whole meeting. </p>
<p>&#8220;When virtual teams are starting out, in fact when any new team gets together, there is always a period of ‘getting to know each other&#8217; and learning team values and culture,&#8221; explains <a href="http://www.happymelly.com/virtual-ice-ice-breakers/" target="_blank">Louise Brace at Happy Melly</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;Another big plus that virtual icebreakers bring to an organization is the ability to extend the tool up and down the hierarchy. &#8230; The benefits extend up and down, something that wouldn&#8217;t normally happen in a traditional coaching or icebreaker session. Every employee receives the same level of respect and collaboration.&#8221;</p>
<p>What seems like a fun five minutes of distractions is actually a productivity tool. Once your teams know this, they can jump on board with their own ideas. </p>
<p>&#8220;Icebreakers fit into a larger strategy of team-building and establishing team culture.&#8221; <a href="http://blog.lucidmeetings.com/blog/5-icebreakers-for-distributed-team-meetings" target="_blank">Chris Higgins writes for Lucid Meetings</a>. &#8220;Everything that happens in any collaborative meeting should serve the purpose of the meeting. The icebreaker functions to get the team connected enough that they can begin working together in a collaborative way.&#8221;</p>
<p>Think of your ice-breaking session as an opportunity for your employees to learn how to communicate with each other and understand their personalities and humor. They can pick up on subtle clues and lower barriers of communication. </p>
<p>&#8220;Meeting someone new can be overwhelming when you have no time constraint on your conversation,&#8221; <a href="https://zapier.com/learn/the-ultimate-guide-to-remote-working/remote-team-communication/" target="_blank">Belle Beth Cooper writes for Zapier</a>. &#8220;Because we&#8217;re wired to look for threats in any new situation, our first reaction to meeting someone is to be wary of them until we start building up some rapport.&#8221;</p>
<p>All it takes is five minutes before a meeting to build report, which can lead to years of collaboration. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/laptop-1-1024x682.jpg" alt="laptop" width="1024" height="682" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5195" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/laptop-1-1024x682.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/laptop-1-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/laptop-1-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/laptop-1-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/laptop-1.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Find Bonding Activities That Work for Your Team</h2>
<p>While icebreakers are commonplace in remote conference calls, additional activities are up to you. These will depend on your resources, commitment level, and creativity.</p>
<p>&#8220;It may sound trivial, but having a movie night will get people&#8217;s guards down. It provides a space to talk about things unrelated to work,&#8221; <a href="https://remote.co/5-interactive-remote-team-building-exercises-for-distributed-teams/" target="_blank">Niraj Ranjan Rout, founder of Hiver</a>, writes for Remote.co. </p>
<p>&#8220;Choose a popular movie that everyone can watch on their laptops, and have a live chat running so you can have everyone&#8217;s opinion about every scene. After the movie is done, you can have a short discussion on how they liked it.&#8221; </p>
<p>You can also harness major events like the Super Bowl or World Cup and create a chat thread to engage employees who would normally be watching it anyway. </p>
<p>&#8220;Each year, we&#8217;ve had a company Christmas party via Skype,&#8221; <a href="http://tech.co/10-rituals-remote-teams-2015-04" target="_blank">Allan Branch, co-founder at Less Everything</a>, writes, for Tech.co. &#8220;We each take a turn being the gift recipient, which means muting your mic. Then the rest of the team will search the web for gift ideas. The recipient sits silently as the team will discuss their possible tastes in gifts. Finally, together a gift is chosen by the team and purchased by the company.&#8221;</p>
<p>Hosting a holiday party, even if it&#8217;s just a conference call, is a great way to bring a physical office tradition to remote teams. </p>
<p>&#8220;Place-based volunteering ideas include things like volunteering at a local soup kitchen, helping build a Habitat for Humanity house, or delivering gifts to children&#8217;s hospitals during the holidays,&#8221; writes <a href="http://blog.hubspot.com/marketing/creative-team-outing-ideas#sm.001xjr46h18eafi9pjw27zcloq10q" target="_blank">Lindsay Kolowich at HubSpot</a>. </p>
<p>She created a list of 17 fun corporate outings, many of which can be tweaked for remote teams. &#8220;Skill-based volunteering is a cool way to stretch your employees&#8217; expertise: It&#8217;s when your team volunteers their time and uses their professional skills — anything from marketing to app development to writing — to help a nonprofit.&#8221;</p>
<p>Your team could even consider hosting a &#8220;digital 5K,&#8221; where individuals run for a cause in their own areas and share their experiences online. </p>
<p>There is no set guide to how your company can form personal bonds. Take an idea that your employees are excited about and run with it. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/party-1024x768.jpg" alt="friends friendship celebration outdoors party concept" width="1024" height="768" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5196" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/party-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/party-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/party-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/party-600x450.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/party.jpg 1582w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Consider Hosting A Company-Wide Retreat</h2>
<p>Once your team becomes more established, you can even consider hosting a company retreat where everyone who is able to travels to one location for a few days.</p>
<p>&#8220;Research strongly suggests that an initial face-to-face meeting, or an annual one at minimum for long-term virtual teams, is vital to team success,&#8221; <a href="http://www.management-issues.com/connected/6986/building-social-capital-in-remote-teams/" target="_blank">Wayne Turmel</a>, co-founder of The Remote Leadership Institute, writes for Management Issues. </p>
<p>&#8220;Organizations often view this as an unnecessary expense, but their investment will be repaid several times over in efficiency and effectiveness. &#8230; The data shows that team members who are friends, and not just work colleagues, are more likely to share strong social capital ties.&#8221;</p>
<p>Buffer is one remote-success story that many companies try to emulate. They&#8217;ve created guides for successfully conducting remote team retreats. </p>
<p>&#8220;Monday-Friday, teammates tend to work together on a 9-to-5(ish) schedule,&#8221; explains <a href="https://open.buffer.com/remote-work-retreats/" target="_blank">Buffer&#8217;s Courtney Seiter</a>. &#8220;The actual ‘work time&#8217; is often more centered on conversations, sessions, and ad-hoc syncs than a normal week might be — we like to take advantage of the time in person to have lots of chats. (I always come with my notebook filled with specific conversations I want to have with specific teammates.)&#8221;</p>
<p>While all this is exciting for virtual companies, traditional teams can also take advantage of icebreakers and corporate retreats to form strong internal bonds. </p>
<p>&#8220;Teams no longer have to endure a faceless, beige conference room with boring cold sandwiches and uninspiring corporate culture exercises,&#8221; <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/kaviguppta/2015/09/30/how-remote-workers-are-transforming-the-company-retreat/#2fecae5a10df" target="_blank">Kavi Guppta writes for Forbes</a>. &#8220;These resources aren&#8217;t just for shiny new startups looking to standout. Your teams need to be inspired, and what better way to get them motivated than by shuttling them to an experience like no other?&#8221;</p>
<p>Improving morale through personal relationships doesn&#8217;t have to take more than a few minutes a week, but your teams might enjoy it enough to extend it on their own time to multiple hours. Employees who are happy with what they&#8217;re doing and who they work for are two crucial keys to long-term business success. </p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
<em>©goodluz/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/kelseyannvere-339731/" target="_blank"><em>kelseyannvere</em></a><em>, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/JuralMin-2051452/" target="_blank"><em>JuralMin</em></a><em>, ©rawpixel/123RF Stock Photo</em><br />
</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/remote-employees/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>6 Reasons Embracing Failure is Crucial to Project Management</title>
		<link>/embracing-failure/</link>
					<comments>/embracing-failure/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2016 15:54:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mental Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Psychology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5179</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How a company reacts to failure says more than when it succeeds. Here’s why embracing failure is a crucial part of work and how to make the most of it.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Our society tends to favor constant positivity. Parents worry about scolding their kids, we always answer &#8220;fine&#8221; or &#8220;good&#8221; when asked how we&#8217;re doing, and we&#8217;re told to chin up whenever something bad happens. </p>
<p>This state of constant happiness has entered the business world, where employees are expected to constantly be successful and fill their day with new wins. </p>
<p>This isn&#8217;t always the case. </p>
<p>Sometimes we fail.</p>
<p>Sometimes we lose. </p>
<p>How a company, or even a department, reacts to failure says more about its culture than how it performs during successful time. Furthermore, admitting and embracing failure, instead of sweeping it under the rug, can help teams in the long run. </p>
<p>Here&#8217;s why failure is a crucial to your team&#8217;s growth and how you can make the most of it.</p>
<h2>Accepting Failure Improves Employee Morale</h2>
<p>As a manager, one of the worst things you can do is make failure seem like something that&#8217;s completely unacceptable within the company. Nobody is perfect, and pressuring your staff to hit impossible goals will only break them. </p>
<p>&#8220;De-emphasizing perfection will encourage your employees to work hard, and grow loyal to your company,&#8221; says <a href="http://fortune.com/2015/06/02/amy-errett-keeping-your-best-employees/" target="_blank">Amy Errett, CEO and co-founder of Madison Reed</a>. &#8220;We would all like our employees to be perfect, but everyone is susceptible to making mistakes — even the best employees. Too much criticism can discourage employees, and create an adversarial atmosphere.&#8221;</p>
<p>Furthermore, setting impossible standards creates a new problem within your team: apathy. If they know going in that there&#8217;s no way to accomplish their goals, they might not bother to try their best. </p>
<p>&#8220;The worst thing about starting a project is having employees being apathetic towards it,&#8221; writes the team at <a href="http://capriconsulting.co.uk/2016/08/31/5-reasons-for-project-management-failure/" target="_blank">Capri Consulting</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you have employees on the project who are not motivated and do not pose any interest, the project is already doomed. Employees LOVE validation. If they see that you realize they are a valuable asset to the organisation, their motivations for projects will increase as well as their drive to succeed.&#8221;</p>
<p>As more companies acknowledge the benefits of failure, they&#8217;re encouraging employees to take risks. This has actually become a popular question within job interviews. </p>
<p>&#8220;Hiring managers don&#8217;t expect you to be perfect. They know that everybody fails,&#8221; says <a href="https://biginterview.com/blog/2014/02/biggest-failure-question.html" target="_blank">Pamela Skillings, co-founder of Big Interview</a>. &#8220;They ask this question to understand: Are you someone who can learn from failure? Are you self-aware enough to acknowledge failure and weakness? Do you take smart risks? After all, if you&#8217;ve never failed, then you&#8217;ve probably never succeeded on any significant level either.&#8221;</p>
<p>Managers would rather have a team that&#8217;s passionate enough to take risks than apathetic toward the project or too timid to try. The easiest way to do that is to create a safe zone for failure that is reviewed and at times rewarded. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/mistake.jpg" alt="mistake" width="798" height="532" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5183" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/mistake.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/mistake-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/mistake-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/mistake-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>Admitting Failure Gives Your Team Time to Process</h2>
<p>Often, creating a &#8220;culture of failure&#8221; is easier said than done, especially in established enterprises that already have a set hierarchy. </p>
<p>&#8220;Large hiring bonuses are given to executives who often also receive huge parachute payouts when their failures or disappointing performance get them fired,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.ideaarchitects.org/2015/01/failing-flailing.html" target="_blank">Jeffrey Cufaude of Idea Architects</a>. &#8220;When the worst thing that can happen is you get fired and walk out the door with a six or seven-figure check, it is indeed very OK to fail.&#8221; </p>
<p>Meanwhile, lower-level employees worry about how failing will reflect their job reviews, advancement potential and even salaries. There&#8217;s more to lose for them, which means they&#8217;re less likely to take risks.</p>
<p>&#8220;Before telling everyone that it&#8217;s OK to fail, at minimum spend more time (1) thinking about how this advice/request sounds to those possessing less privilege within the organization and perhaps framing your message differently, and (2) ensuring that the organization&#8217;s key systems (performance reviews, compensation, et al) are aligned with the acceptance of failure you envision,&#8221; Cufaude advises. </p>
<p>Failure isn&#8217;t always about risk-taking. There are times when everyone does their part to complete a goal that doesn&#8217;t pan out. Once this happens, team members need time to process the loss, and in some cases grieve. </p>
<p>&#8220;Failure can take a hefty emotional toll, and that&#8217;s OK,&#8221; <a href="http://lifehacker.com/how-to-move-past-failure-1597951611" target="_blank">Patrick Allen at Lifehacker</a> writes. &#8220;What&#8217;s important is getting the negative feelings you have out of your system so you can regroup and tackle what&#8217;s next. Failure can leave an open wound, and it&#8217;s unwise to ignore it. Without acknowledging it, your wound will continue to hurt, take longer to heal, and possibly get infected.&#8221;</p>
<p>On a managerial level, this means evaluating the morale of your team and understanding the effects of the setback. </p>
<p>&#8220;It&#8217;s OK to let everyone wallow in disappointment and negative feelings for a little while,&#8221; explains <a href="https://hbr.org/2015/02/how-to-help-your-team-bounce-back-from-failure" target="_blank">Amy Gallo, contributing editor at Harvard Business Review</a>. She tells a story about Susan David, founder of the Harvard/McLean Institute of Coaching, losing a client on a Friday that her company had been trying to land for months. </p>
<p>&#8220;Although she was trying to be motivating and forward-focused, to her devastated team, she came off as uncaring and uncommitted. In fact, negative or neutral emotions are conducive to deductive reasoning, which means they can help your team more effectively process and analyze the failure. When you acknowledge the disappointment &#8230; you&#8217;re not just stroking people&#8217;s emotions. You&#8217;re facilitating a critical appraisal of the situation.&#8221;</p>
<p>Instead of brushing failure under the rug or immediately looking for lessons and advice, give your team some time to let the news sink in, and then find ways to grow from it. </p>
<h2>Project Reviews Teach You About the Business and Employees</h2>
<p>The Butterfly Effect — the idea that a butterfly flaps its wings in one part of the world and causes a tsunami in the next — also applies to business. A small setback for one project can have massive effects on others or on future performance. </p>
<p>&#8220;As an entrepreneur I try to look at every mistake as a lesson,&#8221; says <a href="http://fortune.com/2015/03/31/shahrzad-rafati-best-mistake/" target="_blank">Shahrzad Rafati, founder and CEO of BroadbandTV</a>. &#8220;I want to understand why the mistake was made and how I can avoid making the same one in the future. More importantly, I want to understand how that mistake has changed or affected my business. Whether it&#8217;s a significant error in judgment or a minor oversight, I try to find value in the outcome.&#8221;</p>
<p>One of the fastest ways to identify mistakes and solve them is to assign a dollar value to them. However, you can also assign value in the form of lost time and employee stress. </p>
<p>Evaluating project performance extends beyond failure. Many successful calls and events happen through sheer luck, which can&#8217;t be counted on in the future. </p>
<p>&#8220;People are naturally wired to recognize when things aren&#8217;t going well, and to focus intently on how to fix problems,&#8221; says <a href="http://blog.lucidmeetings.com/blog/how-to-lead-a-successful-project-retrospective-meeting" target="_blank">Elise Keith, co-founder at Lucid Meetings</a>. &#8220;This leads us to take our successes for granted, assuming that things went well because we did a great job.</p>
<p>&#8220;An enormous part of what helps one project work where another doesn&#8217;t is luck — and we take it for granted. Instead, we should be looking for ways to learn from our lucky breaks and design ways to be successful that we can manage directly.&#8221;</p>
<p>Luck is never a good strategy, and companies who evaluate their projects&#8217; success and failures are taking the right steps toward admitting what was skill and what was a nice break. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/ship.jpg" alt="ship" width="798" height="532" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5185" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/ship.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/ship-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/ship-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/ship-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>Failure Helps You Execute the Next Project Better</h2>
<p>Once you&#8217;re ready to move on to the next project, you have the opportunity to take what you experienced and apply it moving forward. This is why many people advocate for post-project reviews even for small tasks and test runs. </p>
<p>&#8220;Even if a project is small, there are always things that pop up which will help you learn for larger projects,&#8221; writes one account manager at <a href="https://www.portent.com/blog/10-tips-for-a-successful-post-mortem.htm" target="_blank">Portent, Inc.</a> &#8220;For example, let&#8217;s say that the project was delayed because of communication issues. This could lead to a delay of a few days for a small project. But in a massive project, this could delay you by months and more importantly, increase the cost by two-fold.&#8221;</p>
<p>In some cases, the project itself was executed properly, but the process of approval and collaboration failed. This is often the case in companies with complex approval processes or agencies that work between account managers and clients. </p>
<p>&#8220;A project often has multiple parties interested in its outcome, and groups may even have divergent goals and expectations,&#8221; says <a href="http://blog.hightail.com/five-reasons-projects-fail/" target="_blank">Mike Trigg, COO at Hightail</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;I once spent weeks working with a designer and copywriter on a website home page redesign, only to have our carefully-crafted work dismantled by the company&#8217;s various heads of department demanding changes to meet their individual needs. Our problem was that we failed to establish who owned the project and therefore didn&#8217;t deal with potential conflicts and disappointments in advance.&#8221;</p>
<p>This is where the real project reviews come it. Delays, setbacks and challenges often aren&#8217;t caused by employees lacking the right skills or instructions, but by the creation process itself. </p>
<p>Reviewing flaws in small projects sets you up to create channels of improvement in the big ones. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you don&#8217;t have a clear focus at the at the earliest stage of the process, you are making things harder on yourself,&#8221; says <a href="https://project-management.com/top-10-main-causes-of-project-failure/" target="_blank">Rosanne Lim, writing for ProjectManagement.com</a>. &#8220;Have a meeting, even if it is lengthy, with stakeholders to discuss their expectations on cost, time and product quality. </p>
<p>&#8220;Tracking milestones is how you are going to know whether you are meeting expectations. Proper recording and monitoring lets the PM identify where more resources are needed to complete a project on time.&#8221;</p>
<p>Treat your projects like a leaky dam. If you find the source of a small leak — perhaps a faulty approval process or miscommunications between client and vendor — then take the necessary steps to patch it up. </p>
<p>That way, you&#8217;ll reduce the risk of a small leak breaking down the whole dam when you most need it. </p>
<h2>Failure Can Improve Customer Relations</h2>
<p>If it&#8217;s hard for employees to admit their faults to their managers, then it&#8217;s almost impossible for vendors to admit problems to their customers.</p>
<p>&#8220;Consider bringing in representatives from the client side to take a look at the lifespan of the project,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.business.com/program-and-project-management/the-postmortem-learning-the-most-in-post/" target="_blank">Andrew Lovasz, CEO of Main Path Marketing</a>. &#8220;Whether it&#8217;s over a conference call or passing along documents from the meeting, it&#8217;s always wise to share knowledge of how the project performed. Although this may seem a bit intimidating, it&#8217;s entirely useful to help manage the client&#8217;s expectations going forward.&#8221;</p>
<p>Bringing in these parties to discuss failure can actually improve customer relations. You&#8217;re taking necessary steps to improve your relationship while proving your commitment to growth.</p>
<p>Again, customers don&#8217;t want apathetic vendors.</p>
<p>If your team and vendors feel a little intimidated about really sharing their feelings, consider making the process anonymous for all parties. </p>
<p>&#8220;We&#8217;ve found both internal and external feedback on projects to be more candid when it&#8217;s submitted anonymously,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.business2community.com/strategy/10-things-include-project-post-mortem-0968906#OyzCgsih6iI57yeK.97" target="_blank">Brittany Hodak, co-founder of ZinePak</a>. &#8220;Now, before every project debrief, we collect anonymous survey responses in Google Forms. This feedback helps us shape our regroup meetings to make sure all problems are being addressed so future projects can run more smoothly.&#8221;</p>
<p>It&#8217;s entirely possible that people who have ideas for improvement are too intimidated to say anything and don&#8217;t want to ruffle feathers. As long as the criticism is constructive and leads to results, there&#8217;s no reason to avoid anonymous feedback. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Cookies.jpg" alt="cookies" width="798" height="532" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5182" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Cookies.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Cookies-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Cookies-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Cookies-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>You Reduce the Risk of Failure for Next Time</h2>
<p>Many educators are also teaching their students about failure and taking lessons from the business world. Like managers, they&#8217;re setting the standards incredibly high to push students so that they learn take feedback and try again. </p>
<p>&#8220;How do you make failure students&#8217; friend?&#8221; asks <a href="http://www.edutopia.org/blog/failure-essential-learning-bob-lenz" target="_blank">Bob Lenz, executive director of the Buck Institute for Education</a>. &#8220;Set a high standard and don&#8217;t be afraid to tell students that they haven&#8217;t met it. </p>
<p>&#8220;But in the next breath, give detailed suggestions on what they can do to improve. And, most important — though so often given short shrift — allow students the time, space and support to make the revisions.&#8221;</p>
<p>By making revisions part of the process, students learn early on to keep growing and improving. </p>
<p>As a manager, you can learn from this by letting your team know that no project is perfect — and no project is executed perfectly. There is always room for improvement. </p>
<p>&#8220;Failure brings with it important firsthand knowledge,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.wanderlustworker.com/the-importance-of-failure-5-valuable-lessons-from-failing/" target="_blank">R.L. Adams at Wanderlust Worker</a>. &#8220;That knowledge can be harnessed in the future to overcome that very failure that inflicted so much pain in the first place.&#8221;</p>
<p>Today, you might solve a big problem with communication, which allows you to find smaller problems that can also get fixed tomorrow. As long as your employees are growing and your office is improving, the likelihood of failure — and the sting when it eventually occurs — diminishes. </p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
<em>©gstockstudio/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/stevepb-282134/"><em>stevepb</em></a><em>, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/skeeze-272447/"><em>skeeze</em></a><em>, ©Novic/123RF Stock Photo</em><br />
</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/embracing-failure/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Project Management Software Has Changed Workplace Communication</title>
		<link>/project-management/</link>
					<comments>/project-management/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2016 22:47:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow software]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet Tools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5170</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As the digital office has evolved, communication has developed a set of rules. Here’s how you can get the most out of your project management software.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The onboarding process for any employees — whether they&#8217;re remote or in house — follows the same procedure. Create an email login, sign into chat, set up your voicemail, save the conference dial-in number, and plug in your webcam. (Most companies stop short of assigning carrier pigeons to their employees or handing out guidebooks on Morse code.)</p>
<p>Communication is crucial in the workplace, and its level of effectiveness can make or break a project or an employee&#8217;s experience. As the digital office has evolved, communication has also developed its own set of rules. Here&#8217;s how modern employees best use their communication tools, and how you should use them in the office.</p>
<h2>How Have Our Office Conversations Evolved?</h2>
<p>Before we look at the tools we use to communicate, we have to look at what we&#8217;re saying. Previously, conversations between managers and teams focused on <em>what</em> needed to get done, but now people primarily discuss <em>how</em> to do things.</p>
<p>&#8220;Employee productivity and efforts have been improved, allowing them to place more emphasis on more important things such as precision and creativity,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.iofficecorp.com/blog/4-ways-technology-has-changed-the-modern-workplace" target="_blank">Elizabeth Dukes, Partner at iOffice</a>.</p>
<p>&#8220;The level of expectation of clients and co-workers has also changed as a result of technology in the workplace, keeping everyone connected on a constant basis. Results are expected much faster than ever before.&#8221;</p>
<p>Productivity software like <a href="https://www.teamfocus.me/">teamfocus</a> has been a major contributor in this transition, and some people are even advocating for it to completely replace email.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2499696,00.asp" target="_blank">Jill Duffy, author of Get Organized</a>, believes email only makes employees stressed and overwhelmed when it comes to project work. &#8220;The last few years, productivity enthusiasts have pushed knowledge workers to get off of email, or at least to ditch internal company email. An excellent way shift away from email is to all but ban it from project work and move that communication to a project management service instead.&#8221;</p>
<p>However, like the conference call and voicemail, email will continue to be an important part of communication. In fact, many of today&#8217;s communication tools will remain in use as long as each of them has an important purpose in the workforce.</p>
<p>&#8220;Each of us has personal preferences for communication based on what we feel is easiest — for example, some people have an easier time writing than speaking, and some people prefer meeting in person rather than the impersonality of text,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.inc.com/jayson-demers/communication-in-2015-text-voice-video-or-in-person.html" target="_blank">Jayson DeMers, founder and CEO of AudienceBloom</a>.</p>
<p>&#8220;But it&#8217;s important to see beyond the limits of our own convenience. The selection of a medium can have a drastic impact on both the efficiency of your communication and the interpretation of your message.&#8221;</p>
<p>The rest of this article will discuss when each form of technology is appropriate, and how teams can use it to the fullest.</p>
<h2>When Should You Meet in Person?</h2>
<p>The oldest form of technology is our human bodies, which communicate verbal and nonverbal cues more effectively than any other channel. This is still the preferred method when forming personal bonds and discussing sensitive information.</p>
<p>&#8220;A study from Adobe found that Millennials value interpersonal interaction over digital interaction at work,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.cio.com/article/3082775/unified-communications/millennials-are-shaking-up-workplace-communication.html" target="_blank">Sarah White, writer at CIO</a>. &#8220;While 81 percent of Millennials said &#8216;state of the art technology&#8217; was paramount to an ideal working environment over perks or amenities, 55 percent they valued in-person communication at work over digital.&#8221;</p>
<p>However, she says those same respondents tended to overestimate how much everyone else relies on digital communication tools. &#8220;46 percent of respondents anticipated their peers to value IM and texts over interpersonal communication, but the real number ended up being just 11 percent.&#8221;</p>
<p>Just because young people are known for texting and online communication doesn&#8217;t mean society&#8217;s preference for human engagement is changing.</p>
<p>But sometimes, unintentionally or otherwise, messages get lost in the digital either.</p>
<p>In an article for Quartz, <a href="http://qz.com/523049/its-hard-to-fire-people-who-work-remotely-as-one-unfortunate-twitter-employee-just-discovered/" target="_blank">writer Max Nisen</a> covered the story of Bart Teeuwisse, a remote employee at Twitter who found out he was laid off when he couldn&#8217;t access his work accounts.</p>
<p>&#8220;When a manager can&#8217;t just pull someone into an office or a conference room, sometimes, as in this case, the logistics of layoffs — i.e. closing out company email accounts — get in ahead of informing the affected staff personally. Even the phone is not the option it once was, now that so many of us ignore calls and voicemails.&#8221;</p>
<p>With remote work, it&#8217;s not always possible to meet in person, but managers should be mindful and make a concentrated effort to get on the phone with affected employees before sensitive news breaks.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5163" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/phone-1024x682.jpg" alt="phone" width="1024" height="682" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/phone-1024x682.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/phone-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/phone-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/phone-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/phone.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Are Phone and Conference Calls Still Effective?</h2>
<p>Many people have become frustrated with the conference call. It&#8217;s viewed as a time suck and a way to talk about work without actually doing it.</p>
<p>&#8220;You have to both be engaged and seem engaged,&#8221; says <a href="http://money.usnews.com/money/careers/articles/2015/10/21/a-remote-workers-guide-to-conference-calls" target="_blank">writer Laura McMullen</a> for US News. &#8220;You have to fight for just. one. second. to jump in and add your two cents without feeling like Godzilla, stomping on other people&#8217;s words.</p>
<p>&#8220;You have to somehow catalog every team member&#8217;s voice and distinguish one from another. And you have to wrestle with bad connections, sound delays and other technological voodoo that seems to curse every call.&#8221;</p>
<p>However, despite the frustrations, many remote employees enjoy regular check-ins, and they use them as opportunities to ask questions and get to know their team members.</p>
<p>&#8220;You may think you are 100% approachable as a manager,&#8221; writes the team at <a href="https://justworks.com/blog/surefire-ways-make-remote-employees-loathe-you" target="_blank">JustWorks</a>. &#8220;But if you don&#8217;t actually explain to your remote employees how you can be approached, they&#8217;re going to err on the side of not approaching you at all.&#8221;</p>
<p>They recommend setting regular calls to give employees a chance to discuss issues and ask questions.</p>
<p>&#8220;[Create] a daily or weekly meeting that is always scheduled where the employee has a reason to call in and talk to you. It can be for ten minutes a day, but what you&#8217;re giving them is the chance to talk.&#8221;</p>
<p>Of course, weekly phone calls are only as effective as your team is at listening. One survey by <a href="https://www.westuc.com/en-us/blog/conferencing-collaboration/mobile-conferencing-changing-how-we-work" target="_blank">West Unified Communications Service</a> found 64% of employees do other work while on a conference call. Meanwhile, the rest are using the time for other activities.</p>
<p>&#8220;Workers take full advantage of the multitasking opportunities that mobile conferencing provides,&#8221; they write. &#8220;Respondents claimed to be doing all kinds of other tasks while on a mobile conference call. The multitasking activities included: getting other work done, sending emails, eating, texting, social media, video games, shopping and even going to the restroom.&#8221;</p>
<p>In fact, 27% of respondents said they&#8217;ve fallen asleep during a conference call.</p>
<p>While phone communication and conference calls are here to stay, voicemail is officially optional. Washington Post columnist <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/on-leadership/wp/2015/06/04/the-end-of-office-voice-mail/" target="_blank">Jena McGregor</a> writes that companies like Coca-Cola and JPMorgan Chase have disconnected voicemail entirely because it&#8217;s considered outdated and time-consuming.</p>
<p>&#8220;We&#8217;ve all sat through rambling, five-minute-long messages from people who really should have sent a two-line email. We&#8217;ve all screened numbers we didn&#8217;t want to answer and then — minutes later — gotten a redundant email or cell phone call. And we&#8217;ve all wondered if that automated, robotic voice saying &#8216;message. received. on. Thursday. June. 4th. at. 2. 53. pm&#8217; could really be any slower.&#8221;</p>
<h2>How Has Email Communication Evolved with Technology?</h2>
<p>While conference calls might drag employees down, there&#8217;s a general consensus that important communication should be funnelled through phone calls if two parties can&#8217;t meet in person. Most experts believe that email is no place for sensitive discussions.</p>
<p>&#8220;Never confront via email — it suggests you&#8217;re afraid of confrontation, which suggests you aren&#8217;t committed to your message,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/244492" target="_blank">Ross McCam mon, articles editor at GQ magazine</a>. &#8220;Plan what you&#8217;re going to say, but don&#8217;t script it out &#8230; like you would if you weren&#8217;t addressing a difficult matter. Point out the way you may be contributing to the problem.&#8221;</p>
<p>Email should be the last place you turn when trying to communicate with an employee. Even company chat boxes provide more of a back-and-forth conversational feel than an email.</p>
<p>&#8220;Don&#8217;t send a confrontation email to someone unless you&#8217;ve tried to get in touch with him or her every other possible way with no success, or if the problem is so urgent that he or she needs to be told immediately and the only available option is email,&#8221; agrees <a href="https://www.themuse.com/advice/confronting-an-employee-over-email-5-tips-for-doing-it-right" target="_blank">Lily Herman, managing editor at WayUp</a>.</p>
<p>However, if you&#8217;re on the fence about sending the email, Herman recommends use the six-sentence rule.</p>
<p>&#8220;If you feel like you can&#8217;t explain your case in six sentences or fewer, perhaps the subject is too big and hairy for email. After all, you don&#8217;t want to minimize a delicate situation.&#8221;</p>
<p>Outside of confrontational situations, email is getting ignored because workers think it&#8217;s slow. The response time and length required to draft it bog down the process more than chat or a phone call.</p>
<p>&#8220;Sending an email isn&#8217;t always the fastest way to say something,&#8221; says team members <a href="http://glasscanopy.com/send-email-pick-up-phone-how-to-decide/" target="_blank">glassCanopy</a>. &#8220;Sometimes, I spend more time drafting an email than I would in a phone call communicating the same information. That may be partly because I&#8217;m a wordsmith by trade; but also because emails that contain a lot of information deserve a higher level of curation.&#8221;</p>
<p>This is often because people use email when they want to document something that can be referenced later, or communicate specific instructions.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5162" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/email-1024x683.jpg" alt="email" width="1024" height="683" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/email-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/email-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/email-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/email-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/email.jpg 1677w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>How Does the Modern Workforce Use Chat?</h2>
<p>The frustrations behind long conference calls and tedious email chains have caused a new hero to arise in the world of office communication: chat boxes.</p>
<p>&#8220;Chat is far more efficient than long, drawn-out email chains (who likes those, anyway?),&#8221; says <a href="https://www.formassembly.com/blog/remote-teams-communicate/" target="_blank">Hannah Wright at FormAssembly</a>. &#8220;Plus, there&#8217;s one more bonus: It&#8217;s fun.</p>
<p>&#8220;One thing to keep in mind is that written text lacks the subtle cues of in-person conversation. With chat, you do need to be careful about how your words might be interpreted and possibly misunderstood. That&#8217;s why there&#8217;s an abundance of emoticons and gifs in our everyday chats — they&#8217;re useful in conveying the right nuances.&#8221;</p>
<p>Chat is one of the best ways for remote employees to ask quick questions from across the world and even get to know the people they work with better.</p>
<p>&#8220;When working remotely, team members don&#8217;t have a chance to make small talk with their neighbor in the next cubicle or discuss weekend plans by the coffeemaker,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.teambonding.com/5-team-bondingtips-for-remote-employees/" target="_blank">Samantha McDuffee for Teambonding</a>. &#8220;It&#8217;s that kind of personal chit-chat, however, that helps employees relate to each other.&#8221;</p>
<p>The best part is that chat creates an even plane, as in-house employees are using chat even more. This means remote employees aren&#8217;t left out of conversations (and in-house teams get to use emojis in their professional instruction).</p>
<p>&#8220;Trendy open-plan offices are infamous for their cacophonous din — they were originally designed to get workers across the office to strike up conversations that hopefully lead to innovative collaborations,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/users/2015/04/slack_and_the_office_chat_several_people_are_typing_who_s_working.html" target="_blank">Amanda Hess, writer for The New York Times</a>.</p>
<p>&#8220;While bosses are free to convene closed-door meetings, it&#8217;s hard for underlings to have a private word unless they physically leave the premises. But now, Slack has given every employee a virtual office door, and boy do we use them.&#8221;</p>
<p>If project management software has changed what we talk about, so that more teams are focusing on how things should get done, then it makes sense for chat to rise up as the leading communication tool. It&#8217;s the platform for quick questions and team collaboration, both of which are crucial for meeting deadlines and moving work forward.</p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
<em>©rawpixel/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/geralt-9301/" target="_blank"><em>geralt</em></a><em>, ©alexeyboldin/123RF Stock Photo</em></small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/project-management/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
