<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Workflow &#8211; teamfocus | project team management | web-based task management</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/workflow/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Workflows for teams</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 13:22:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	
	<item>
		<title>Distributed Down Under: 13 Australian Companies That Get Remote Teamwork</title>
		<link>/australian-companies/</link>
					<comments>/australian-companies/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 13:00:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5279</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you are struggling to understand how to manage a remote team, look to these 13 Australian companies for examples of best practices.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most companies in Australia struggle to integrate their <a href="https://www.teamfocus.me/hire-remote-employees/" >remote employees</a> into company operations and workflows.</p>
<p>It’s not that they fail to grasp the benefits of telecommuting, nor are they stuck in the mindset that employee productivity is measured by time spent in the office.</p>
<p>According to the team at <a href="http://www.launchgroup.com.au/2016/03/02/australian-management-not-equipped-to-deal-with-remote-workers/" >Launch Group</a>, the sticking point most companies have is actually understanding how to manage their remote team members. Less than half of Australian businesses offer senior management any special training in supervising distributed teams, Launch Group says, citing research from Regus. </p>
<p>Still, several companies in Australia have solved this onboarding problem — and some are growing rapidly thanks to their distributed teams.</p>
<p>The 13 companies below are ahead of the curve. If your company is struggling to understand how to manage a remote team, look to them for examples of best practices.</p>
<p></p>
<h2>X-Team</h2>
<p><a href="https://x-team.com/" >X-Team</a> brings together ad hoc teams of full-time developers for any clients who need to have software built. By being totally distributed, the company has the flexibility to scale its dev teams up or down to whatever the client’s needs are.</p>
<p>CEO Ryan Chartrand frequently writes on the X-Team blog about the challenges of leading such a company. One tip, he says, is to break the ice among team members by having each person host a Q&amp;A chat on Slack. </p>
<p>“For example, we do AMAs in our #travel channel whenever someone gets back from a nomading trip to another country,” he writes. “&#8230; It allows people an opportunity to learn something new from someone with hands-on experience and/or a ton of passion around the topic.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>Red Guava</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.redguava.com.au/" >Red Guava</a> is the company that built Cliniko, a healthcare practice management system that clinics and hospitals in 55 different countries are currently using.</p>
<p>The company’s apparent secret to success is pretty straightforward, too: Focus on people. Not in a sterile, “people-centric outlook” kind of way, but in a way that demonstrates real compassion. </p>
<p>For example, one of Cliniko’s killer features is its support community, which includes an active forum plus responsive phone and email communication. And internally, the company extends that same kind of compassion to its team: Standard terms of employment include full-time pay for a 30-hour workweek.</p>
<p></p>
<h2>Envato</h2>
<p><a href="https://envato.com/" >Envato</a> is one of Australia’s great success stories. Millions of people tap this marketplace for creative work — website building, software development, graphic design, etc. — every year.</p>
<p>As with Red Guava above, Envato’s growth is built on a pretty simple premise: “We believe good ideas deserve a chance to grow. We believe people deserve to earn a living doing what they love. We believe in making it easy to get things done.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>WP Curve</h2>
<p><a href="https://wpcurve.com/" >WP Curve</a>, which announced it was joining GoDaddy at the end of 2016, has been one of the Internet’s go-to providers for WordPress help for a few years. Note that WordPress powers about a quarter of all websites, which is why WP Curve’s team is handling more than 4,000 jobs per month.</p>
<p>And like X-Team, WP Curve has employees all over the map. That flexibility allows the company to offer 24-7 support to WordPress users, no matter the time zone.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/workspace-1024x682.jpg" alt="workspace" width="1024" height="682" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5282" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/workspace-1024x682.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/workspace-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/workspace-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/workspace-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/workspace.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>SuiteBox</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.suitebox.com/" >SuiteBox</a>’s entire offering is built on remote workflows. The company has patented a handful of tools and processes so that its clients can conclude deals remotely. This includes group video conferencing, document collaboration and even legal digital signatures.</p>
<p>Banks, financial firms and insurance companies especially have adopted SuiteBox because no longer having to meet clients on site lets them scale their operations exponentially. </p>
<p></p>
<h2>Campaign Monitor</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.campaignmonitor.com/" >Campaign Monitor</a> is actually better-known for being one of Australia’s best places to work. The email marketing provider — which turned heads a few years ago by closing a quarter-billion-dollar funding round — does leave room for remote roles among its team members, though.</p>
<p>The perks there are nice, too: Remote employees receive an additional allowance, a brand new Macbook Air, and ample flex and holiday time so they can find the work/life balance that best suits them.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most important lesson we can learn from Campaign Monitor’s success is the importance of values. These lay the foundation for company culture, which like everything else has to be strong enough to scale rapidly at a tech company, <a href="https://www.virgin.com/entrepreneur/difference-between-culture-and-values" >CEO Alex Bard</a> says. </p>
<p>Having that kind of values focus changes the discussion. It’s no longer about where an employee is located — the office or elsewhere — but whether you have in place “the framework on which to base key decisions like hiring talent into new offices.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>Appen</h2>
<p><a href="http://appen.com/" >Appen</a> is one of the veterans on this list. Founded in Sydney in 1996, Appen was building out linguistic technologies long before <a href="http://a16z.com/2016/08/20/why-software-is-eating-the-world/" >software began to eat the world</a>. In those 21 years, Appen has navigated a company merger and a name change, and it has partnered with some of the biggest names in technology.</p>
<p>For example, in 2010 after the Haitian earthquake Appen worked with Microsoft to build machine translation tools so disaster relief teams could understand Haitian Creole.</p>
<p></p>
<h2>Canva</h2>
<p><a href="https://about.canva.com/" >Canva</a> is among the best-known and fastest-growing startups in Australia. As at Campaign Monitor, Canva’s executive team understood that a tech startup needs to be flexible with its employees to scale at the speed it’s built for. That’s why employees are given the option to work from home as much as they need to.</p>
<p>“We know people work best when they’re happy and challenged to keep getting even better at what they do,” the company says. “So at Canva, we look after our team.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>INCSUB</h2>
<p><a href="https://incsub.com/" >INCSUB</a>, short for “Incorporated Subversion,” builds some of the most-used blogging tools for WordPress users. The company’s headquarters are in Melbourne, but its team is located all over the world. In fact, the company says just about every time zone in the world is represented on its team.</p>
<p>This policy, the company says, means it can recruit the best and brightest from anywhere. The company also puts a special emphasis on diversity because providing equal opportunity employment to all applicants makes the company better.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/remote-employee-1024x660.jpg" alt="working online from home" width="1024" height="660" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5280" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/remote-employee-1024x660.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/remote-employee-300x193.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/remote-employee-768x495.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/remote-employee-600x387.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/04/remote-employee.jpg 1706w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Quiip</h2>
<p><a href="http://quiip.com.au/" >Quiip</a> provides online community management for companies around the world, who hire Quiip to moderate forums, update social feeds and respond to blog comments, among other things.</p>
<p>This means there is a 24-7 demand for what Quiip’s team does.</p>
<p>To meet that demand, the company has a policy of what it calls radical flexibility: “The notion of the 40 (or 60) hour week is a legacy of the long-gone days of industry and we can do better. Why not create jobs that are 10/20/30 hours a week. Not job-share, not part-time, just simply a role in itself that suits the employee.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>CloudPeeps</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.cloudpeeps.com/" >CloudPeeps</a> — which makes the list by having an Australian founder, though the company is based in San Francisco — is a marketplace for freelancers and service providers. These professionals are vetted and then connected with clients for specific projects.</p>
<p>Founder and CEO Kate Kendall was herself a freelancer before she launched the company in 2015. Kendall spoke with <a href="https://remote.co/company/cloudpeeps/" >Remote.co</a> at the time to discuss the challenges of building relationships on a distributed team:</p>
<p>“We place a strong emphasis on transparency, authenticity and being direct. We do monthly one-on-one feedback sessions, which we call ‘pair calls,’ where we run through challenges, positive feedback and constructive areas to improve. These are non-hierarchical where openness and honesty is encouraged. It doesn’t matter if you’re the CEO or the newest member of the team — we share how you can improve coming from a kind place.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>Fifty Acres</h2>
<p><a href="http://fiftyacres.com.au/" >Fifty Acres</a> is the first virtual communications and government agency in Australia. The agency’s principal, Jo Scard, says she baked remote work flexibility into the foundation of her company because the rigidity of a 9-to-5 schedule excluded so many working mothers.</p>
<p>“We don’t need an office,” Scard tells <a href="https://www.myob.com/au/blog/remote-working-made-these-3-companies-successful/" >Nina Sochon</a> (a New Zealand-based consultant who has built a career by teaching company leaders how to help their remote teams thrive — the very weak spot SMEs identified in the Regus research). </p>
<p>“&#8230; As a result we can avoid passing on office costs to our clients, which has helped to keep our charges down.”</p>
<p></p>
<h2>Jobvibe</h2>
<p><a href="http://jobvibe.me/" >Jobvibe</a> is another Australian company that builds remote working into the core of its offering. </p>
<p>Jobvibe’s software lets teams share feedback in real time so that companies can establish a culture of transparency and trust, even if team members don’t share an office or time zone.</p>
<p>While the company’s headquarters are in Sydney, it relies on a network of contractors around the world build out and scale up the business. The secret to making that structure work? Trust.</p>
<p>“Everyone is treated as an adult, so we work from home from time to time, and we don&#8217;t care so much about when you start or finish,” the company says. “It&#8217;s about getting the job done.”</p>
<p>
<em><small>images by: ©verbaska/123RF Stock Photo, <a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/TheDigitalWay-3008341/" >TheDigitalWay</a>, <a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/350543-350543/" >350543</a></small></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/australian-companies/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>5 Types of Meetings (And How to Make Your Employees Love Them)</title>
		<link>/types-of-meetings/</link>
					<comments>/types-of-meetings/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 11:06:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5270</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[These are the 5 types of meetings you frequently encounter in the workplace, and how an effective leader can get the most out of them.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most organizations have a love-hate relationships with meetings. Some companies ban meetings at certain times or days, while others feel like more meetings will solve all of their problems. </p>
<p>However, the meeting length and frequency isn’t nearly as important as the meeting content.</p>
<p>To make your meetings more productive — and to improve the happiness of employees who sit through them — we’ve created a guide to the five types of meetings you encounter in the workspace, and how you can make the most of them.</p>
<h2>1. Status Updates and Check-Ins</h2>
<p>Every company has these meetings on a regular basis, from daily scrums to end-of-week reviews. While they’re often appreciated by employees, they can get out of hand.</p>
<p>“The stand-up became enormously popular as a core practice of software teams using an agile development methodology,” <a target="_blank" href="http://blog.lucidmeetings.com/blog/4-ways-status-meetings-remote-team-that-work">Elise Keith</a> writes at Lucid Meetings. “Since then, it’s gained many names (daily Scrum, daily meeting) and spread to other departments, who liked the fast, energetic pace.” </p>
<p>Update meetings should last no more than 15-minutes for daily scrum reviews, and no more than an hour for weekly or monthly check-ins. Anything longer, and you’ve lost your audience.</p>
<p>“Since the time is short, the team members should know exactly what they would speak at the meeting,” <a target="_blank" href="http://www.scrum-institute.org/blog/10-Tips-To-Get-The-Best-Out-Of-Your-Daily-Scrum-Meetings">Nirav Patel</a> writes at The Scrum Institute. “Their speech should be strictly limited to what they did the day before, what they plan to do today and what are the difficulties they are facing in meeting their goals. </p>
<p>“For this, the scrum leader should make it clear to the team members what he expects to hear from them at the meeting. Anything off the topic should be immediately interrupted.” </p>
<p>Furthermore, not all problems need to be solved in one specific meeting. Place items that require more time or discussion in the “parking lot,” and address them at a later time or during a one-on-one with those involved. </p>
<p>“The purpose of [these] meetings is to provide information,” <a target="_blank" href="https://www.hrbartender.com/2015/training/the-only-3-reasons-to-hold-a-business-meeting/">Sharlyn Lauby</a> writes as HR Bartender. “The reason they’re so dreaded is because, when there’s nothing to convey, the meeting still happens.” </p>
<p>Almost all employees have languished through a pointless meeting with no updates, praying it ends early. Conversely, other teams have scheduled meetings, but continue to cancel them every week to the point where they’re completely forgotten. The key to these update meetings is to make sure actual news is shared, or they should be held less often.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/startup.jpg" alt="startup" width="798" height="531" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5275" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/startup.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/startup-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/startup-768x511.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/startup-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>2. Decision-Making Meetings</h2>
<p>Decision meetings tend to be the most heated within the company. Representatives from multiple departments want to make sure they’re heard and the company moves in the best interest of their team. </p>
<p>“For continuity, it’s helpful to tie all discussions back to your broader strategic goals,” <a target="_blank" href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/272078">David Chait</a> writes at Entrepreneur. “There are many ways to do this, but a dead simple one is to simply start your regular team meetings by posting or quickly running through those goals.”</p>
<p>This ensures that all decisions made by the assembled team will be in the best interest of the company, even if certain members are inconvenienced. </p>
<p>After the goals, the moderator should explain the process for finding a solution. By explaining this before the debate begins, employees can understand how everyone came to a solution at the end. </p>
<p>“Some decisions may call for unanimous agreement, while others may best be done as a decision by the owner,” <a target="_blank" href="http://www.quickanddirtytips.com/productivity/meetings/how-to-run-a-decision-making-meeting?page=1">Stever Robbins</a> writes at Quick and Dirty Tips. “When people agree on process first, then even if that process chooses an option some people don&#8217;t like, they&#8217;ll usually agree to abide by the decision.” If people are unaware that the manager can override them at anytime, they could feel suppressed when the meeting comes to an abrupt end. </p>
<p>By explaining the process and goals, the team moderator is able to reduce friction when people disagree on certain decisions. </p>
<p>“One of the most important aspects of decision meetings is to create unity around the decision that is created,” writes the team at <a target="_blank" href="http://meetingsift.com/decision-making-meetings/">Meeting Sift</a>. “When each participant feels their opinion has been fully considered as part of the decision making process they are more likely to feel ownership of the decision, even in cases when it is not the outcome they hoped for.”</p>
<p>By following these rules, and making sure every employee is listened to and treated with respect, managers can ensure decision-making meetings stay professional and productive. </p>
<h2>3. Creative Planning and Brainstorming Sessions</h2>
<p>On the opposite end of the decision spectrum is the creative brainstorming sessions, which tend to go long because employees are distracted and having fun.</p>
<p>“Meetings want to suck,” <a target="_blank" href="https://heleo.com/jake-knapp-brainstorming-hurting-meetings-success/5789/">Jake Knapp</a> writes at Heleo. “Two of their favorite suckiness tactics are group brainstorming and group negotiation. Give them half a chance, and they’ll waste your time, sap your energy, and leave you with poor ideas and a watered-down decision. But meetings don’t have to be that way.”</p>
<p>Despite their power to hijack an afternoon, many amazing concepts and solutions come from these meetings. </p>
<p>“The ability to contribute to a shared vision is the magic behind those 2 a.m. breakthroughs that are part of every startup story,” Veer Gidwaney of <a target="_blank" href="http://www.inc.com/veer-gidwaney/how-to-hold-a-weekly-team-meeting-without-wasting-people-s-time.html">Maxwell Health</a> writes at Inc. “The human collective is much more creative than one person working alone, because employees&#8217; individual experiences bump up against one another, forming new associations and revealing intriguing possibilities.”</p>
<p>By adding structure to your meeting, whether you’re brainstorming a client solution or planning a fundraiser, you should be able to stay on task and leave with actionable ideas. </p>
<p>“A lot of creatives are quick on their feet and love to spitball ideas,” <a target="_blank" href="http://www.unseminary.com/9-elements-of-effective-creative-brainstorm-meetings/">Rich Birch</a> writes at Unseminary. “But not every creative person is wired this way. Not everyone develops their best ideas in the midst of a brainstorming meeting. Some people thrive with time and thought. Communicate the scope of the discussion beforehand to aid folks who like to mull over ideas.”</p>
<p>This also allows your team to conduct research beforehand about the topic, so they’re better informed when coming up with ideas. </p>
<p>“It&#8217;s [the] moderator&#8217;s duty to note down all the ideas on a whiteboard or anything else as per the convenience and discuss them with the participants,” Bhupendra Sharma writes at <a target="_blank" href="https://yourstory.com/2016/09/successful-brainstorming-session/">YourStory</a>. “For this, a brainstorming session can be divided into two or more sub-sessions. While the first half can be dedicated to the idea-sharing activity, the other half can be devoted to discussing the pros and cons of those ideas.”</p>
<p>Not only does this limit segues that take the discussion off track, but it also lets teams return to past ideas and use them at a different time without needing to call a fresh meeting. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/laptop.jpg" alt="laptop" width="798" height="531" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5274" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/laptop.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/laptop-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/laptop-768x511.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/laptop-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>4. Collaborative and Planning Meetings</h2>
<p>Collaborative meetings are becoming more popular as a way to kick off a project and make sure it has the appropriate follow-through. </p>
<p>“39% of employees surveyed in a recent study felt that people within their organizations did not collaborate enough, while 86% of executives and employees cite lack of collaboration or ineffective communication for workplace failures,” <a target="_blank" href="http://www.wespire.com/8-steps-to-improve-workplace-collaboration/">Elliot Gordon</a> writes at WeSpire. </p>
<p>“The core benefit of collaboration is the ability to share knowledge and expertise quickly and easily, and this sharing leads to better products and innovations, which in turn drives better profitability, employee engagement, and employee satisfaction.”</p>
<p>These meetings often work to map out a strategy, decide on certain elements, and assign tasks to complete afterward. The challenge of these meetings is that they can be dense and overwhelming to attendees who struggle to keep up. </p>
<p>“Social scientists are discovering evidence that the human brain is wired to pay attention and absorb information for 10 to 18 minutes before it begins to tune out,” Ade at the <a target="_blank" href="https://jell.com/blog/productive-meetings-science/">Jell</a> blog writes. “The more information an audience is asked to consume, the more intense the mental load becomes. Eventually this ‘cognitive backlog’ becomes so heavy that listeners drop it all and fail to remember anything at all.” </p>
<p>Consider that next time you try to map out an entire project in one sitting. Before your attendees arrive at the meeting, send out an agenda of what will be covered and when. This way, your team comes prepared and knows what to expect. </p>
<p>“Looking at your agenda will give you a rough idea of how much time you can afford to devote to each item, because time is an important element of team meetings,” <a target="_blank" href="http://recruitloop.com/blog/5-steps-to-running-an-effective-team-meeting/">Paul Slezak</a> writes at RecruitLoop. “They should start on time and only go for the allotted time. If some items on the agenda require more time than is available, they should be moved to the next meeting or, if urgent, a separate meeting should be held with those immediately involved.” </p>
<p>In some cases, the actual task assigned at the completion of the agenda item might be for two or three people to meet individually to come up with a plan or make a decision. </p>
<p>“In general, meetings and obligations tend to fill the space you give them,” <a target="_blank" href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/281131">Cameron Herold</a> writes at Entrepreneur. “Estimate how long you think a meeting or task will take, then cut it in half. By limiting time, you increase your productivity, maximize efficiency and create a more highly profitable system of time management.”</p>
<p>If you schedule an hour-long meeting with only 30-minutes of content to cover, then your meeting will still last an hour. Try to limit the time to what is absolutely necessary, so your team can focus on doing instead of just planning. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/training.jpg" alt="training" width="798" height="531" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5276" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/training.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/training-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/training-768x511.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/training-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>5. Training and Professional Improvement Hours</h2>
<p>The last type of meeting doesn’t directly impact the sales and revenue of a company, but it can improve the company in the long run. These sessions typically involve one or two presenters working with a handful of employees. While these meetings aren’t stressful, they can get boring if the subject isn’t relevant. </p>
<p>“Let employees choose training topics,” <a target="_blank" href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/larry-alton/stop-neglecting-employee-_b_8954736.html">Larry Alton</a> writes at the Huffington Post. “Nobody knows your employees better than themselves. Using our IT example, an employee struggling with a particular security solution has incentive to take a class on this topic because they know that it’s an opportunity to get better at their job and continue advancement.” </p>
<p>This also ensures the training will be relevant and fresh, and training meetings won’t go unattended after the first few sessions.</p>
<p>“Employees who don’t love learning can make your training sessions a nightmare,” <a target="_blank" href="https://smallbiztrends.com/2015/06/small-business-training-new-employees.html">Drew Hendricks</a> writes at SmallBizTrends. “If you want successful trainings, begin by encouraging self-motivation and a love of learning.” </p>
<p>These benefits will extend beyond training meetings. Self-motivated employees can work by themselves and will research new ideas and possibilities before they come to you with a problem. This takes the burden off of you as a manager to constantly put out their fires. </p>
<p>“Employee training shouldn’t just be based on acquiring specific knowledge for a position,” <a target="_blank" href="http://www.polleverywhere.com/blog/train-to-retain-7-tips-for-better-employee-training/">Heather Huhman</a> writes at Poll Everywhere. “Focus training efforts on building an understanding the company mission, organizational culture, values, and goals. Through this specific training, employees will garner a greater understanding, interest, and respect for company culture, allowing them to better utilize it on a day-to-day basis.” </p>
<p>This gives them a sense of purpose by showing them where the company is going (and how they can help achieve it) while instilling a sense of importance and value in their work — which turns into loyalty. </p>
<p>With this information, you can ensure that your employees approach every meeting confident that they will accomplish their goals without leaving drained, ignored, or bored. You’re proving that their time is valuable, and that you value what they do throughout the day. Soon your whole office — not just your meetings — will be buzzing with efficiency. </p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
<em>©goodluz/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a target="_blank" href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/StartupStockPhotos-690514/"><em>StartupStockPhotos</em></a><em>, </em><a target="_blank" href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/jamesoladujoye-3409212/"><em>jamesoladujoye</em></a><em>, ©rawpixel/123RF Stock Photo</em><br />
</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/types-of-meetings/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Lead Engaging Meetings Your Employees Actually Want to Attend</title>
		<link>/engaging-meetings/</link>
					<comments>/engaging-meetings/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 18:22:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Entrepreneurship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5215</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Meetings are a crucial element to almost any business, but they&#8217;re also one of the most universally disliked parts of the job. In fact, 47 percent of employees think meetings are unproductive, and 76 percent say they aren&#8217;t even necessary. Unfortunately, this disdain counters management best practices of checking in regularly as a means to...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Meetings are a crucial element to almost any business, but they&#8217;re also one of the most universally disliked parts of the job. </p>
<p>In fact, <a href="http://blog.hubspot.com/sales/why-we-hate-meetings-so-much#sm.001xjr46h18eafi9pjw27zcloq10q" target="_blank">47 percent</a> of employees think meetings are unproductive, and 76 percent say they aren&#8217;t even necessary. Unfortunately, this disdain counters management best practices of checking in regularly as a means to improve communication. </p>
<p>It&#8217;s possible that most employees are simply shooting the messenger — or in this case shooting the dial-in number. Meetings themselves aren&#8217;t bad, but so many people run them so poorly that the experience is tainted. </p>
<p>Follow the advice of these 16 experts to improve your meeting style and better engage your employees. </p>
<h2>Understand Your Role as Meeting Leader</h2>
<p>The success of a meeting falls on the person who called it. However, that person doesn&#8217;t always have to be the facilitator that keeps the team moving. In some cases, your implicit bias might mean inviting upper management or a peer from another department to lead the meeting for you. </p>
<p>&#8220;If your meeting is a daily standup, a weekly team check-in, or a similar kind of non-controversial status meeting, your bias probably doesn&#8217;t matter much,&#8221; <a href="http://blog.lucidmeetings.com/blog/5-tips-to-lead-and-facilitate-a-meeting-simultaneously" target="_blank">Chris Higgins writes for Lucid Meetings</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;But let&#8217;s say you&#8217;re deciding a major strategy that affects the coming year of work. Or you&#8217;ve got an angry client and you&#8217;re trying to save the account. &#8230; In these cases, your leader bias prevents you from being an effective facilitator. When the stakes are high, trying to fill both roles is truly risky. If you face this situation, find somebody else to facilitate or be prepared to risk a bad outcome for the meeting.&#8221;</p>
<p>Along with finding a facilitator, the meeting manager needs to make sure everyone who should hear the information is invited. However, this requires a delicate balance between keeping the team informed and crowding the room. </p>
<p>&#8220;The scheduler, usually the boss, will often throw people onto the roster even if there&#8217;s only a small chance that the topic is relevant to them or that they&#8217;ll have something meaningful to contribute,&#8221; <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/244499" target="_blank">Anna Johansson writes for Entrepreneur</a>. &#8220;This inflates the number of people attending, which is sometimes seen as a good thing — more minds means more opportunities to solve the problem at hand — but it&#8217;s actually quite damaging. Not only does it draw more employees away from work, it also muddles the focus and presents more opportunities for distraction.&#8221; </p>
<p>Various experts have different beliefs about ideal meeting sizes — Five? Seven? 10? — but all agree that you should agree on a cap to prevent overcrowding. </p>
<p>Finally, the meeting manager also needs to inform upper management and employees who missed the section about any resolutions and updates discussed. </p>
<p>&#8220;The leader has the additional responsibility of keeping senior managers involved and informed through effective communication and feedback,&#8221; <a href="https://www.thebalance.com/meeting-leader-roles-and-responsibilities-1918732" target="_blank">Susan Heathfield writes for The Balance</a>. &#8220;Building ownership from employees outside of the team or meeting, especially organization leaders, ensures that the team or meeting is successful at developing, implementing and integrating its solutions or ideas.&#8221;</p>
<p>Once you take ownership of your meetings and lead them responsibility, you can start cutting out the waste the frustrates attendees. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/meeting-1024x693.jpg" alt="business people meeting conference discussion working concept" width="1024" height="693" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5219" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/meeting-1024x693.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/meeting-300x203.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/meeting-768x520.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/meeting-600x406.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/meeting.jpg 1666w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Create a Plan for Every Call, Chat or Session</h2>
<p>Before you walk into a conference room or pick up the phone, you and your attendees should have a clear picture of what will be discussed during this meeting. </p>
<p>&#8220;Unless designated as a brainstorming or strategic session, actual meeting time should be used to report findings, make suggestions or answer questions,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.lindaswindling.com/the-worst-meeting-ever-how-to-keep-meetings-on-track/" target="_blank">Linda Swindling, speaker and negotiation expert</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;A board member&#8217;s or leader&#8217;s time should be spent giving direction, deciding a course of action, discussing areas of concern and granting approval to proceed. Allow individuals, task forces and committees to do the heavy lifting and research so that meetings can stay high level.&#8221;</p>
<p>This means daily or weekly check-ins should follow the same format so your team can build a routine. One-off meetings should have an ad hoc list of items to cover. </p>
<p>&#8220;Make the meeting about helping your attendees leave better as a result of having invested their time with you and/ or the group,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.inspireyourpeople.com/blog/better-meetings/" target="_blank">Sam Parker at Inspire Your People</a>. &#8220;[Use this] helpful question to guide you: ‘What do I hope to have people doing and thinking about in the days/weeks/months following the meeting?'&#8221;</p>
<p>Some companies do this by assigning an employee to every task discussed during the process. </p>
<p>&#8220;Every project component or task has a ‘DRI,'&#8221; <a href="http://99u.com/articles/7220/how-to-run-your-meetings-like-apple-and-google" target="_blank">Sean Blanda writes for 99u</a>. &#8220;Apple breeds accountability at meetings by having a Directly Responsible Individual whose name appears next to all of the agenda items they are responsible for. With every task tagged, there&#8217;s rarely any confusion about who should be getting what done.&#8221;</p>
<p>This DRI list can be applied before a meeting so employees prepare, and then adjusted for takeaways and assignments as people leave. </p>
<h2>Change Up the Way You Run Meetings</h2>
<p>Once you have the structure established and your employees know that your meetings will stay on track, you can start breaking the rules and become more flexible with the agenda.</p>
<p>&#8220;If you want people engaged, you have to be sure to include them,&#8221; says the team at <a href="http://blog.achievers.com/2015/09/5-ways-to-make-meetings-more-engaging-2/" target="_blank">Achievers</a>. &#8220;Think about implementing different strategies to get people sharing ideas, collaborating and speaking with one another. </p>
<p>&#8220;To do this, try routinely hosting a round at different points in a meeting where participants can contribute, share opinions, and even voice complaints. Think about breaking people up into groups or partners, or even using ‘speed dating,&#8217; where everyone switches partners quickly to bounce ideas off one another.&#8221; </p>
<p>This works especially well for longer presentations and brainstorming sessions. Different strategies also tap into multiple learning types, not just the auditory learners on your team. </p>
<p>&#8220;We all learn in different ways, so mix up the media and engage your audience through various senses,&#8221; <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/work-in-progress/2014/11/14/six-ways-to-avoid-death-by-powerpoint/#29a6455c34cb" target="_blank">Kristi Hedges writes for Forbes</a>. &#8220;See how you can illustrate your points through photos, music, demos and videos. It can even be helpful to provide something tangible for your audience to hold in their hands. I once saw a speaker pass around a watch his grandfather had made to illustrate the diversity of entrepreneurship in our society.&#8221;</p>
<p>Remember, it&#8217;s OK to place agenda items on the back burner, either by moving them to a next meeting or stopping the discussion to cover more important factors. </p>
<p>&#8220;You do not need to resolve every problem on the agenda; simply begin the discussion and when you are a few minutes away from the allotted time, suggest that the areas which remain unresolved, or in contention, be revisited at the next meeting,&#8221; <a href="http://hubpages.com/business/Facilitation_Tips-A_is_for_Agenda_Creating_a_Roadmap_for_Successful_Meetings" target="_blank">Kathy Stutzman writes for HubPages</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;This will only work if you intentionally place the issue in the parking lot and then place it as a priority at the next meeting and actually revisit the topic. Even if the topic is still contentious or time-consuming when you meet again, it needs to be revisited if you say it will be revisited.&#8221;</p>
<p>This serves two goals: </p>
<ol>
<li>It proves to your team that you won&#8217;t get bogged down by one issue, </li>
<li>and it shows that you won&#8217;t let important issues get swept under the rug — thus instilling a sense of trust that you will run meetings effectively. </li>
</ol>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/beard-1024x683.jpg" alt="two employees discussing electronic data at meeting" width="1024" height="683" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5218" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/beard-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/beard-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/beard-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/beard-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/beard.jpg 1678w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Identify and Talk With Toxic Attendees </h2>
<p>If the meeting agenda isn&#8217;t the problem, then it&#8217;s possible the attendees are. We discussed one way to mitigate this earlier by limiting the number of people in the room or on the call, but you may need to address the issue with the group or individually if a few people are causing problems. </p>
<p>&#8220;Debbie and Donnie Downer show up to almost every community meeting, it seems, and meet every idea and proposal with a reason (or five) why it&#8217;ll never work,&#8221; <a href="http://www.citylab.com/navigator/2016/02/community-meeting-etiquette/463434/" target="_blank">Steve Holt writes for CityLab</a>. &#8220;It&#8217;s not to say we shouldn&#8217;t speak up if we see a fatal flaw in the plan, or draw on our experience, but when certain attendees — or even facilitators — constantly question and sow negativity, the optimism for solving the problem is severely compromised.&#8221;</p>
<p>In addition to negative employees, managers also have to contend with employees who derail the conversation or get distracted easily. </p>
<p>&#8220;It&#8217;s frustrating when you and your team are trying to sort through the details of a tricky project, only to have someone derail the conversation by completely changing the subject,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.themuse.com/advice/3-signs-youre-talking-way-too-much-in-meetings-and-how-to-stop-being-that-person" target="_blank">Rich Moy at The Muse</a>. &#8220;Although you probably have good intentions and usually aren&#8217;t trying to bring up a new topic entirely, it&#8217;s a time waster, especially because the team now likely has two unresolved issues to get through in a limited amount of time.&#8221;</p>
<p>Often, these people have good intentions. They&#8217;re just not reading the room and understanding the flaws in their behavior. </p>
<p>&#8220;Most people who talk too much don&#8217;t realize they do it,&#8221; <a href="http://time.com/money/3701528/career-mistake-talking-too-much/" target="_blank">Donna Rosato writes for Time</a>. &#8220;Whether it&#8217;s fueled by insecurity or overconfidence, however, this quality can be deadly to one&#8217;s career — especially these days.</p>
<p>&#8220;&#8230; If you can&#8217;t get to the point in a meeting, your boss may wonder about your ability to communicate with higher ups or clients. Prattling on in an interview could obscure the points that you&#8217;re trying to make, and hamper your chances at getting the job.&#8221;</p>
<p>Yes, it will be hard to talk with these team members about their meeting behavior. But if it is done in a constructive way, they could become better employees because of it. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/office-1024x678.jpg" alt="office" width="1024" height="678" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5220" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/office-1024x678.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/office-300x199.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/office-768x509.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/office-600x398.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/office.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Decide Whether Video Conferencing is Right for Your Team</h2>
<p>In the digital realm, more companies are turning to video calls to replace traditional dial-in numbers, which has been met with mixed reviews from remote and telecommuting audiences. </p>
<p>&#8220;When you have a team spread around the country — or a team that just likes to work from home — video conferencing seems like a way to make people feel like they&#8217;re together in the same room,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/business/the_ladder/2016/06/video_conferencing_is_the_worst_way_to_conduct_meetings.html" target="_blank">L.V. Anderson, associate editor at Slate</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;However, many people work from home because they don&#8217;t want to be in the same room as other people. One of the most appealing parts of working from home is slouching on the sofa in your pajamas with unkempt hair on days when you&#8217;re not up for making yourself presentable. Video conferencing forces you to make yourself, and your surroundings, presentable.&#8221; </p>
<p>While seeing your co-worker unkempt and reporting from their couch is unprofessional, video calls can also be downright disgusting. </p>
<p>&#8220;Sadly, 10% of people have reported seeing someone pick their nose during a meeting,&#8221; says the team at <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/sc/video-conference-things-to-avoid-2015-8" target="_blank">join.me</a>. &#8220;No matter how discreet you think you&#8217;re being, keep in mind that your face is enlarged on someone&#8217;s screen. To be safe, just don&#8217;t touch your face at all.&#8221;</p>
<p>However, there are psychological benefits to facing your co-workers and seeing their pores up close, and you may decide that your team communication and understanding improves because of it. </p>
<p>&#8220;By consistently seeing your coworker&#8217;s expressions, you get more comfortable reading and understanding how their body language matches (or plays against!) their words and mood,&#8221; <a href="https://trust.guidestar.org/blog/2015/02/03/stop-the-excuses-4-reasons-to-start-using-video-calls/" target="_blank">Anisha Singh writes for the GuideStar blog</a>. &#8220;[Video calls] will be awkward at first. But it gets easier. With practice, video calls are such an advantage! You can see your coworker&#8217;s eyes, read their body language, and at the end of the day, you&#8217;re better able to communicate with the people you work with on a daily basis.&#8221;</p>
<p>At the very least, you can use video calls to make sure everyone stays alert and focused during the meeting. </p>
<p>&#8220;A lot of people use conference calls as found time to catch up on their email or RSS feeds,&#8221; says <a href="https://michaelhyatt.com/never-do-another-conference-call.html" target="_blank">Michael Hyatt</a>. &#8220;That might be the consequence of the organizer just not knowing how to run a meeting, but we&#8217;ve found that visual contact keeps everyone engaged, and that means meetings go quicker and more gets done.&#8221;</p>
<p>There are countless ways to make employees hate meetings. You can call them too often, keep them unstructured, and invite too many irrelevant people. </p>
<p>However, by keeping your meetings engaging and controlled, you can boost morale and improve the productivity of your team. </p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
<a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/Unsplash-242387/" target="_blank"><em>Unsplash</em></a><em>, ©rawpixel/123RF Stock Photo, ©pressmaster/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/Jo_Johnston-1865729/" target="_blank"><em>Jo_Johnston</em></a><br />
</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/engaging-meetings/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>5 Types of Problematic Remote Employees [infographic]</title>
		<link>/problematic-remote-employees/</link>
					<comments>/problematic-remote-employees/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 15:56:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5200</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Problematic remote employees can be a challenge. But by knowing your team better, you can understand behavior and create policies that work for everyone.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Recent studies by <a href="http://globalworkplaceanalytics.com/resources/costs-benefits" target="_blank">Global Workplace Analytics</a> have found that 37% of employees would take a pay cut of 10% if they could work from home. Many employees crave the freedom, flexibility, and convenience of remote work. </p>
<p>But that doesn&#8217;t necessarily mean they&#8217;re cut out for the job. In some cases, distractions pop up that cut into employee productivity. In others, insecurities lead to overwork and job frustration. </p>
<p>Managers often struggle to identify why their employees are having problems. In a traditional office, they could walk over and talk to that employee, or they would be able to identify the problem just from observation. </p>
<p>This is harder for remote workers, who might be in different time zones and rely primarily on digital communication. To make it easier for them to understand what is happening, we created the infographic below: </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/TE126-IG.jpg" alt="te126-ig" width="800" height="5626" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5201" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/TE126-IG.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/TE126-IG-768x5401.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/11/TE126-IG-600x4220.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /> </p>
<h4>Embed this infographic on your site:</h4>
<p><textarea cols="60" rows="6">&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.teamfocus.me/5-types-problematic-remote-employees&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/TE126-IG.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;5 Types of Problematic Remote Employees&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.teamfocus.me/5-types-problematic-remote-employees&quot;&gt;5 Types of Problematic Remote Employees – www.teamfocus.me&lt;/a&gt;</textarea></p>
<p>Not all employees are a good fit for remote work setups. Some — especially those who don&#8217;t have previous telecommuting experience — get easily distracted by their surroundings. They think they&#8217;re multi-tasking by running a load of laundry during the day or clearing the dishwasher during a conference call, but they&#8217;re really just tuned out. </p>
<p>At best, this person is distracted. At worst, they&#8217;re a liability when they miss deadlines and show up unprepared. </p>
<p>Of course, not all hard-to-reach employees are distracted. Some remote workers enjoy working from home to reduce distractions found in the workplace. According to <a href="https://www.surepayroll.com/resources/blog/productivity-prohibitors-how-to-stop-them-in-their-tracks" target="_blank">Surepayroll</a>, 61 percent of employees said loud colleagues were the biggest distraction in the office, and 86 percent said they hit maximum productivity when working alone. It&#8217;s entirely possible that this employee has signed out of chat boxes and closed their emails as a way to eliminate distractions completely. </p>
<p>This silence is what frustrates some managers. They want to know that their remote teams are working hard and able to meet their deadlines, which they can&#8217;t do if their employees are unreachable. </p>
<p>This actually creates a double-edged sword: Checking in distracts employees, but managers need to contact them for regular updates and confirmation. </p>
<p>These are just two types of employees whom managers have to deal with when leading remote teams. In every case, though, by knowing your remote employees&#8217; personalities, you can better understand their behavior and create policies that will keep them focused, on-task and accountable.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/problematic-remote-employees/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>6 Reasons Embracing Failure is Crucial to Project Management</title>
		<link>/embracing-failure/</link>
					<comments>/embracing-failure/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2016 15:54:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mental Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Psychology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5179</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How a company reacts to failure says more than when it succeeds. Here’s why embracing failure is a crucial part of work and how to make the most of it.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Our society tends to favor constant positivity. Parents worry about scolding their kids, we always answer &#8220;fine&#8221; or &#8220;good&#8221; when asked how we&#8217;re doing, and we&#8217;re told to chin up whenever something bad happens. </p>
<p>This state of constant happiness has entered the business world, where employees are expected to constantly be successful and fill their day with new wins. </p>
<p>This isn&#8217;t always the case. </p>
<p>Sometimes we fail.</p>
<p>Sometimes we lose. </p>
<p>How a company, or even a department, reacts to failure says more about its culture than how it performs during successful time. Furthermore, admitting and embracing failure, instead of sweeping it under the rug, can help teams in the long run. </p>
<p>Here&#8217;s why failure is a crucial to your team&#8217;s growth and how you can make the most of it.</p>
<h2>Accepting Failure Improves Employee Morale</h2>
<p>As a manager, one of the worst things you can do is make failure seem like something that&#8217;s completely unacceptable within the company. Nobody is perfect, and pressuring your staff to hit impossible goals will only break them. </p>
<p>&#8220;De-emphasizing perfection will encourage your employees to work hard, and grow loyal to your company,&#8221; says <a href="http://fortune.com/2015/06/02/amy-errett-keeping-your-best-employees/" target="_blank">Amy Errett, CEO and co-founder of Madison Reed</a>. &#8220;We would all like our employees to be perfect, but everyone is susceptible to making mistakes — even the best employees. Too much criticism can discourage employees, and create an adversarial atmosphere.&#8221;</p>
<p>Furthermore, setting impossible standards creates a new problem within your team: apathy. If they know going in that there&#8217;s no way to accomplish their goals, they might not bother to try their best. </p>
<p>&#8220;The worst thing about starting a project is having employees being apathetic towards it,&#8221; writes the team at <a href="http://capriconsulting.co.uk/2016/08/31/5-reasons-for-project-management-failure/" target="_blank">Capri Consulting</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you have employees on the project who are not motivated and do not pose any interest, the project is already doomed. Employees LOVE validation. If they see that you realize they are a valuable asset to the organisation, their motivations for projects will increase as well as their drive to succeed.&#8221;</p>
<p>As more companies acknowledge the benefits of failure, they&#8217;re encouraging employees to take risks. This has actually become a popular question within job interviews. </p>
<p>&#8220;Hiring managers don&#8217;t expect you to be perfect. They know that everybody fails,&#8221; says <a href="https://biginterview.com/blog/2014/02/biggest-failure-question.html" target="_blank">Pamela Skillings, co-founder of Big Interview</a>. &#8220;They ask this question to understand: Are you someone who can learn from failure? Are you self-aware enough to acknowledge failure and weakness? Do you take smart risks? After all, if you&#8217;ve never failed, then you&#8217;ve probably never succeeded on any significant level either.&#8221;</p>
<p>Managers would rather have a team that&#8217;s passionate enough to take risks than apathetic toward the project or too timid to try. The easiest way to do that is to create a safe zone for failure that is reviewed and at times rewarded. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/mistake.jpg" alt="mistake" width="798" height="532" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5183" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/mistake.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/mistake-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/mistake-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/mistake-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>Admitting Failure Gives Your Team Time to Process</h2>
<p>Often, creating a &#8220;culture of failure&#8221; is easier said than done, especially in established enterprises that already have a set hierarchy. </p>
<p>&#8220;Large hiring bonuses are given to executives who often also receive huge parachute payouts when their failures or disappointing performance get them fired,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.ideaarchitects.org/2015/01/failing-flailing.html" target="_blank">Jeffrey Cufaude of Idea Architects</a>. &#8220;When the worst thing that can happen is you get fired and walk out the door with a six or seven-figure check, it is indeed very OK to fail.&#8221; </p>
<p>Meanwhile, lower-level employees worry about how failing will reflect their job reviews, advancement potential and even salaries. There&#8217;s more to lose for them, which means they&#8217;re less likely to take risks.</p>
<p>&#8220;Before telling everyone that it&#8217;s OK to fail, at minimum spend more time (1) thinking about how this advice/request sounds to those possessing less privilege within the organization and perhaps framing your message differently, and (2) ensuring that the organization&#8217;s key systems (performance reviews, compensation, et al) are aligned with the acceptance of failure you envision,&#8221; Cufaude advises. </p>
<p>Failure isn&#8217;t always about risk-taking. There are times when everyone does their part to complete a goal that doesn&#8217;t pan out. Once this happens, team members need time to process the loss, and in some cases grieve. </p>
<p>&#8220;Failure can take a hefty emotional toll, and that&#8217;s OK,&#8221; <a href="http://lifehacker.com/how-to-move-past-failure-1597951611" target="_blank">Patrick Allen at Lifehacker</a> writes. &#8220;What&#8217;s important is getting the negative feelings you have out of your system so you can regroup and tackle what&#8217;s next. Failure can leave an open wound, and it&#8217;s unwise to ignore it. Without acknowledging it, your wound will continue to hurt, take longer to heal, and possibly get infected.&#8221;</p>
<p>On a managerial level, this means evaluating the morale of your team and understanding the effects of the setback. </p>
<p>&#8220;It&#8217;s OK to let everyone wallow in disappointment and negative feelings for a little while,&#8221; explains <a href="https://hbr.org/2015/02/how-to-help-your-team-bounce-back-from-failure" target="_blank">Amy Gallo, contributing editor at Harvard Business Review</a>. She tells a story about Susan David, founder of the Harvard/McLean Institute of Coaching, losing a client on a Friday that her company had been trying to land for months. </p>
<p>&#8220;Although she was trying to be motivating and forward-focused, to her devastated team, she came off as uncaring and uncommitted. In fact, negative or neutral emotions are conducive to deductive reasoning, which means they can help your team more effectively process and analyze the failure. When you acknowledge the disappointment &#8230; you&#8217;re not just stroking people&#8217;s emotions. You&#8217;re facilitating a critical appraisal of the situation.&#8221;</p>
<p>Instead of brushing failure under the rug or immediately looking for lessons and advice, give your team some time to let the news sink in, and then find ways to grow from it. </p>
<h2>Project Reviews Teach You About the Business and Employees</h2>
<p>The Butterfly Effect — the idea that a butterfly flaps its wings in one part of the world and causes a tsunami in the next — also applies to business. A small setback for one project can have massive effects on others or on future performance. </p>
<p>&#8220;As an entrepreneur I try to look at every mistake as a lesson,&#8221; says <a href="http://fortune.com/2015/03/31/shahrzad-rafati-best-mistake/" target="_blank">Shahrzad Rafati, founder and CEO of BroadbandTV</a>. &#8220;I want to understand why the mistake was made and how I can avoid making the same one in the future. More importantly, I want to understand how that mistake has changed or affected my business. Whether it&#8217;s a significant error in judgment or a minor oversight, I try to find value in the outcome.&#8221;</p>
<p>One of the fastest ways to identify mistakes and solve them is to assign a dollar value to them. However, you can also assign value in the form of lost time and employee stress. </p>
<p>Evaluating project performance extends beyond failure. Many successful calls and events happen through sheer luck, which can&#8217;t be counted on in the future. </p>
<p>&#8220;People are naturally wired to recognize when things aren&#8217;t going well, and to focus intently on how to fix problems,&#8221; says <a href="http://blog.lucidmeetings.com/blog/how-to-lead-a-successful-project-retrospective-meeting" target="_blank">Elise Keith, co-founder at Lucid Meetings</a>. &#8220;This leads us to take our successes for granted, assuming that things went well because we did a great job.</p>
<p>&#8220;An enormous part of what helps one project work where another doesn&#8217;t is luck — and we take it for granted. Instead, we should be looking for ways to learn from our lucky breaks and design ways to be successful that we can manage directly.&#8221;</p>
<p>Luck is never a good strategy, and companies who evaluate their projects&#8217; success and failures are taking the right steps toward admitting what was skill and what was a nice break. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/ship.jpg" alt="ship" width="798" height="532" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5185" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/ship.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/ship-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/ship-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/ship-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>Failure Helps You Execute the Next Project Better</h2>
<p>Once you&#8217;re ready to move on to the next project, you have the opportunity to take what you experienced and apply it moving forward. This is why many people advocate for post-project reviews even for small tasks and test runs. </p>
<p>&#8220;Even if a project is small, there are always things that pop up which will help you learn for larger projects,&#8221; writes one account manager at <a href="https://www.portent.com/blog/10-tips-for-a-successful-post-mortem.htm" target="_blank">Portent, Inc.</a> &#8220;For example, let&#8217;s say that the project was delayed because of communication issues. This could lead to a delay of a few days for a small project. But in a massive project, this could delay you by months and more importantly, increase the cost by two-fold.&#8221;</p>
<p>In some cases, the project itself was executed properly, but the process of approval and collaboration failed. This is often the case in companies with complex approval processes or agencies that work between account managers and clients. </p>
<p>&#8220;A project often has multiple parties interested in its outcome, and groups may even have divergent goals and expectations,&#8221; says <a href="http://blog.hightail.com/five-reasons-projects-fail/" target="_blank">Mike Trigg, COO at Hightail</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;I once spent weeks working with a designer and copywriter on a website home page redesign, only to have our carefully-crafted work dismantled by the company&#8217;s various heads of department demanding changes to meet their individual needs. Our problem was that we failed to establish who owned the project and therefore didn&#8217;t deal with potential conflicts and disappointments in advance.&#8221;</p>
<p>This is where the real project reviews come it. Delays, setbacks and challenges often aren&#8217;t caused by employees lacking the right skills or instructions, but by the creation process itself. </p>
<p>Reviewing flaws in small projects sets you up to create channels of improvement in the big ones. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you don&#8217;t have a clear focus at the at the earliest stage of the process, you are making things harder on yourself,&#8221; says <a href="https://project-management.com/top-10-main-causes-of-project-failure/" target="_blank">Rosanne Lim, writing for ProjectManagement.com</a>. &#8220;Have a meeting, even if it is lengthy, with stakeholders to discuss their expectations on cost, time and product quality. </p>
<p>&#8220;Tracking milestones is how you are going to know whether you are meeting expectations. Proper recording and monitoring lets the PM identify where more resources are needed to complete a project on time.&#8221;</p>
<p>Treat your projects like a leaky dam. If you find the source of a small leak — perhaps a faulty approval process or miscommunications between client and vendor — then take the necessary steps to patch it up. </p>
<p>That way, you&#8217;ll reduce the risk of a small leak breaking down the whole dam when you most need it. </p>
<h2>Failure Can Improve Customer Relations</h2>
<p>If it&#8217;s hard for employees to admit their faults to their managers, then it&#8217;s almost impossible for vendors to admit problems to their customers.</p>
<p>&#8220;Consider bringing in representatives from the client side to take a look at the lifespan of the project,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.business.com/program-and-project-management/the-postmortem-learning-the-most-in-post/" target="_blank">Andrew Lovasz, CEO of Main Path Marketing</a>. &#8220;Whether it&#8217;s over a conference call or passing along documents from the meeting, it&#8217;s always wise to share knowledge of how the project performed. Although this may seem a bit intimidating, it&#8217;s entirely useful to help manage the client&#8217;s expectations going forward.&#8221;</p>
<p>Bringing in these parties to discuss failure can actually improve customer relations. You&#8217;re taking necessary steps to improve your relationship while proving your commitment to growth.</p>
<p>Again, customers don&#8217;t want apathetic vendors.</p>
<p>If your team and vendors feel a little intimidated about really sharing their feelings, consider making the process anonymous for all parties. </p>
<p>&#8220;We&#8217;ve found both internal and external feedback on projects to be more candid when it&#8217;s submitted anonymously,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.business2community.com/strategy/10-things-include-project-post-mortem-0968906#OyzCgsih6iI57yeK.97" target="_blank">Brittany Hodak, co-founder of ZinePak</a>. &#8220;Now, before every project debrief, we collect anonymous survey responses in Google Forms. This feedback helps us shape our regroup meetings to make sure all problems are being addressed so future projects can run more smoothly.&#8221;</p>
<p>It&#8217;s entirely possible that people who have ideas for improvement are too intimidated to say anything and don&#8217;t want to ruffle feathers. As long as the criticism is constructive and leads to results, there&#8217;s no reason to avoid anonymous feedback. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Cookies.jpg" alt="cookies" width="798" height="532" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5182" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Cookies.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Cookies-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Cookies-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Cookies-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>You Reduce the Risk of Failure for Next Time</h2>
<p>Many educators are also teaching their students about failure and taking lessons from the business world. Like managers, they&#8217;re setting the standards incredibly high to push students so that they learn take feedback and try again. </p>
<p>&#8220;How do you make failure students&#8217; friend?&#8221; asks <a href="http://www.edutopia.org/blog/failure-essential-learning-bob-lenz" target="_blank">Bob Lenz, executive director of the Buck Institute for Education</a>. &#8220;Set a high standard and don&#8217;t be afraid to tell students that they haven&#8217;t met it. </p>
<p>&#8220;But in the next breath, give detailed suggestions on what they can do to improve. And, most important — though so often given short shrift — allow students the time, space and support to make the revisions.&#8221;</p>
<p>By making revisions part of the process, students learn early on to keep growing and improving. </p>
<p>As a manager, you can learn from this by letting your team know that no project is perfect — and no project is executed perfectly. There is always room for improvement. </p>
<p>&#8220;Failure brings with it important firsthand knowledge,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.wanderlustworker.com/the-importance-of-failure-5-valuable-lessons-from-failing/" target="_blank">R.L. Adams at Wanderlust Worker</a>. &#8220;That knowledge can be harnessed in the future to overcome that very failure that inflicted so much pain in the first place.&#8221;</p>
<p>Today, you might solve a big problem with communication, which allows you to find smaller problems that can also get fixed tomorrow. As long as your employees are growing and your office is improving, the likelihood of failure — and the sting when it eventually occurs — diminishes. </p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
<em>©gstockstudio/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/stevepb-282134/"><em>stevepb</em></a><em>, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/skeeze-272447/"><em>skeeze</em></a><em>, ©Novic/123RF Stock Photo</em><br />
</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/embracing-failure/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Project Management Software Has Changed Workplace Communication</title>
		<link>/project-management/</link>
					<comments>/project-management/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2016 22:47:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow software]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet Tools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5170</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As the digital office has evolved, communication has developed a set of rules. Here’s how you can get the most out of your project management software.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The onboarding process for any employees — whether they&#8217;re remote or in house — follows the same procedure. Create an email login, sign into chat, set up your voicemail, save the conference dial-in number, and plug in your webcam. (Most companies stop short of assigning carrier pigeons to their employees or handing out guidebooks on Morse code.)</p>
<p>Communication is crucial in the workplace, and its level of effectiveness can make or break a project or an employee&#8217;s experience. As the digital office has evolved, communication has also developed its own set of rules. Here&#8217;s how modern employees best use their communication tools, and how you should use them in the office.</p>
<h2>How Have Our Office Conversations Evolved?</h2>
<p>Before we look at the tools we use to communicate, we have to look at what we&#8217;re saying. Previously, conversations between managers and teams focused on <em>what</em> needed to get done, but now people primarily discuss <em>how</em> to do things.</p>
<p>&#8220;Employee productivity and efforts have been improved, allowing them to place more emphasis on more important things such as precision and creativity,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.iofficecorp.com/blog/4-ways-technology-has-changed-the-modern-workplace" target="_blank">Elizabeth Dukes, Partner at iOffice</a>.</p>
<p>&#8220;The level of expectation of clients and co-workers has also changed as a result of technology in the workplace, keeping everyone connected on a constant basis. Results are expected much faster than ever before.&#8221;</p>
<p>Productivity software like <a href="https://www.teamfocus.me/">teamfocus</a> has been a major contributor in this transition, and some people are even advocating for it to completely replace email.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2499696,00.asp" target="_blank">Jill Duffy, author of Get Organized</a>, believes email only makes employees stressed and overwhelmed when it comes to project work. &#8220;The last few years, productivity enthusiasts have pushed knowledge workers to get off of email, or at least to ditch internal company email. An excellent way shift away from email is to all but ban it from project work and move that communication to a project management service instead.&#8221;</p>
<p>However, like the conference call and voicemail, email will continue to be an important part of communication. In fact, many of today&#8217;s communication tools will remain in use as long as each of them has an important purpose in the workforce.</p>
<p>&#8220;Each of us has personal preferences for communication based on what we feel is easiest — for example, some people have an easier time writing than speaking, and some people prefer meeting in person rather than the impersonality of text,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.inc.com/jayson-demers/communication-in-2015-text-voice-video-or-in-person.html" target="_blank">Jayson DeMers, founder and CEO of AudienceBloom</a>.</p>
<p>&#8220;But it&#8217;s important to see beyond the limits of our own convenience. The selection of a medium can have a drastic impact on both the efficiency of your communication and the interpretation of your message.&#8221;</p>
<p>The rest of this article will discuss when each form of technology is appropriate, and how teams can use it to the fullest.</p>
<h2>When Should You Meet in Person?</h2>
<p>The oldest form of technology is our human bodies, which communicate verbal and nonverbal cues more effectively than any other channel. This is still the preferred method when forming personal bonds and discussing sensitive information.</p>
<p>&#8220;A study from Adobe found that Millennials value interpersonal interaction over digital interaction at work,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.cio.com/article/3082775/unified-communications/millennials-are-shaking-up-workplace-communication.html" target="_blank">Sarah White, writer at CIO</a>. &#8220;While 81 percent of Millennials said &#8216;state of the art technology&#8217; was paramount to an ideal working environment over perks or amenities, 55 percent they valued in-person communication at work over digital.&#8221;</p>
<p>However, she says those same respondents tended to overestimate how much everyone else relies on digital communication tools. &#8220;46 percent of respondents anticipated their peers to value IM and texts over interpersonal communication, but the real number ended up being just 11 percent.&#8221;</p>
<p>Just because young people are known for texting and online communication doesn&#8217;t mean society&#8217;s preference for human engagement is changing.</p>
<p>But sometimes, unintentionally or otherwise, messages get lost in the digital either.</p>
<p>In an article for Quartz, <a href="http://qz.com/523049/its-hard-to-fire-people-who-work-remotely-as-one-unfortunate-twitter-employee-just-discovered/" target="_blank">writer Max Nisen</a> covered the story of Bart Teeuwisse, a remote employee at Twitter who found out he was laid off when he couldn&#8217;t access his work accounts.</p>
<p>&#8220;When a manager can&#8217;t just pull someone into an office or a conference room, sometimes, as in this case, the logistics of layoffs — i.e. closing out company email accounts — get in ahead of informing the affected staff personally. Even the phone is not the option it once was, now that so many of us ignore calls and voicemails.&#8221;</p>
<p>With remote work, it&#8217;s not always possible to meet in person, but managers should be mindful and make a concentrated effort to get on the phone with affected employees before sensitive news breaks.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5163" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/phone-1024x682.jpg" alt="phone" width="1024" height="682" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/phone-1024x682.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/phone-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/phone-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/phone-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/phone.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Are Phone and Conference Calls Still Effective?</h2>
<p>Many people have become frustrated with the conference call. It&#8217;s viewed as a time suck and a way to talk about work without actually doing it.</p>
<p>&#8220;You have to both be engaged and seem engaged,&#8221; says <a href="http://money.usnews.com/money/careers/articles/2015/10/21/a-remote-workers-guide-to-conference-calls" target="_blank">writer Laura McMullen</a> for US News. &#8220;You have to fight for just. one. second. to jump in and add your two cents without feeling like Godzilla, stomping on other people&#8217;s words.</p>
<p>&#8220;You have to somehow catalog every team member&#8217;s voice and distinguish one from another. And you have to wrestle with bad connections, sound delays and other technological voodoo that seems to curse every call.&#8221;</p>
<p>However, despite the frustrations, many remote employees enjoy regular check-ins, and they use them as opportunities to ask questions and get to know their team members.</p>
<p>&#8220;You may think you are 100% approachable as a manager,&#8221; writes the team at <a href="https://justworks.com/blog/surefire-ways-make-remote-employees-loathe-you" target="_blank">JustWorks</a>. &#8220;But if you don&#8217;t actually explain to your remote employees how you can be approached, they&#8217;re going to err on the side of not approaching you at all.&#8221;</p>
<p>They recommend setting regular calls to give employees a chance to discuss issues and ask questions.</p>
<p>&#8220;[Create] a daily or weekly meeting that is always scheduled where the employee has a reason to call in and talk to you. It can be for ten minutes a day, but what you&#8217;re giving them is the chance to talk.&#8221;</p>
<p>Of course, weekly phone calls are only as effective as your team is at listening. One survey by <a href="https://www.westuc.com/en-us/blog/conferencing-collaboration/mobile-conferencing-changing-how-we-work" target="_blank">West Unified Communications Service</a> found 64% of employees do other work while on a conference call. Meanwhile, the rest are using the time for other activities.</p>
<p>&#8220;Workers take full advantage of the multitasking opportunities that mobile conferencing provides,&#8221; they write. &#8220;Respondents claimed to be doing all kinds of other tasks while on a mobile conference call. The multitasking activities included: getting other work done, sending emails, eating, texting, social media, video games, shopping and even going to the restroom.&#8221;</p>
<p>In fact, 27% of respondents said they&#8217;ve fallen asleep during a conference call.</p>
<p>While phone communication and conference calls are here to stay, voicemail is officially optional. Washington Post columnist <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/on-leadership/wp/2015/06/04/the-end-of-office-voice-mail/" target="_blank">Jena McGregor</a> writes that companies like Coca-Cola and JPMorgan Chase have disconnected voicemail entirely because it&#8217;s considered outdated and time-consuming.</p>
<p>&#8220;We&#8217;ve all sat through rambling, five-minute-long messages from people who really should have sent a two-line email. We&#8217;ve all screened numbers we didn&#8217;t want to answer and then — minutes later — gotten a redundant email or cell phone call. And we&#8217;ve all wondered if that automated, robotic voice saying &#8216;message. received. on. Thursday. June. 4th. at. 2. 53. pm&#8217; could really be any slower.&#8221;</p>
<h2>How Has Email Communication Evolved with Technology?</h2>
<p>While conference calls might drag employees down, there&#8217;s a general consensus that important communication should be funnelled through phone calls if two parties can&#8217;t meet in person. Most experts believe that email is no place for sensitive discussions.</p>
<p>&#8220;Never confront via email — it suggests you&#8217;re afraid of confrontation, which suggests you aren&#8217;t committed to your message,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/244492" target="_blank">Ross McCam mon, articles editor at GQ magazine</a>. &#8220;Plan what you&#8217;re going to say, but don&#8217;t script it out &#8230; like you would if you weren&#8217;t addressing a difficult matter. Point out the way you may be contributing to the problem.&#8221;</p>
<p>Email should be the last place you turn when trying to communicate with an employee. Even company chat boxes provide more of a back-and-forth conversational feel than an email.</p>
<p>&#8220;Don&#8217;t send a confrontation email to someone unless you&#8217;ve tried to get in touch with him or her every other possible way with no success, or if the problem is so urgent that he or she needs to be told immediately and the only available option is email,&#8221; agrees <a href="https://www.themuse.com/advice/confronting-an-employee-over-email-5-tips-for-doing-it-right" target="_blank">Lily Herman, managing editor at WayUp</a>.</p>
<p>However, if you&#8217;re on the fence about sending the email, Herman recommends use the six-sentence rule.</p>
<p>&#8220;If you feel like you can&#8217;t explain your case in six sentences or fewer, perhaps the subject is too big and hairy for email. After all, you don&#8217;t want to minimize a delicate situation.&#8221;</p>
<p>Outside of confrontational situations, email is getting ignored because workers think it&#8217;s slow. The response time and length required to draft it bog down the process more than chat or a phone call.</p>
<p>&#8220;Sending an email isn&#8217;t always the fastest way to say something,&#8221; says team members <a href="http://glasscanopy.com/send-email-pick-up-phone-how-to-decide/" target="_blank">glassCanopy</a>. &#8220;Sometimes, I spend more time drafting an email than I would in a phone call communicating the same information. That may be partly because I&#8217;m a wordsmith by trade; but also because emails that contain a lot of information deserve a higher level of curation.&#8221;</p>
<p>This is often because people use email when they want to document something that can be referenced later, or communicate specific instructions.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5162" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/email-1024x683.jpg" alt="email" width="1024" height="683" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/email-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/email-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/email-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/email-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/email.jpg 1677w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>How Does the Modern Workforce Use Chat?</h2>
<p>The frustrations behind long conference calls and tedious email chains have caused a new hero to arise in the world of office communication: chat boxes.</p>
<p>&#8220;Chat is far more efficient than long, drawn-out email chains (who likes those, anyway?),&#8221; says <a href="https://www.formassembly.com/blog/remote-teams-communicate/" target="_blank">Hannah Wright at FormAssembly</a>. &#8220;Plus, there&#8217;s one more bonus: It&#8217;s fun.</p>
<p>&#8220;One thing to keep in mind is that written text lacks the subtle cues of in-person conversation. With chat, you do need to be careful about how your words might be interpreted and possibly misunderstood. That&#8217;s why there&#8217;s an abundance of emoticons and gifs in our everyday chats — they&#8217;re useful in conveying the right nuances.&#8221;</p>
<p>Chat is one of the best ways for remote employees to ask quick questions from across the world and even get to know the people they work with better.</p>
<p>&#8220;When working remotely, team members don&#8217;t have a chance to make small talk with their neighbor in the next cubicle or discuss weekend plans by the coffeemaker,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.teambonding.com/5-team-bondingtips-for-remote-employees/" target="_blank">Samantha McDuffee for Teambonding</a>. &#8220;It&#8217;s that kind of personal chit-chat, however, that helps employees relate to each other.&#8221;</p>
<p>The best part is that chat creates an even plane, as in-house employees are using chat even more. This means remote employees aren&#8217;t left out of conversations (and in-house teams get to use emojis in their professional instruction).</p>
<p>&#8220;Trendy open-plan offices are infamous for their cacophonous din — they were originally designed to get workers across the office to strike up conversations that hopefully lead to innovative collaborations,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/users/2015/04/slack_and_the_office_chat_several_people_are_typing_who_s_working.html" target="_blank">Amanda Hess, writer for The New York Times</a>.</p>
<p>&#8220;While bosses are free to convene closed-door meetings, it&#8217;s hard for underlings to have a private word unless they physically leave the premises. But now, Slack has given every employee a virtual office door, and boy do we use them.&#8221;</p>
<p>If project management software has changed what we talk about, so that more teams are focusing on how things should get done, then it makes sense for chat to rise up as the leading communication tool. It&#8217;s the platform for quick questions and team collaboration, both of which are crucial for meeting deadlines and moving work forward.</p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
<em>©rawpixel/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/geralt-9301/" target="_blank"><em>geralt</em></a><em>, ©alexeyboldin/123RF Stock Photo</em></small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/project-management/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Transition Your Team to Include Remote Employees</title>
		<link>/include-remote-employees/</link>
					<comments>/include-remote-employees/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:43:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet Tools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5148</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you’re considering letting your staff work remotely, or want new hires to include remote employees, follow these tips to make sure all parties are happy.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>According to Gallup, <a href="http://www.gallup.com/poll/184649/telecommuting-work-climbs.aspx" target="_blank">37 percent of companies</a> allow remote work in some shape or form. However, the average employee works from home just two days per month. So, while it seems like companies across the nation are instating successful telecommuting policies, they&#8217;re really just taking advantage of modern technology to make their employees happy. </p>
<p>The ease of telecommuting has allowed many companies to incorporate flexibility into the work schedule, but few have introduced a comprehensive remote work policy and have hired full-time remote workers. Many are in a transitionary period where their employees want to work remotely, but they&#8217;re not sure how to manage those employees. This leads to awkward policies and strange rules. </p>
<p>If you&#8217;re considering letting your current in-house staff work remotely, or want to hire remote team members to join your local employees, follow the advice from these experts to make sure all parties are happy. </p>
<h2>Understand that Remote Work is Part of the Job Description</h2>
<p>Any employee who has checked their email on vacation or answered a call from the boss at home has participated in remote work. <a href="http://scottberkun.com/2015/why-isnt-remote-work-more-popular/" target="_blank">Scott Berkun, author of The Year Without Pants</a>, says remote work is part of most office cultures, just not during traditional business hours. </p>
<p>&#8220;Even in companies that do not allow &#8216;remote work&#8217;, remote work is encouraged implicitly by the equipment used and the daily working habits we&#8217;ve adopted across our culture. The resistance to the concept of remote work is strange, given the reality of most office work.&#8221; </p>
<p>Despite the common practice of working remotely during off hours at home, managers are reluctant to implement it during the day. Their fears are two-fold: They can&#8217;t track employee performance, and employees can&#8217;t stay in touch with company goings on. </p>
<p>&#8220;A common concern about remote work is that company culture will suffer if employees don&#8217;t all show up at the office every day,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.businessnewsdaily.com/7749-create-telecommuting-policy.html" target="_blank">Nicole Fallon at Business News Daily</a>.</p>
<p>&#8220;Staff members who telecommute similarly fear that they&#8217;ll miss out on important office bonding time by not seeing their co-workers face-to-face. With the appropriate use of communications technology, companies can make sure their culture remains intact, even with full-time telecommuters.&#8221; </p>
<p>A strategically implemented remote work policy can make all parties happy while keeping everyone connected. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/interview-1024x683.jpg" alt="job applicant having interview. handshake while job interviewing" width="1024" height="683" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5151" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/interview-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/interview-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/interview-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/interview-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/interview.jpg 1678w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Draft a Concrete Telecommuting Policy</h2>
<p>Informal policies are easily abused and can cause frustration when different parties follow some rules but not others. As remote work continues to grow, companies need to establish written guidelines for their remote staff.</p>
<p>&#8220;Companies need to consider drafting policies and documents that clearly communicate how the organization supports flexible working styles,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/kaviguppta/2016/04/24/four-ways-to-test-remote-work-options-in-your-organization/#137b29a61544" target="_blank">Kavi Guppta, a technology-in-the-workforce writer</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;You won&#8217;t have all the answers or protocols in place immediately, but it&#8217;s important that a rough framework is in place that can be adjusted and improved over time. Remote work habits shouldn&#8217;t impact home office processes, and vice versa.&#8221;</p>
<p>It&#8217;s OK if your first policy has flaws; however, developing something will that you can modify will provide a solid foundation for future disputes. </p>
<p>&#8220;Your policy should [thoroughly] address work hours,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/231999" target="_blank">Kim Lachance Shandrow, writing for Entrepreneur</a>. &#8220;Are telecommuters required to work during your company&#8217;s set business hours, or will they have a flexible schedule that they can determine themselves? Also be sure to address management oversight. How often will managers check in with telecommuters and vice versa?&#8221;</p>
<p>Furthermore, remote hires should also receive a copy of the employee handbook with the understanding that it also applies to them. </p>
<p>&#8220;Even though your remote employees are not physically in the office, they still need to adhere to all relevant rules outlined in your employee handbook,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/got-remote-workers-8-key-points-to-include-in-your-remote-work-policy-2011-7" target="_blank">Ramon Ray of Smart Hustle Magazine</a>. &#8220;For example, if you have defined policies concerning work-related electronic communication, these rules continue to be applicable.&#8221; </p>
<p>These guidelines are meant to help managers and employees. This way, remote team members will meet company expectations but won&#8217;t get abused and overworked by managers. </p>
<h2>Track Employee Performance and ROI</h2>
<p>Another overlooked aspect of remote work is employee ROI. Many companies have found that telecommuting leads to higher retention rates and job satisfaction, but few actually track that in their own companies. </p>
<p>&#8220;A 2015 study conducted by FlexJobs and WorldAtWork found that 80 percent of companies offer flexible work options, but only 3 percent measure programs to quantify ROI,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/270585" target="_blank">Sara Sutton Fell, CEO &amp; founder of FlexJobs</a>. &#8220;Without measurements, it&#8217;s impossible to leverage remote and flexible work to support company goals.</p>
<p>&#8220;At UnitedHealth Group &#8230; performance measurements like work quality, retention rates, and employees satisfaction are tracked to determine the ROI of work-at-home (WAH) arrangements.&#8221;</p>
<p>Along with employee satisfaction, managers should also set up new metrics for managing performance. </p>
<p>&#8220;Rather than being overly stringent and attempting to manage their time and efficiency on a day-to-day basis, provide them the freedom they require as remote workers,&#8221; says <a href="http://readwrite.com/2015/11/18/manage-remote-teams/" target="_blank">Blair Thomas, co-founder of EMerchantBroker</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;Measure their performance, and as long as they&#8217;re attending daily meetings and working as effectively as others, treat your remote employees like secret weapons. Constant monitoring of time, and keeping track of their every move, will only serve to engender stress and reduce their efficacy.&#8221; </p>
<p>This analysis will also be important during their annual reviews, as raises will have to be determined based on accomplishments, not time spent in the office. </p>
<p>&#8220;Having your team work remotely places special emphasis on the need for a compensation system based on output,&#8221;  says <a href="https://divorcediscourse.com/transition-team-remote-work/" target="_blank">Lee Rosen</a>. &#8220;You&#8217;re not going to know what they&#8217;re doing, when they&#8217;re doing it, or how they&#8217;re getting it done, so you need to build a system that rewards results.&#8221;</p>
<p>Tracking your remote employees can feel like an uphill battle, which is why it&#8217;s important to set job satisfaction metrics, performance metrics and project incentives that your team can work toward. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/laptop-1024x682.jpg" alt="laptop" width="1024" height="682" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5152" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/laptop-1024x682.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/laptop-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/laptop-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/laptop-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/laptop.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Build an Inclusive Company Culture</h2>
<p>Along with setting professional guidelines, companies transitioning to remote work also need cultural goals and beliefs. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you have a strong company culture established before you begin distributing work remotely, it is essential to have just as strong a focus on maintaining that culture as your workforce becomes more geographically diverse,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.hoopla.net/blog/posts/5-quick-tips-to-keep-remote-employees-in-the-loop" target="_blank">Mike Smalls, founder and CEO of Hoopla Software</a>.</p>
<p>However, adjusting your company culture might start within. Many career experts have seen toxic cultures without remote employees, much less with them. </p>
<p>&#8220;People blame distance for a lack of culture,&#8221; says <a href="http://thenextweb.com/insider/2015/06/18/how-to-build-a-happy-and-productive-remote-team/#gref" target="_blank">Poornima Vijayashanker, founder of Femgineer</a>. &#8220;But when it comes to communication, even in-house teams struggle with it. I&#8217;ve come across teams where people don&#8217;t know what the person who is sitting right next to them is working on! Hence distance isn&#8217;t the culprit. The culprit is a closed culture, where team members work in silos and don&#8217;t communicate about their projects.&#8221;</p>
<p>Similarly, as you create opportunities for your remote team, look for ways to make your in-house staff more flexible. </p>
<p>&#8220;One of the most empowering parts of being able to telecommute is that employees have more control over their hours and break times,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.inc.com/ariana-ayu/still-not-a-fan-of-telecommuting-here-s-why-you-need-to-get-on-the-bandwagon.html" target="_blank">Ariana Ayu, author of The Magic of Mojo</a>. &#8220;Allowing them to have flexibility when they come into the office will also give them that feeling of control. If nothing else, giving them a window of time within which they can choose their hours will have some of the same morale-boosting effects as telecommuting.&#8221;</p>
<p>As you make decisions to improve the happiness and satisfaction of one party, ask yourself how all other workers will be affected and whether they will be able to enjoy the new changes. </p>
<h2>Find Your Communication Balance</h2>
<p>As companies work to build a culture that includes remote members so they don&#8217;t feel stranded on an island, those companies need to evaluate their communication practices. </p>
<p>&#8220;[A] lack of regular contact can lead to confusion about their status and performance,&#8221; say <a href="https://remote.co/5-tips-for-providing-feedback-to-remote-workers/" target="_blank">Debbie Vasen and Ann MacDonald at LoveToKnow</a>. &#8220;While the old adage &#8216;no news is good news&#8217; may be true in some instances, a lack of news or communication can make a worker feel isolated and uncertain. Without a daily smile and chitchat from you near the coffee machine, a worker can start to wonder if he or she is valued.&#8221; </p>
<p>Furthermore, that daily chitchat is also a crucial part of the training experience. </p>
<p>&#8220;While formal training programs are an essential part of onboarding and development, informal learning can comprise up to 75% of total learning, often taking the form of causal interactions among colleagues who pass along tips for handling specific challenges,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.eremedia.com/tlnt/5-strategies-for-training-remote-employees/" target="_blank">Tricia Sciortino, president of eaHELP</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;Companies can foster a virtual environment that serves the same purpose. Create private groups where employees can seek out new information, share best practices, and share the kinds of conversations and encouragement that would typically happen in the hallway and around the break room.&#8221;</p>
<p>There is good news about remote employees missing out on small conversations during the day: Their minds are free to focus. This lack of distractions is often why employees choose remote work in the first place, and why they feel more productive. </p>
<p>&#8220;One of the advantages that comes from working remotely is the relative freedom to avoid bad meetings and other low-barrier distractions,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.helpscout.net/blog/virtual-teams/" target="_blank">Gregory Ciotti of Help Scout</a>. &#8220;But communication still needs to occur on a regular basis, and oftentimes everything gets pushed to email, creating a bottleneck that results in remote teams spending more time in email than office workers.</p>
<p>&#8220;Instead, remote teams should create a messaging hierarchy that offers guidelines on what sorts of messages are appropriate for which medium.&#8221;</p>
<p>Examples of this hierarchy include weekly calls, daily emails and casual chats. Each form of communication harbors different types of conversations, so your remote team has an appropriate outlet for every problem or question. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/office-1024x683.jpg" alt="office" width="1024" height="683" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5153" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/office-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/office-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/office-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/office-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/office.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Assign Projects and Place Remote Workers on Teams</h2>
<p>Finally, one of the best practices for engaging remote employees — especially newly telecommuting team members — is to encourage teamwork. </p>
<p>&#8220;In a practical sense, requiring teamwork and collaboration helps telecommuters maintain productivity by removing some of the isolating aspects of telecommuting work,&#8221; says <a href="https://www.timesheets.com/blog/2015/12/4-ways-to-stay-in-the-loop-with-telecommuting-employees/" target="_blank">Anum Yoon of Current on Currency</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;As with any strategy or ground mindset, creating teams can have its pitfalls. Do your research and course correct as necessary. You want employees to feel a sense of connection and mutual pride in their work — you don&#8217;t want your employee base split into factions or consistently making bad decisions thanks to group shift.&#8221;</p>
<p>Not only does teamwork encourage communication and concrete deliverables, but it also helps your remote members build personal bonds with their colleagues. </p>
<p>&#8220;You can&#8217;t think of a remote worker initially as, &#8216;well, I can&#8217;t find this person locally so I&#8217;m going to find a remote worker,'&#8221; says <a href="http://www.skilledup.com/insights/transitioning-remote-workforce-two-case-studies" target="_blank">Formstack CEO Chris Byers</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;You might be able to get away with that, but that remote worker is likely going to feel out on an island. If you really want remote to be a thriving part of your organization, somebody from a leadership level has to own that culture and make sure the remote employees are engaged with everybody else.&#8221; </p>
<p>Transitioning from fully in-house employees to a team of telecommuters and remote workers is going to have its growing pains, but managers who are strategic about how their teams work can see their employees thrive. </p>
<p><small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
<em>©rawpixel/123RF Stock Photo, ©alexraths/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/moleshko-350543/" target="_blank"><em>moleshko</em></a><em>, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/Unsplash-242387/" target="_blank"><em>Unsplash</em></a></small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/include-remote-employees/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Delegate Effectively With Project Management Software</title>
		<link>/delegate-effectively/</link>
					<comments>/delegate-effectively/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 04:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workflow software]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Entrepreneurship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet Tools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5139</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Supervisors sometimes micromanage and stress out their employees with modern technology. Follow these 16 managers to learn how to delegate effectively.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The rise of <a href="https://www.teamfocus.me/project-management-software/">project management software</a> has made it easier for managers to delegate tasks and communicate with employees, but that doesn&#8217;t necessarily mean they&#8217;re delegating well. </p>
<p>Many supervisors continue to micromanage, miscommunicate and stress out their employees with the help of modern technology. Follow the advice of these 16 managers to learn how to delegate effectively with project management software. </p>
<h2>Evaluate What Needs to Be Delegated</h2>
<p>Whether the task is going to a remote freelancer or in-house employee, managers need to be careful deciding what assignments go to which employees.</p>
<p>&#8220;When matching individuals or teams to projects, take into consideration their ability, skills, experience and goals,&#8221; says business etiquette expert <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/247758" target="_blank">Jacqueline Whitmore</a>. &#8220;Some tasks are more mundane than others. In this case, find someone who thrives on routine tasks. For the more intricate projects, find someone who likes a challenge and knows to tackle the manageable parts of the job before diving into the more complicated aspects.&#8221; </p>
<p>Speaking of mundane tasks, start by reviewing your own workload and questioning where your time goes. You might be able to eliminate redundant tasks and save both you and your employees time.  </p>
<p><a href="https://www.thebalance.com/top-tips-for-effective-delegation-2951528" target="_blank">Alyssa Gregory, founder of the Small Business Bonfire</a>, has seen small business owners struggle to let go of their tasks and daily activities. When you&#8217;ve been doing it on your own for so long, it can be challenging <a href="https://www.teamfocus.me/managers-guide/">to let go</a> of the reigns. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you kept track of everything you do during your workday, I bet you&#8217;d be surprised to see where your time is going and what qualifies as your biggest time drains. This alone can be a powerful tool for identifying potential tasks to delegate, and even tasks to eliminate from your business.&#8221;</p>
<p>Once you know what you want to delegate, it&#8217;s time make sure the training and onboarding process runs smoothly. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/training-1024x683.jpg" alt="training" width="1024" height="683" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5144" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/training-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/training-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/training-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/training-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/training.jpg 1678w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Take Time to Onboard New Hires to Your Tasks</h2>
<p>If you&#8217;re hiring someone to take work off your plate, you can&#8217;t expect them to learn everything immediately. It&#8217;s the role of the delegating manager to take a step back and make sure their employees are balancing their responsibilities well.</p>
<p>&#8220;New hires need to not only prepare themselves mentally with knowledge, but they need to be emotionally prepared as well,&#8221; says <a href="http://theundercoverrecruiter.com/turn-hire-great-employee/" target="_blank">Sarah Landrum, writing for Undercover Recruiter</a>. &#8220;Throwing them too much at one time can overwhelm them and make them feel as though they won&#8217;t be able to succeed.</p>
<p>&#8220;The best way to handle this is to set milestones and provide small batches of training material at a time. Once the employee has completed a batch, he/she should receive another one, and so on and so forth.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="http://blog.uassistme.co/blog/best-delegation-practices-for-a-virtual-or-remote-team-member" target="_blank">Rodolfo Schildknecht, co-founder of Uassist.ME</a>, emphasizes the importance of detailed onboarding for all employees, especially virtual ones. </p>
<p>&#8220;A virtual employee&#8217;s onboarding only consists of formal onboarding meetings, and misses out on valuable hallway chatter and impromptu meetings. For this reason, it&#8217;s important to make those initial onboarding sessions as valuable as possible. Spending this time upfront can help your virtual employee produce higher quality work from the get-go, without coming back and forth to you with questions.&#8221;</p>
<p>While it might be easy for an in-house employee to ask a one-off question, remote employees have a harder time contacting and explaining their problems or concerns. </p>
<h2>Create Assignments That Will Challenge and Inspire Employees</h2>
<p>Along with offloading time-consuming tasks, managers also want to delegate projects that will help employees grow. After all, they&#8217;re proteges, not secretaries. </p>
<p><a href="http://www.profitguide.com/manage-grow/leadership/how-to-give-instructions-your-employees-will-actually-follow-92618" target="_blank">Merge Gupta-Sunderji, leadership development consultant</a>, explains that employees don&#8217;t like receiving busy work or tasks with no end result. To prevent this, provide context to why you&#8217;re asking them to do something. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you want to increase the likelihood of getting the end-result you desire from your employees, tell them why what you&#8217;re trying to communicate matters. In the workplace, we&#8217;re dealing with adults. Chances are you didn&#8217;t buy your parents saying &#8216;Because I said so&#8217; when you were a child, so why would it be true for the adults you employ?&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="http://blog.getbridge.com/give-employees-room-to-stretch" target="_blank">Jeff Weber, SVP at Instructure, Inc.</a>, recommends assigning &#8220;stretch assignments,&#8221; or a project that challenges employees to grow outside of their normal duties.</p>
<p>&#8220;One way to do this is to meet with employees individually and ask them what types of projects they&#8217;d like to work on or what skills they&#8217;d like to develop, and then use that information to assign them to a project you wouldn&#8217;t normally have tapped them to complete before you knew their interests.&#8221; </p>
<p>These assignments give employees a sense of purpose, while giving them a new challenge to master at work. </p>
<p>Even if you&#8217;re not providing stretch assignments, simply highlighting the benefits of completion can ease the onboarding process of delegation. </p>
<p><a href="https://www.themuse.com/advice/how-to-delegate-work-to-your-team-without-being-annoying" target="_blank">Tim Sieck, principal partner with On Target Talent</a>, was inspired by Adrian Gostick&#8217;s &#8220;WIIFM&#8221; philosophy, or &#8220;What&#8217;s in it for me?&#8221; which assigns a reason for doing something that benefits the employee, along with a task.</p>
<p>&#8220;Frankly, it doesn&#8217;t matter why you want the job done. If your employee can&#8217;t find a reason to want to do it, he or she may say no. So, if the employee has expressed an interest in being promoted, discuss how this project will prove valuable in achieving that goal.&#8221; </p>
<p>Other motivational incentives include networking, skill-building and long-term ease of workload. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/learn-1024x682.jpg" alt="learn" width="1024" height="682" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5142" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/learn-1024x682.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/learn-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/learn-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/learn-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/learn.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Give Employees the Freedom to Grow and Learn</h2>
<p>Now that your team is armed with stretch assignments and tasks, you can take a step back and let them work. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you are a new manager, you need to recognize that your job is now managing people, not tasks,&#8221; says <a href="http://er.educause.edu/blogs/2015/6/why-autonomy-is-important-for-peak-performance" target="_blank">Joan Cheverie at Educause</a>. </p>
<p>&#8220;This is the point where you stop telling your staff how to do their job and, instead, set the strategic direction, deadlines, and benchmarks and then allow them to determine how to accomplish the job.&#8221; </p>
<p>This fulfills your employees&#8217; need for choice and an ability to make decisions of their own volition. </p>
<p>&#8220;Effective delegation is when you give a task to someone who knows both what they have to do and how to do it how to get it done on time,&#8221; explains <a href="http://www.tonylbrown.com/best-way-to-delegate-tasks-to-my-freelancer" target="_blank">business systems strategist Tony Brown</a>. &#8220;It is giving a task to someone who can take responsibility for that task if it changes. Ineffective delegation is when you give a task to someone else and it doesn&#8217;t save you any time or money.&#8221; </p>
<p>This means managers who spend just as much time assigning, reviewing and tracking the progress of a task are failing to delegate effectively, as it&#8217;s causing them just as much stress as if they did it themselves. </p>
<p>In the same way you&#8217;re reviewing your employees whom you delegate to, you should review yourself as a manager. <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/3052984/know-it-all/four-signs-youre-micromanaging-your-employees" target="_blank">Baron Schwartz, founder and CEO of Vivid Cortex</a>, discovered he was micromanaging when he became part of the problem.</p>
<p>&#8220;Employees might put it delicately (which can make it easy to miss), but if they communicate that you&#8217;re the cause of a delay, you&#8217;re probably in too deep. &#8230; Try to take a step back and ask whether it&#8217;s a decision you should be making in the first place. Can one or more of your team members make that call just as well on their own?&#8221;</p>
<p>On the employee side, communicating any problems or issues up front can save time and frustration down the road. </p>
<p><a href="http://money.usnews.com/money/blogs/outside-voices-careers/articles/2016-01-19/how-to-handle-a-micromanaging-boss-without-getting-fired" target="_blank">Certified career coach Hallie Crawford</a> found being proactive was an important step for employees on the receiving end of micromanaging behaviors. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you notice that it happens at a certain time of day, provide your boss with an update an hour in advance of that time. When it occurs before or after a specific meeting, help prepare your manager in advance of that meeting for whatever he needs to report on.&#8221; </p>
<p>Some managers actually hope to inspire employees to reach this level of proactivity as a sign they can be left alone. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/video-1024x683.jpg" alt="video call conference chatting communication concept" width="1024" height="683" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5145" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/video-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/video-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/video-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/video-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/video.jpg 1677w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h2>Choose the Right Time to Assign Tasks</h2>
<p>Another important aspect of digital project management is knowing when to assign tasks to employees. Even if you&#8217;re just sending comments or assigning tasks before you forget them, you could cause undue stress within the team. </p>
<p><a href="https://hbr.org/2015/03/your-late-night-emails-are-hurting-your-team" target="_blank">Maura Nevel Thomas of Regain Your Time</a> wrote an article for the Harvard Business Review about communicating with employees in their off-hours: </p>
<p>&#8220;If the boss is emailing late at night or on weekends, most employees think a late night response is required — or that they&#8217;ll impress you if they respond immediately. Even if just a couple of your employees share this belief, it could spread through your whole team. … After all, everyone is looking for an edge in their career.&#8221;</p>
<p>In fact, researchers at the University of Illinois have coined the term &#8220;telepressure,&#8221; or the urge to immediately respond to work communication.</p>
<p><a href="http://time.com/3560203/stress-work-email/" target="_blank">Mandy Oaklander, health editor at TIME magazine</a>, found telepressure has long-term psychological effects on employees, including lost sleep, higher levels of burnout and health-related absences. Furthermore, she found that few employees are exempt from the pressure to respond immediately to their managers. </p>
<p>&#8220;Individual differences are only weakly associated — telepressure is a workplace problem, not a worker problem. We learn how to respond to email through our colleagues&#8217; behavior &#8230; and it&#8217;s a consequence of the social dynamics within a work environment.&#8221; </p>
<p>As a manager, it&#8217;s your job to set the tone of the workplace and let employees know that it&#8217;s OK to disengage. </p>
<p><a href="https://www.flexjobs.com/employer-blog/delegating-tips-for-remote-managers/" target="_blank">Matt Krumrie, writing for Flexjobs</a>, offers advice to managers trying to communicate with remote teams. With the rise of chat windows through Gmail, Slack and Skype, it&#8217;s easy to track your employees&#8217; availability throughout the day. However, this can be misleading. </p>
<p>&#8220;If your remote worker forgets to turn on IM in the morning, or leaves status at &#8216;away&#8217; for what seems like hours, don&#8217;t hover at that status, wondering where they are or if they are working. Sometimes, when things get busy, remote workers may step away, update their status, and come back and forget to update that status. &#8230; Trust them to do the job. Lead them to succeed.&#8221;</p>
<p>This can be difficult for remote workers in different time zones, but this respect and behavior will result in happier employees in the long run. </p>
<h2>Make Sure Your Instructions are Clear and Detailed</h2>
<p>There is a whole art to assigning new tasks to employees. Make sure you are giving the proper instructions for them to complete those tasks. Offering the right information can make the difference between successful or frustrated employees. </p>
<p><a href="https://www.tinshingle.com/blog/how-give-directions-work-right-way-aka-you-have-tell-them-where-put-parsley" target="_blank">Sabina Hitchen, co-founder of Tin Shingle</a>, was inspired by her mom — a professional chef — who taught her how to give effective directions to her staff. One key ingredient is face time. </p>
<p>&#8220;Set specific times of the day or week to stop everything else you&#8217;re doing and go through the directions and expectations for a new project. This also lets them prepare any question about said project and bring the to the meeting.&#8221; </p>
<p>This is also important for remote employees, who should be able to call into address any questions or concerns. </p>
<p><a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/advice/2015/10/21/how-delegate-freelancers-and-virtual-assistants-essay" target="_blank">KerryAnn Rockquemore, speaker on faculty development and leadership</a>, has found the same principles apply to a virtual team as in-house staff. </p>
<p>&#8220;If you know how to designate tasks, establish benchmarks and bring out the best out in people, you can find an awesome virtual team to support you.&#8221; </p>
<p>She also encourages managers to keep the lines of communication open and provide detailed feedback on performance early on. </p>
<p>&#8220;When you work with people virtually, they will have questions and need feedback. (They don&#8217;t just magically do perfect work without any guidance.) It&#8217;s far better to answer questions and over communicate up front than to be disappointed later on by an unsatisfactory outcome.&#8221;</p>
<p>Virtual success through project management software relies on many of the same principles as in-house work. Managers that respect their employees and communicate well will have an easier time than those who provide limited directions but continue to micromanage their staff. </p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
<em>©gpointstudio/123RF Stock Photo, ©kasto/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/Unsplash-242387/" target="_blank"><em>Unsplash</em></a><em>, ©rawpixel/123RF Stock Photo</em><br />
</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/delegate-effectively/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Break Down a Massive Project With an IT Task Manager</title>
		<link>/it-task-manager/</link>
					<comments>/it-task-manager/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 21:13:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Entrepreneurship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5121</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Often, your team lacks a clear process for completion and a timeline. Many of these problems can be solved, or mitigated, with an IT task manager.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Less than <a href="http://blog.capterra.com/surprising-project-management-statistics/" target="_blank">a third of all projects</a> were completed on time and on budget in 2015. While it&#8217;s common to extend deadlines — and most clients or managers expect they will have to — why is it so common for projects to run out of time and money?</p>
<p>Often, the root of all overruns is a lack of strategic planning. The team lacks clear processes for completion, backup plans, and timelines that leave room for error. Many of these problems can be solved, or at least reduced, with team task management tools.</p>
<p>Before you begin your next project, follow these steps to break out a project through your IT task manager and test how the workflow improves.</p>
<h2>Hold a Meeting to Address the Project&#8217;s Scope</h2>
<p>Whenever you take on a new project, or have an assignment looming ahead that requires multiple hands, it&#8217;s important to call a meeting to review the scope. The breakdown can either be discussed during the meeting, or the project manager can create tasks and assignments beforehand.</p>
<p>Start with a 20,000-foot view of what&#8217;s going to happen and address any challenges or concerns. Then, take a deep dive into the tasks and time required. Before your team leaves this meeting, everyone should know what is expected of them and what their due dates are.</p>
<p>Once you have an outline of what the project entails, give yourself room to fail. Use your calendar and task management tool to add hours for missed deadlines and extra items. Even if you think you&#8217;ve thought of everything, there will almost always be little details you forgot that need to get done.</p>
<p>Some teams pad their calendars with TBD tasks and schedule them in multiple departments. This way, the time is already assigned when the forgotten task comes up.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/office.jpg" alt="office" width="798" height="399" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5126" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/office.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/office-300x150.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/office-768x384.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/office-600x300.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>Meet as a Team and Individuals on a Regular Basis</h2>
<p>As you&#8217;re organizing your calendar and task management tool around a project, set up regular touch-base meetings for your team members along with a group meeting at least once a week.</p>
<p>When you meet on an individual level, go into a deep dive of what each team member is working on, what their problems are, and whether they expect to be on time. Some of these meetings will take three minutes if the project hasn&#8217;t reached them yet, but some will take almost an hour. Regardless of the time, it&#8217;s important for your team to get in the habit of meeting around a project and reporting their status.</p>
<p>The purpose of the individual meetings is to make the team meetings go smoother. No one wants to be stuck in a project meeting with nothing to say, where the focus is on an entirely different department.</p>
<p>The group meeting should cover major changes to the project that might affect the workload or timeline of several people involved, problems that address multiple departments, and major milestones hit. Remember, <a href="https://enplug.com/blog/7-surprising-internal-communications-stats" target="_blank">69% of employees</a> say they would work harder if they felt better appreciated and recognized, and this meeting is a great opportunity to celebrate your team.</p>
<h2>Create Detailed Subtasks As You Complete the Project</h2>
<p>Documentation of your time and resources needs to be part of the project scope, even if you don&#8217;t bill your clients hourly. The primary reason is education. By documenting the exact steps required and time spent on each of them, managers can see what is sucking up their employees&#8217; time and look for ways to improve it.</p>
<p>Documentation also provides insight into how well a project was planned. If an employee only has a week to complete a task and logs 60 hours to get their part done on time, the IT task manager knows to extend their deadlines on the next project. Conversely, if they&#8217;re given a week and only spend two hours working on it during a Friday afternoon, they might not need as much turnaround time.</p>
<p>Creating tasks and subtasks will also help your department when a similar project arises or you need to recreate the event next year. It&#8217;s easy to look backward through rose-colored glasses, and you could make the same mistakes year-over-year and project-over-project if you&#8217;re not writing down what is going wrong and how you plan to fix it.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/meeting.jpg" alt="meeting" width="798" height="399" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5125" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/meeting.jpg 798w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/meeting-300x150.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/meeting-768x384.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/meeting-600x300.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></p>
<h2>Require Teams to Conduct a Post-Mortem</h2>
<p>Even if the project is complete and the client has paid your company, you cannot close the book on the process until your employees create <a href="http://www.cdlib.org/cdlinfo/2010/11/17/the-project-post-mortem-a-valuable-tool-for-continuous-improvement/" target="_blank">post-project reviews</a>. Each review should address open-ended topics such as what went right and what went wrong, but they should also address concerns such as tight deadlines, bottlenecks, ambiguity in the instructions, and unexpected tasks.</p>
<p>As a manager, it&#8217;s your job to upload these individual reports into your team task management tools along with your own analysis of your team&#8217;s performance. This reflection and documentation will help you when creating tasks for the next project that comes along.</p>
<h2>Reuse Old Projects to Create New Scopes</h2>
<p>All of these project updates, comments, and reviews and completely useless if you fail to learn anything from your failures. Many calendar and task management tools allow users to copy old projects and update them with new information. This is ideal for agencies and companies that sell the same services (such as campaigns, software onboarding and training) and try to tailor them for their new clients. Our <a href="https://www.teamfocus.me/teamfocus-use-cases/workflow-sharing/">Workflow Sharing</a> makes this process incredibly easy.</p>
<p>As you share, copy and update old projects, read over the notes from your past experiences and see what changes can be made. What roadblocks did you face then that you&#8217;re not worried about now? What new roadblocks have arisen?</p>
<p>As much as the company founders and CEOs want you to immediately improve with your IT task manager, there&#8217;s a learning curve that most managers will experience when applying the new tool to their projects.</p>
<p>This is an education tool that you will use to learn why you&#8217;re failing before you can take the necessary steps reduce errors in time management, budget allocation and employee engagement. Without it, you&#8217;re taking shots in the dark and hoping your process improves.</p>
<p>Remember, hope is never a strategy.</p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
©chagin/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/tpsdave-12019/" target="_blank"><em>tpsdave</em></a><em>, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/skeeze-272447/" target="_blank"><em>skeeze</em></a><br />
</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/it-task-manager/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Experts Weigh in on Improving Company Workflow</title>
		<link>/improving-company-workflow/</link>
					<comments>/improving-company-workflow/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tfadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2016 16:15:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Workflow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Entrepreneurship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Management/HR]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.teamfocus.me/?p=5111</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It’s important to evaluate company workflow to make sure employees are making the most of their time. Follow these expert tips to improve your processes.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Teams are constantly changing, whether it&#8217;s because of a new employee, promoted manager, or corporate restructuring. While change is usually a good thing, it tends to throw off the equilibrium within a company as everyone adjusts to the new status quo.</p>
<p>For managers, it&#8217;s important to evaluate the current workflow during this time to reduce friction and make sure employees are getting the most from their time.</p>
<p>Follow these tips from our 17 experts to learn how to improve the processes within your department.</p>
<h3>Identify the Most Important Tasks for the Week</h3>
<p>Mark Twain once said, &#8220;Eat a live frog first thing in the morning and nothing worse will happen to you the rest of the day.&#8221; Many business professionals swear by this method (though not literally, usually) in their daily and weekly projects.</p>
<p>In fact, <a href="http://blog.desktime.com/2016/02/19/eat-frog-every-morning/" target="_blank">Nora Inveiss at DeskTime</a> found delaying her hardest projects drags on her during the day. &#8220;It&#8217;s hard to focus on other tasks when there&#8217;s something else in the back of your mind that&#8217;s stressing you out. Getting your most dreaded assignments out of the way first thing gives you a sense of relief, and the rest of your day will be more productive as a result.&#8221;</p>
<p>To prevent the difficult and cumbersome work from piling up on your desk while you whiz through the parts of your job that are easy, <a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/3026484/work-smart/5-ways-to-finally-stop-wasting-your-time" target="_blank">Gwen Moran at Fast Company</a> recommends analyzing your workflow to identify mission-critical tasks and extra assignments that have attached themselves to you.</p>
<p>&#8220;As you begin to see how your days typically shape up, observe what really has to be done during the course of your day and what you&#8217;re doing because it&#8217;s a habit or because someone asked you to take on a task, but it wasn&#8217;t really necessary.&#8221;</p>
<p>Once you have your top tasks, you can set your calendar for the week. <a href="http://www.inboundmarketingagents.com/inbound-marketing-agents-blog/bid/338828/5-Effective-Ways-to-Stop-Wasting-Time-at-Work" target="_blank">Bill Faeth, CEO of Inbound Marketing Agents</a>, swears by organizational calendars to lay out your tasks: &#8220;Schedule the amount of time you&#8217;d like to spend on each task and don&#8217;t deter from your plan. When you have a schedule in front of you and self-created deadlines, it will be easier for you to stay on track and fight the time-wasters that take a bite out of your productivity.&#8221;</p>
<p>Daily micro-deadlines are the easiest way to measure whether you&#8217;re accomplishing your goals. This can also be applied to employees to ensure they&#8217;re not spending too much time on projects of low importance.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/paperwork-1024x680.jpg" alt="paperwork" width="1024" height="680" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5116" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/paperwork-1024x680.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/paperwork-300x199.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/paperwork-768x510.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/paperwork-600x398.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/paperwork.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h3>Eliminate Busywork from Your Team</h3>
<p>Once you have identified the most important parts of your week, you can study the other end of the spectrum to find and remove busywork and tasks that should be automated.</p>
<p>&#8220;Developers are the first people to notice when a manual process could just be automated,&#8221; says <a href="http://blog.dwolla.com/designing-for-developers-cutting-the-busywork/" target="_blank">Melissa Cooper at Dwolla</a>. &#8220;Unfortunately, performing up-front tasks to get to the heart of what you&#8217;re trying to do is all too often part of the job. Look for moments where developers expect things to be tedious and instead wow them by removing the busy work; make the processes seamless.&#8221;</p>
<p>Along with manual processes, time traps can also drain your weekly hours. <a href="http://blog.cengage.com/three-ways-to-avoid-time-wasting-activities/" target="_blank">Tami Strang at Cengage Learning</a> offers advice for dealing with them.</p>
<p>&#8220;Manage your time traps by defining and limiting the amount of time you spend on them,&#8221; Strang says. &#8220;To keep yourself accountable, set a timer … and step away from the activity once it goes off. (No hitting snooze!)&#8221;</p>
<p>She also suggests using time traps — such as checking email or reorganizing your desk — as a reward for finishing your most important work.</p>
<p>If you&#8217;re unsure whether something is busywork, ask yourself and your employees why they do it, and what benefit it has to the company.</p>
<p>For example, <a href="https://forumone.com/ideas/no-dreams-or-busywork-designing-successful-projects" target="_blank">Michael Rader at Forum One</a> believes execution without an idea is just busywork, and advises managers to tie both concepts together to create motivated teams. &#8220;A clear understanding of your project goals helps tie what you&#8217;re doing back to what your organization as a whole is trying to accomplish.&#8221;</p>
<p>If the task helps the bottom line, it can stay, but managers should reevaluate potential automation opportunities in the future.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/training-1024x683.jpg" alt="training" width="1024" height="683" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5117" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/training-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/training-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/training-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/training-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/training.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h3>Decide What Should be Delegated</h3>
<p>The next step in your process evaluation needs to be delegation, and deciding what should be passed onto your team. Now that you&#8217;ve removed busywork from your employees, their calendars should be more open to taking some of your work.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.halogensoftware.com/blog/5-reasons-managers-need-to-delegate" target="_blank">Melany Gallant of Halogen Software</a> admits that deciding what to delegate can be a challenge, but sometimes a manager just needs to let go. &#8220;Maybe you&#8217;re concerned that things won&#8217;t be done &#8216;right&#8217; unless you do it. Ask yourself if this is a case of you wanting things done &#8216;your way&#8217; or whether your employees truly don&#8217;t have the skills to complete the task successfully. If it&#8217;s the latter, then a coaching conversation is in order.&#8221;</p>
<p>This is especially hard for managers who have built a team or department from the ground up, and now have to pass their skills onto the growing team.</p>
<p>&#8220;You have earned your position in the company because you have the skills and the experience to execute the work successfully,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.inc.com/jayson-demers/7-guidelines-for-delegating-tasks-to-employees.html" target="_blank">Jayson DeMers, founder and CEO of AudienceBloom</a>.</p>
<p>&#8220;If everybody in the company had those skills, your position wouldn&#8217;t be unique. There will be some tasks and projects that you&#8217;ll have to tackle on your own, but there should also be a set of tasks on your plate that someone else can handle.&#8221;</p>
<p>Once your employees prove they can handle the work, take a step back and let them grow.</p>
<h3>Trust Your Employees to Set Their Own Priorities</h3>
<p>As you transition the workflow of your team, let them know that you will be there to support them during the implementation process, but that they will have more freedom in the long run.</p>
<p>&#8220;Examine your workflow, and identify key areas that would benefit from greater flexibility and creative input,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/drewhendricks/2014/01/27/6-ways-to-empower-your-employees-with-transformational-leadership/#5ff5a9893268" target="_blank">Drew Hendricks, CMO at Blogpros</a>. &#8220;Sit down with your team and explain how much flexibility they will each have within a task. Don&#8217;t leave it open-ended — give them some parameters to work with so that they&#8217;re not overwhelmed with options.&#8221;</p>
<p>Flexibility and trust has been proven to increase employee engagement, which has significant financial and cultural benefits within an organization.</p>
<p><a href="http://dupress.com/articles/employee-engagement-strategies/" target="_blank">Josh Bersin, founder of Bersin by Deloitte</a>, has made it his goal to modernize how we think about employee engagement. &#8220;The first and perhaps most important part of employee engagement is job-person fit. &#8230; Despite [pressure] to improve productivity, research shows that when we enrich jobs, giving people more autonomy, decision-making power, time, and support, the company makes more money.&#8221;</p>
<p>Furthermore, failing to let your team make their own priorities will increase turnover, causing more calamity for your employees, peers, and co-workers.</p>
<p><a href="http://wheniwork.com/blog/employee-management/" target="_blank">Rob Wormley at When I Work</a> explains that constant micromanagement is more than a time waster for managers: It also causes employees to disengage. &#8220;Employees under continual gaze develop fear and resentment, and even if you can keep them productive, attitude and other issues will pop up. If you don&#8217;t trust your employees, it shows.&#8221;</p>
<p>It may seem paradoxical to engage with employees less if you want them to be more engaged, but this freedom allows them to grow and eventually step into their own managerial roles within the company.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.teamfocus.me/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/education-1024x682.jpg" alt="education" width="1024" height="682" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-5115" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/education-1024x682.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/education-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/education-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/education-600x400.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/09/education.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h3>Make Sure Knowledge is Shared Across Teams</h3>
<p>While your employees don&#8217;t need to be micromanaged, they do need your support and the right tools for the job. As a manager, you should create processes for cross-training, mentoring and knowledge sharing.</p>
<p>&#8220;Companies are suffering because individuals are having trouble accessing the knowledge they need in order to do their job,&#8221; the team at <a href="https://bloomfire.com/blog/522359-5-ways-to-encourage-knowledge-sharing-within-your-organization/" target="_blank">Bloomfire</a> says. &#8220;Not only can they not access it, sometimes the people who have that information refuses to share … [Knowledge hoarding] is a detriment to any organization. It causes distrust among employees, killing any efforts to get your team collaborating.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="https://community.dynamics.com/b/msftdynamicsblog/archive/2015/10/23/7-big-benefits-of-giving-employees-the-knowledge-they-need " target="_blank">Tricia Morris at Microsoft</a> agrees: &#8220;When different employees and different departments have or provide different answers to the same question, confusion, frustration and mistakes often result. This &#8230; is compounded when employees are operating with different information from what the public is given.&#8221;</p>
<p>At best, failure to cross-train your employees leads to confusion and frustration. At worst, it leaves your company completely in the lurch when someone quits.</p>
<p>&#8220;Certain practices that are critical to your business may be the responsibility of a single employee,&#8221; says the team at <a href="https://www.paychex.com/articles/human-resources/building-employee-confidence-productivty-through-knowledge-management" target="_blank">Paychex</a>. &#8220;Should that employee and their knowledge be removed from the workplace, productivity (and profitability) can come to a grinding halt.&#8221;</p>
<p>Even if they&#8217;re taking a vacation or out sick for a day, the whole process can be interrupted until their knowledge and skillset returns.</p>
<h3>Create a Culture of Collaboration and Teamwork</h3>
<p>Once your workflow is restructured and your team is fully onboarded to the new process, it&#8217;s the role of management to create an environment where the team can thrive.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.partnersinleadership.com/insights-publications/responsibility-vs-accountability/" target="_blank">Tracy Skousen, writing for Partners in Leadership</a>, recommends letting employees know that it&#8217;s OK to fail in order to prevent a culture where peers throw each other under the bus. &#8220;Justifying the way you think and act in an effort to &#8216;cover your tail&#8217; pulls in the opposite direction of achieving results — often sapping time and resources to the detriment of others or the organization.&#8221; It also hinders risk-taking in the future, which will hold the company back.</p>
<p>Another way to create a collaborative culture is to create education hubs that let employees highlight skills through training.</p>
<p>&#8220;Ensure that employees have several methods of sharing their information,&#8221; says <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/kenny-kline/how-to-harness-employee-knowledge-at-your-company_b_8830704.html" target="_blank">Entrepreneur Kenny Kline</a>. &#8220;Each employee will have different passions and different strengths. If you force every employee to share their knowledge through the same channels, you will end up discouraging them from sharing.&#8221;</p>
<p>For example, some employees love public speaking while others hate it. Only a small part of your team will volunteer if you turn cross-training into an oral exercise.</p>
<p>The final key for employee collaboration is finding the right tools for the job. <a href="http://blog.namely.com/blog/2014/10/20/9-surprising-ways-to-improve-daily-workflow" target="_blank">Matt Straz, founder &amp; CEO of Namely</a>, recommends silencing email in favor of more productive collaboration software.</p>
<p>&#8220;Studies show email isn&#8217;t as effective of a collaboration tool as it used to be,&#8221; he says. &#8220;In fact, employees are interrupted by email every five minutes, slowing down productivity. It&#8217;s becoming more expensive and is a poor channel of communication for immediate decisions.&#8221;</p>
<p>There are two main tracks that all managers have to explore when improving their workflow:</p>
<ul>
<li>They have to prioritize and remove tasks to make sure their employees are doing the most impactful work possible,</li>
<li>and they have to provide teams with the right environment and tools to succeed.</li>
</ul>
<p>When these two elements are balanced, highly-engaged teams can perform at optimal levels, personally and professionally.</p>
<p>&nbsp;<br />
<small><br />
<em>Images by:</em><br />
©rawpixel/123RF Stock Photo, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/Unsplash-242387/" target="_blank"><em>Unsplash</em></a><em>, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/weinstock-25534/" target="_blank"><em>weinstock</em></a><em>, </em><a href="https://pixabay.com/en/users/jill111-334088/" target="_blank"><em>jill111</em></a><br />
</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/improving-company-workflow/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
